[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Quality is ______ variability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) opposite of",
            "b) proportional to",
            "c) reciprocal of",
            "d) synonym of"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quality is defined as the fitness of a product for use. In normal circumstances, the fitness of a product for use increases with a reduction in variability. So, Quality is reciprocal of Variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which one of these is a dimension of quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Performance",
            "b) Hazard rate",
            "c) Process Capability",
            "d) Control limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Performance is a key component of quality. Hence, it is counted in the dimensions of quality by Garvin (1987)."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Performance of a product is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) how long the product lasts",
            "b) how easy it is to repair the product",
            "c) how often the product fails",
            "d) whether the product is capable of doing the intended job"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Performance of a manufactured product is defined as the capability of a product to do the job, for which it is designed."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which one of these is not a component of quality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reliability",
            "b) Durability",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Serviceability"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 8 components of quality which include reliability, durability, and serviceability. Acceptance sampling is not one of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "How is the aesthetics of a product defined as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) How good the product performs its job",
            "b) How good it looks",
            "c) How fast the job of the product is completed",
            "d) Whether the product is made exactly as the designer intended"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The visual appeal of the product is regarded as the aesthetics of the product. The looking of a product is the aesthetic dimension of quality."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What does reduced variability result in?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased failure rate",
            "b) Decreased reliability",
            "c) Fewer repair claims",
            "d) Increased repair costs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reduction in variability removes harmful differences between product units. This means fewer failures, hence lesser repair claims."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Quality of a product is at its lowest when ____ quality component is neglected while it’s manufacturing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) performance",
            "b) reliability",
            "c) aesthetics",
            "d) serviceability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a product does not carry out its job efficiently (performance), it will be of no use. So performance is a key factor of quality of any product."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Quality characteristics are classified into variables and ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) constants",
            "b) attributes",
            "c) standards",
            "d) specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Quality characteristics are broadly divided into two parts. Variables and Attributes are the two parts of Quality characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which one of these is physical CTQ characteristic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length",
            "b) Appearance",
            "c) Reliability",
            "d) Color"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Variable can only take continuous values. Attributes can only take discrete values. Plus, variables are independent of attributes.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "What does CTQ characteristic mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Close to quality characteristic",
            "b) Comparison to quality characteristic",
            "c) Consumer to quality characteristic",
            "d) Critical to quality characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Length is a physical CTQ characteristic, whereas appearance and color are sensory CTQ characteristics. Reliability is a Time-Orientation CTQ characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Specifications are defined as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) desired measurements of CTQ characteristics of whole product",
            "b) actual measurements of CTQ characteristic of whole product",
            "c) difference from desired measurements of CTQ characteristic of the components of product",
            "d) desired measurements of CTQ characteristics of the product components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CTQ characteristic is termed as Critical to Quality characteristics. All the other options are not any relevance to Statistical Quality Control."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Length of a rectangular box is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) a continuous measurement, i.e. a variable",
            "b) a discrete measurement, i.e. an attribute",
            "c) a continuous measurement, i.e. an attribute",
            "d) a discrete measurement, i.e. a variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For any manufactured product, the specifications are the desired measurements for the quality characteristics of the components, which make up the product."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "What is the “value of a measurement that corresponds to the desired value for that quality characteristic” called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nominal value",
            "b) USL value",
            "c) LSL value",
            "d) Original value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A target or desired value, for a product component to be manufactured, is said to be the Nominal value, which is lower than USL and higher than LSL."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "USL is defined as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) the highest positive allowable difference from the nominal value of a CTQ characteristic",
            "b) the highest allowable value of a CTQ characteristic",
            "c) the lowest difference between the highest allowable value and the nominal value of a CTQ characteristic",
            "d) the highest difference between the highest allowable value and the lowest allowable value of a CTQ characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: USL is defined as the highest tolerable value of a Critical-to-Quality characteristic. There is no mention of difference in the definition of USL."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Full form of LSL is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) lowest safe limit",
            "b) largest safe limit",
            "c) lowest specification limit",
            "d) lowest specified limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The smallest permissible value of a particular quality characteristic is described as the lowest specification limit or LSL of that particular quality characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Nonconformity is described as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) a client not confirming a product deal",
            "b) a defect in manufacturing process",
            "c) a difference from the Nominal value of a specification",
            "d) a specific type of failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nonconforming products are defined as the products, which fail to meet one or more of its specifications. Nonconformity is defined as a specific type of failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Who gave the principles of “Scientific Management”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Henry Ford",
            "b) Mayo",
            "c) Fayol",
            "d) F. W. Taylor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The principles of “Scientific Management” were given by Frederick W. Taylor, in the year of 1875. This affected the production standards the most."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Who introduced the Assembly Line concept?",
        "Options": [
            "a) W.S. Gosset",
            "b) Henry Ford",
            "c) R.A. Fisher",
            "d) A.V. Feigenbaum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The concept of assembly line was first introduced by Henry Ford. This refined the work methods. The goal of this concept was to improve productivity and quality."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Who was the man who first introduced the concept of Control charts in the arena of quality control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frank Gilbreth",
            "b) Henry Grant",
            "c) W. A. Shewhart",
            "d) G. Taguchi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1924, W. A. Shewhart introduced the control chart concept in a Bell Laboratories technical memorandum. This was an avant-garde step that made the producers thinking to improve their quality standards to the modern world. "
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Acceptance sampling methodology was first developed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) H. F. Dodge and H. G. Romig",
            "b) Motorola",
            "c) U.S. War department",
            "d) W. E. Deming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1928, acceptance sampling methodology was developed and introduced by H. F. Dodge and H. G. Romig at Bell Laboratories."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "By whom was Six-sigma methodology first developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motorola",
            "b) Bell Laboratories",
            "c) Ford Motors",
            "d) The ministry of Supply Advising Service on Statistical methods and Quality Control, UK"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Motorola developed Six-Sigma technique, and started implementing the initiative, after the year of 1987."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "When was first ISO quality system standards published?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1977",
            "b) 1989",
            "c) 1987",
            "d) 1981"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the year of 1987, ISO published its first quality system criterion was published. The goal of these was to improve quality system standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "What does ASQC stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All-India Standards for Quality Control",
            "b) Attribute Specified Quality Control",
            "c) American Society for Quality Control",
            "d) All-India Society for Quality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ASQC stands for American Society for Quality Control, formed in 1946. This organization promotes the use of quality improvement techniques, used in all kinds of production industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "There are two types of inputs to a process besides the raw material. That are controllable inputs and _____ inputs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) noise",
            "b) voice",
            "c) monitoring",
            "d) service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 3 types of input to every process viz. raw materials, controllable inputs and uncontrollable inputs. Uncontrollable inputs are also called Noise inputs."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "In the low level of maturity of any organization, the technique of quality improvement that is used the most is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) acceptance sampling",
            "b) statistical process control",
            "c) design of experiments",
            "d) regression analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In early stage of any organization, the quality knowledge to management is negligible. So acceptance sampling is chosen to get the highest level of it."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "In the Factorial design type of design of experiments, which of these points are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controlling noise factors",
            "b) Outgoing inspection",
            "c) Incoming inspection",
            "d) Testing outputs of all possible combination of factor levels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We cannot control noise factors. In factorial design, factors are varied together, in such a way that all possible combination of factor levels is tested."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Factorial design is a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) off-line quality control tool",
            "b) on-Line quality control tool",
            "c) in-process procedure",
            "d) redundancy plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Off-line quality control means, quality control before process starts. Factorial design is implemented before process starting, so it is an off-line quality control tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Control chart is a useful ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) manufacturing process",
            "b) process monitoring technique",
            "c) off-line quality control tool",
            "d) part of acceptance sampling techniques"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Control chart is a very useful part of process monitoring tool, as it can only give information if the process is going out of control."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of feedback control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engineering control",
            "b) Automatic control",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Routine adjustment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process variables are adjusted as needed, to get the output process characteristics on target value. This routine adjustment is called Engineering control or feedback control."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The highest reduction in the variability from one unit of product to other can be obtained by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) statistical process control",
            "b) acceptance Sampling",
            "c) design of Experiments",
            "d) design of Experiments with automatic control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Design of experiments gives the highest reduction in variability. When it is combined with automatic components, the variability reduces even more."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Quality assurance is related to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) strategic activities to ensure the financial plans",
            "b) set of activities that ensures that the services and product meet the requirements",
            "c) set of activities that ensures that the supplier-customer quality issues are properly resolved",
            "d) set of activities that include inspection and planning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quality assurance is the set of activities, that ensure the quality levels of products and services are properly maintained, and the supplier-customer relations are good."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not based on Deming’s points?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Focus on continuous improvement",
            "b) An ongoing program of education of employees is necessary",
            "c) Reach the slogans and numerical goals for the workplace",
            "d) Elimination of numerical quotas and work standards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Inspection identifies defects at the instant when the producer has already paid to make them. So we cannot rely on mass inspection as it costs much."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "How many points did Deming give to elaborate methods for quality improvement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 23",
            "d) 14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Deming, a goal of zero defects is useless, without any plan for the achievement of the goal like this. These slogans are usually counterproductive."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which of these is not the part of Deming’s 7 diseases of Management?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lack of constancy of purpose",
            "b) Emphasis on short-term profits",
            "c) Emphasis on Long term profits",
            "d) Mobility of top management"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: W. Edwards Deming has summarized his philosophy of quality improvement, in the set of several points for management to work on. There are total 14 points in it."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Mobility of top management is described as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) constant improvement of processes",
            "b) management by visible figures alone",
            "c) performance reviews on the basis of short-term performance",
            "d) manager not taking important decisions about business"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Long term profits give higher chances of survival of business. So it is not among the 7 diseases of management."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Lack of constancy of purpose means ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) low short term profits",
            "b) low long term profits",
            "c) inferior strategically planning about the continuous improvement",
            "d) lack of investment planning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mobility of top management is described as widespread practice of job-hopping; that is manager spending lesser time for the current job, and more time on the next career move of his/her."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "PDSA is expanded as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plan-Define-Study-Analyze",
            "b) Plan-Define-Study-Act",
            "c) Plan-Do-Study-Act",
            "d) Plan-Do-Study-Analyze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PDSA cycle is termed as Plan-Do-Study-Act cycle. Sometimes, study step is called check step. So, PDSA cycle becomes PDCA cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of Juran Trilogy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planning",
            "b) Control",
            "c)  Check",
            "d) Improvement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Juran Trilogy consists of 3 points viz. planning, control, improvement. The check step is not included in the Juran trilogy."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "According to Armand V. Feigenbaum, Which of these is not the 3 tools of Quality improvement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quality leadership",
            "b) Quality Technology",
            "c) Organizational commitment",
            "d) Quality commitment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Feigenbaum, the 3 tools of quality improvement are Quality leadership, quality technology, and organizational commitment."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "ISO was founded in the year of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1943",
            "b) 1946",
            "c) 1949",
            "d) 1956"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ISO was founded in the year of 1946 in Geneva, Switzerland for development of standards for quality systems. It issued its first standards in 1987."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The Malcolm Baldrige National Quality Award was created by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) U.S. Congress",
            "b) British Government",
            "c) ISO",
            "d) ASQ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Malcolm Baldrige National Quality Award was created by U.S. Congress in 1987. It is given to recognize U.S. organizations for performance excellence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "In 3-σ quality performance, the probability of producing a conforming product is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.9973",
            "b) 0.9500",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0.9467"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 3-σ quality performance, the probability of getting a product, conforming to standards, is exactly 0.9973 which is almost 2700ppm defective. "
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Using 3 sigma quality performances, we get 2700 products produced which are nonconforming. If we operate on the 3- σ performance, and we produce 100 independent product components, what is the probability of finding a product not defective?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  0.7891",
            "b) 0.27",
            "c) 0.7631",
            "d)  0.007631"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Probability of finding an single product not defective= 1- (2700/1,000,000) = 1 – 0.0027= 0.9973\nProbability of finding a single product not defective chosen from 100 independent product components\n= 0.9973 x 0.9973 x 0.9973 x … x 0.9973 = 0.9973100 = 0.7631. "
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "For any stable process, if the process follows 6 – sigma quality performance, how many products it will produce defective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.9946 ppm",
            "b) 3.4000 ppm",
            "c) 1200 ppm",
            "d) 934 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By reaching till the level of six-sigma quality level,  we get almost 3.4 ppm defective products."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "If the value-add time for a process is 10% of the process cycle time, what will be the PCE or Process Cycle efficiency of the mentioned process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 12%",
            "c) 23%",
            "d) 14%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the process behavior is variable, the process performance will vary accordingly. So, process performance can only be predicted when process is stable."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Consider a mortgage refinance operation at a bank. If the average completion rate for submitted applications is 100 completions per day, and there are 1500 applications waiting for processing, the process cycle time is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 hrs",
            "b) 15 days",
            "c) 150 days",
            "d) 15.33 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PCE= Value-add time / Process Cycle Time = 10% Process cycle time / Process cycle time = 10%."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of these is an appraisal cost?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inspection and testing of incoming material",
            "b) New product review",
            "c) Complaint adjustment",
            "d) Rework"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Process Cycle Time = Work-in-progress / Average completion rate = 1500/100 = 15 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which one of them is an External failure cost?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burn-in",
            "b) Materials and the services consumed",
            "c) Scrap",
            "d) Indirect costs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Appraisal costs are the costs, which are associated with measuring, evaluating, or auditing products, and purchased material, to insure the conformance to standards that have been imposed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Failure analysis is a ______ cost.",
        "Options": [
            "a) prevention cost",
            "b) internal failure cost",
            "c) appraisal cost",
            "d) external failure cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: External failure costs are the costs occurring when the product does not perform satisfactorily after it is delivered to customers. Indirect cost is one of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "DMAIC stands for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Do-Measure-Act-Implement-Check",
            "b) Define-Measure-Act-Implement-Control",
            "c) Define-Measure-Analyze-Improve-Control",
            "d) Do-Measure-Analyze-Improve-Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DMAIC is a problem solving process. It is a collection of 5 steps. D stands for Define, M stands for Measure, A stands for Analyze, I stands for Improve and C stands for control. "
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "What DMAIC process does is, to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manufacture any product",
            "b) Define specification limits for a product",
            "c) Solve root cause of quality and process problems",
            "d) Define quality system standards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DMAIC is a problem solving tool. Hence, its main objective is to find root causes of problems in a process, which create variability. It attempts to remove those root origins."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of the Define step of DMAIC process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Verify and gain approval for final solutions",
            "b) Define critical customer requirements",
            "c) Establish project charter and build team",
            "d) Document process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Define step of DMAIC, which consists of identifying or validating the improvement opportunity, knowing customer requirements, mapping process, and establishing project charter."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "DMAIC is often associated with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Six-sigma activities",
            "b) Kaizen board",
            "c) 5-s",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DMAIC is often associated with six-sigma activities. The main objective of this is to give the maximum output with good quality. Almost all six-sigma implementation use DMAIC PSP for project management and completion."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "PSP is expanded as ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Problem Solving Process",
            "b) Product safeguarding process",
            "c) Product Sampling Process",
            "d) Project Settling Procedure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PSP is expanded as Problem Solving Process. There are many types of PSP’s available. DMAIC PSP is one of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The Cause and Defect Diagram is a part of _____ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Analyze",
            "c) Control",
            "d) Measure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cause and defect diagram is an diagram which shows defects in a product, and the corresponding cause for it. This is counted in the Measure step of DMAIC."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Tollgate reviews are presented to managers and “owner” of a process __________ in the six-sigma organizations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The project champions and the black belts not working directly on the project",
            "b) Industrial engineering team",
            "c) Quality control manager",
            "d) Developers of the factory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tollgate reviews are the reviews of a report developed by the project team. In a six sigma organization, the project champion and the black belts also review this report, besides the manager and the owner."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "DFSS refers to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Development of Six-Sigma",
            "b) Design for Six-Sigma",
            "c) Define for Six-Sigma",
            "d) Development for Six-Sigma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the original process is operating very badly, or if there is a new product or service is required, then the Improvement step of DMAIC process actually becomes Design step."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Tollgate reviews are done _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before each step of DMAIC",
            "b) After DMAIC process ending",
            "c) Before the whole DMAIC process",
            "d) After each step of DMAIC process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a six-sigma organization, when it is determined that a new product is required, the improve step in DMAIC becomes Design step. This is sometimes called, Design for Six-Sigma."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Process capability tests are a part of _____ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Improvement",
            "c) Measure",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tollgate reviews are done after each step of DMAIC process. They contain a review by the manager and owner, of a report of the step which is developed by the project team. This offers evaluation of the work of the team."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "A DMAIC process is implemented on a process only when ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are signs of potential breakthrough",
            "b) It is estimated that quality of products will decrease in near future",
            "c) Exceptionally bad quality review of a product",
            "d) When the project impact of DMAIC is estimated low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Measure step contains the evaluation of the current state of the production process.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Projects with high potential negative impact are _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Most desirable",
            "b) Least desirable",
            "c) Having highest risk",
            "d) Have a low risk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DMAIC process is put into practice only when there are chances of improvement in the final quality of product/service. This improvement or potential change is measured on the basis of financial improvement."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "In SIPOC diagram, P stands for  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process",
            "b) Product",
            "c) Progress",
            "d) Profit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Projects which have a chance of positive impact on the final product quality are most suitable for DMAIC application. But if the impact is predicted negative, they become the least desirable of all projects."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Input is defined as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Material provided to a process",
            "b) Changes made to controllable variables",
            "c) Development of in the process",
            "d) Desired product specification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The input to a process is defined as the material and the information provided to a process, before it starts producing any product. This is an important factor to the quality of the product."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "KPIV’s and KPOV’s are measured in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define step",
            "b) Measure step",
            "c) In both Define and Measure step",
            "d) Improve step"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: KPIV’s and KPOV’s are the variables, which matter the most on the output of a process. They are identified at least tentatively in the define step, and mostly identified during the measure step."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "A gauge repeatability and reproducibility study can also be said _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formal gauge capability",
            "b) Gauge metrology",
            "c) Gauge potential",
            "d) Gauge capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For evaluation of current state of the process, we need to find the process capability. This is found via using formal gauge capability study, which is also called gauge repeatability and reproducibility study. "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Repeatability is defined as ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repeating ability of a process to give almost same products in short interval of time",
            "b) Repeating ability of a measuring instrument to give almost same measurement in short interval of time",
            "c) Repeating ability of a process to give almost same products in long interval of time",
            "d) Repeating ability of a measuring instrument to give almost same measurement in long interval of time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Repeatability is generally described as, “The ability of a measuring instrument, to give almost or exactly same measurement of one dimension of an object, when the measuring person and the outer conditions are same.”"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of these is not necessary in a tollgate report after measure step of DMAIC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A list of identified KPIV’s and KPOV’s",
            "b) Measurement system capability",
            "c) SIPOC diagram",
            "d) Assumptions made during the data collection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a tollgate review, all the important things used in measure step like KPIV’s and KPOV’s, capability of measurement system, and the assumptions made during the data collection etc are listed. SIPOC is the part of define step."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "“The data collected in measure step may have a reference from the historical records.” Which of these options is correct bearing the above statement in mind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data from the historical records is satisfactory",
            "b) Data from the historical records may not always be satisfactory",
            "c) Data must always be collected only from historical records",
            "d) Historical records are most reliable for data collection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement says we can only have a reference from historical records, but we cannot always rely on it. This is because history may be incomplete or the methods of record keeping may have changed."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "RPN stands for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reliability priority number",
            "b) Risk priority number",
            "c) Recalled precautions number",
            "d) Reliability precautions number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The scores of the 3 criteria of the FMEA give information about variability, failure, and error score. They are multiplied together to find the RPN(Risk Priority Number)."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "In FMEA, M stands for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modes",
            "b) Measurement",
            "c) Manufacture",
            "d) Material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: FMEA is expanded as Failure Modes and Effect Analysis which is used as a very important tool during measurements of Measure step of DMAIC."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "The 3 criterion for FMEA are scored on _____ scale.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 to 1",
            "b) 0 to 100",
            "c) 0 to 10",
            "d) 0 to 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 3 criterion for FMEA are scored between o and 10. 0 stands for least possible and 10 stands for highest possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Which one of these is not a part of the 3 criteria for FMEA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Likelihood of a process going wrong",
            "b) Ability of detecting a failure",
            "c) Cause for a failure",
            "d) The severity of a failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 3 criteria for FMEA (Failure Modes and Effect Analysis) are the likelihood that something will go wrong, the ability to detect a failure, and the severity of a failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of tollgate review after Improve step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adequate documentation of how the solution was obtained",
            "b) Documentation on alternative solutions that were considered",
            "c) Complete results of pilot tests",
            "d) Results of FMEA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tollgate review after Improve step includes documentation about the appropriate solution and other alternative solutions considered, and the results of pilot tests, whereas, results of FMEA are part of the Measure step tollgate review. "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Pilot tests and mistake proofing are parts of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measure step",
            "b) Define step",
            "c) Improve step",
            "d) Analyze step"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mistake proofing is done to ensure the process improvement method is correct. Pilot test is also a form of confirmation experiment. So they both are included in Improve step of DMAIC."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Regression analysis and other multivariate methods are a part of which step of DMAIC process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Analyze",
            "c) Improve",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There may be chances of potential improvement in the six-sigma systems also. So, it cannot be predicted that six-sigma systems do not require DMAIC process at all. "
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a tool to describe variation in product units?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The box plot",
            "b) The histogram",
            "c) Stem-and-Leaf plot",
            "d) Acceptance Sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The box plot, the histogram, and the Stem-and-Leaf plot, all are used to illustrate variation among the product units. But, Acceptance sampling cannot be used to describe variation as; it is not a variation describing tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Descriptive statistics is used _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) To develop information regarding the product sample using the measured data",
            "b) To measure the data for a sample",
            "c) To draw conclusions about the population",
            "d) To control the variation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Descriptive statistics is used to show how simple graphical and numerical techniques can be used, to summarize the information about the product. The evaluation of this information is done, by using Statistical Inference."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of these shows the ordered Stem-and-Leaf Plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stems arranged by magnitude",
            "b) Stems not arranged by magnitude",
            "c) Stems and the leaves, both arranged by magnitude",
            "d) Neither stems nor leaves are arranged by magnitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  A Stem-and-Leaf plot is said to be ordered if it has its leaves arranged by magnitude. If it has stems also arranged with leaves, it surely is the ordered Stem-and-Leaf plot."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "The median for an odd number of observations is _________ where n is the number of observations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) [(n-1)/2 + 1] rank on the ascending order of observations",
            "b) [(n+1)/2 + 1] rank on the ascending order of observations",
            "c) Average of [(n+1) / 2] and (n/2) rank on the ascending order of observations",
            "d) (n/2) rank on the ascending order of observations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Median is the fiftieth percentile of the data distribution. For the odd number of observations (n), the median is [(n-1)/2 + 1] rank on the ascending order of observations. This can also be written as [(n+1)/2] rank on the ascending order of observations."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "For even number of observations of a data distribution, what is the median?",
        "Options": [
            "a) [(n-1)/2 + 1] rank on the ascending order of observations",
            "b) (n/2) rank on the ascending order of observations",
            "c) Average of (n/2)th  observation and (n/2 + 1)th observation",
            "d) Average of [(n+1) / 2] and (n/2) rank on the ascending order of observations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For even number of observation (n) of a data variation, the median is Average of (n/2)th  observation, and (n/2 + 1)th observation. This is because median of a data distribution is the fiftieth percentile of the data distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "IQR is defined as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) difference between fourth and first quartile",
            "b) difference between fourth and third quartile",
            "c) difference between third and first quartile",
            "d) difference between second and first quartile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IQR is expanded as interquartile range. It is defined as the difference between third and first quartile. IQR = Q3-Q1; where Q1 = First Quartile; Q3 = Third Quartile."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "In stem-and-leaf plot, the measure of variability is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IQR",
            "b) Mean",
            "c) Median",
            "d) Third quartile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IQR is the interquartile range, which is equal to the value of difference between third and first quartile. It is used as a measure of variability, in the case of stem-and-leaf plot."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of these, does not take time order of observations into account?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time series plot",
            "b) Run chart",
            "c) Marginal plot",
            "d) Stem-and-leaf plot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Although Stem-and-leaf plot is an excellent way to visually show the variability in the observations. But it does not take time order of observations into account. So, time series plot or marginal plot or run chart is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of these is not the name of the intervals created for the construction of the histogram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class intervals",
            "b) Cells",
            "c) Bins",
            "d) Boxes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To construct histogram for continuous data, we must divide the range of the data into intervals, which are usually called class intervals, cells, or bins."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "For a set of data having 100 observations, how many bins must be created for satisfactory results of histogram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 28",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bin number, in the case of creating a histogram, must be between 5 and 20, to give satisfactory results. If we choose no. of bins approx. equal to the square root of the number of observations, it results well. √n=√100=10"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Relative frequency is defined as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) difference of frequency of an observation from the highest one",
            "b) frequency of an observation",
            "c) highest known frequency among all frequencies of the data",
            "d) frequencies of each bin divided by the number of observations (n)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The histogram is a plot between the frequency of an observation in a data, and the bins of data created. But, the box plot is a graphical display that simultaneously displays many features of data, like variability and departure from symmetry."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Cumulative frequency plot is defined as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) height of each bar less than or equal to upper limit of bin",
            "b) height of each bar more than or equal to upper limit of bin",
            "c) height of each bar less than or equal to lower limit of bin",
            "d) height of each bar more than or equal to upper limit of bin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Relative frequencies are defined as the frequencies of each bin of the histogram, divided by the total number of observations (n) in the data. They are shown on vertical scale of histogram."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of these give an expression for the mean of a discrete distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\( \\int_{-\\infty}^{\\infty} xf(x)dx\\) ",
            "b) \\( \\sum_{i=1}^{\\infty} x_i p(x_i)\\) ",
            "c) \\( \\sum_{i=1}^{\\infty} (x-\\mu)^2 p(x_i)\\) ",
            "d) \\( \\int_{-\\infty}^{\\infty} (x-\\mu)^2 f(x)dx\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Increasing frequency plot or Cumulative frequency plot is defined as, the histogram in which, the height of each bar is less than or equal to upper limit of the bin or class interval."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "The most important measure of central tendency in a sample is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample Average",
            "b) Sample variance",
            "c) Frequency of highest observation",
            "d) Frequency of lowest observation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a sample data of n observations, sample average is the most important measure of central tendency. It is arithmetic mean of all the observations of the sample data."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of these is called the center of mass of the sample data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample variance",
            "b) Median of the data",
            "c) Arithmetic mean of the data",
            "d) The number having the highest frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The histogram exactly “balances” at the point of the sample average, which is arithmetic mean of the whole data. So it is called the center of mass of the data."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The variability in the sample data is measured by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample Data",
            "b) Sample mean",
            "c) Sample variance",
            "d) Range of data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sample variance is the measure of the variability of the sample data, because it shows deviation of the observations from the mean of the data."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The sample mean/average of the data is expressed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\( \\sum_0^n x_i \\div n \\) ",
            "b) \\( \\sum_0^{n-1} x_i \\div (n-1) \\) ",
            "c) \\( \\sum_1^{n-1} x_i \\div (n-1) \\) ",
            "d) \\( \\sum_{i=1}^n x_i \\div n \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mean of a sample data with n number of observations is expressed by,\n\\( \\overline{x} = \\sum_{i=1}^n x_i \\div n \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the expression/inequality is always true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\( \\overline{x} = s\\) ",
            "b) sample standard deviation = \\(\\sqrt{Sample \\,Variance}\\) ",
            "c) sample standard deviation > sample variance",
            "d) \\( \\overline{x} = s^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sample variance is always the square of the sample standard deviation. This clarifies that,\nsample standard deviation = \\(\\sqrt{Sample \\,Variance}\\).  "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The standard deviation of the data is expressed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(s = \\left\\{\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i – \\overline{x})^2}{n}\\right\\}^{1/2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(s = \\left\\{\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i – \\overline{x})^2}{n-1}\\right\\}^{1/2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(s = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i – \\overline{x})^2}{n-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(s = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i – \\overline{x})^2}{n}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The data sample standard deviation is expressed as,\n\\(s = \\left\\{\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i – \\overline{x})^2}{n-1}\\right\\}^{1/2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Which of these cannot be displayed by the box plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Location or central tendency",
            "b) Spread",
            "c) Departure from symmetry",
            "d) Mean of the data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard deviation of a sample data is the square root of the sample variance. As variance is also calculated with respect to the mean, the above statement is true."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Line at the either end of the box plot shows the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extreme values",
            "b) First quartile",
            "c) Third quartile",
            "d) Median"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although sample variance is the square of sample standard deviation, but it can never be predicted that it will always be greater than or equal to the sample standard deviation. For example, for S.D. = 0.2, Variance = 0.04."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Probability distribution relates the value of a variable to ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its frequency",
            "b) Its probability of occurrence",
            "c) Random variable",
            "d) Probability of occurrence of values other than that"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The box plot graphically displays simultaneously several features of data, such as location, spread/variability, departure from symmetry, and identification of outliers."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of these statements give exact definition of a random variable?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  A random value from the set of integers",
            "b) A random value from the set of natural numbers",
            "c) A random value from the set of whole numbers which can take many values",
            "d) A variable which takes on different values in population according to some random mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A line at the either end of the box of the box plot shows the extreme values, i.e. maximum and minimum values. This line is also called whisker, bases on what, the box plot is also called box and whisker plot. "
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of these gives a correct definition of continuous distributions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probability distribution of the variable being measured which takes on random values",
            "b) Probability distribution of the variable being measured which takes on values dependent over a calculated mechanism",
            "c) Probability distribution of the variable which takes some certain values such as integers",
            "d) Probability distribution of the variable being measured that takes values on continuous scale"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Probability distribution is a mathematical model, which relates the value of the variable with the probability of occurrence of that value in the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which of these expressions is correctly describing a continuous distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P(x=xi)=1-P(x≠xi)",
            "b) P{a≤x≤b} = \\(\\int_a^b f(x)dx\\) ",
            "c) P{x=xi}=p(xi)",
            "d) P(x=xi)≤1-p(x≠xi)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A random variable is generally described as a variable, which can take different values in population, i.e. the set of data, and follows no calculated mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of these give an expression for the mean of a continuous distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\( \\int_{-\\infty}^{\\infty} xf(x)dx\\) ",
            "b) \\( \\sum_{i=1}^{\\infty} x_i p(x_i)\\) ",
            "c) \\( \\sum_{i=1}^{\\infty} (x-\\mu)^2 f(x)dx\\) ",
            "d) \\( \\int_{-\\infty}^{\\infty} (x-\\mu)^2 p(x_i)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the parameter being measured can be expressed only on a continuous scale, its probability distribution is called a continuous distribution. E.g. length of a chip."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What will be the variance of the sample following hyper geometric distribution and having 5 items defective in 100 lot items, if 10 samples are taken without replacement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.431818",
            "b) 0.410023",
            "c) 0.483838",
            "d) 0.568898"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: variance of hyper geometric distribution is given by,\n\\(\\sigma^2 = \\frac{nD}{N} (1-\\frac{D}{n})(\\frac{N-n}{N-1})\\)\nPutting, N=100, n=10, D=5; we get variance=0.431818."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "For a Poisson distribution, parameter λ is having a value of 7. What is the variance for the distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.64",
            "b) 2.78",
            "c)  7",
            "d) 14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the Poisson probability distribution, the variance is equal to the parameter λ of the probability distribution. So for the above stated distribution, the variance will be equal to 7."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "For 9 Bernoulli trials, what will be the mean of trials when the probability of failure is 0.56?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.04",
            "b) 1.74",
            "c) 3.96",
            "d) 2.82"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For n=9 and probability of failure=0.56, we get probability of success;\n p = 1 – 0.56 = 0.44.\nUsing this, we get;\nmean= np=9*0.44=3.96."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "In sample fraction defective, the   ̂ symbol represents that ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) p ̂  is an estimate of the true value of binomial parameter p",
            "b) It is the “raised to power” operator",
            "c) It is having no significance",
            "d) It is the true value of binomial parameter p"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The   ̂ symbol represents the estimate of the true, unknown value of the binomial parameter p.p is the value of sample fraction defective or sample fraction nonconforming."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "For a Pascal distribution, the probability of occurrence of a event x is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(p(x)=\\left(x-1 \\atop r-1\\right) p^x (1-p)^{x-r}\\) ",
            "b) \\(p(x)=\\left(r-1 \\atop x-1\\right) p^x (1-p)^{x-r}\\) ",
            "c) \\(p(x)=\\left(x-1 \\atop r-1\\right) p^x (1-p)^{1-r}\\) ",
            "d) \\(p(x)=\\left(x-1 \\atop r-1\\right) p^x (1-p)^{x-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The Pascal probability distribution is given by the following equation,\n\\(p(x)=\\left(x-1 \\atop r-1\\right) p^x (1-p)^{x-r}\\) \nWhere x=r, r+1, r+2… and r≥1 is an integer."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "When is Pascal distribution, called negative binomial distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When r>0 but not necessarily an integer",
            "b) When r<0 but an integer",
            "c) When r>3 and an integer",
            "d) When r=0 and an integer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When in a Pascal probability distribution, r is greater than 0 but not necessarily an integer, the Pascal distribution is called, negative binomial distribution. This is a special case of Pascal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "When r=1 in a Pascal distribution, what is this case called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Negative binomial distribution",
            "b) Positive binomial distribution",
            "c) Hyper geometric distribution",
            "d) Geometric distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The special case of Pascal distribution when r=1, we get geometric distribution. This represents the number of Bernoulli trials until the first success occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the expression represents the mean of Pascal distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) r/p",
            "b) np",
            "c) nD/N",
            "d) np(1-p)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lognormal distributions are an important part of continuous distributions, as they represent probability distribution of variables having continuous values. They are not counted in discrete distributions."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The equation of variance, i.e. σ2=\\(\\frac{r(1-p)}{p^2}\\) is true for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyper geometric distribution",
            "b) Pascal Distribution",
            "c) Normal distribution",
            "d) Binomial distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mean of the Pascal distribution is given by the following equation,\nμ=r/p\nWhere r > 1 and an integer and p is probability of success. "
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Bernoulli trials are a part of _____ probability distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poisson",
            "b) Binomial",
            "c) Hyper geometric",
            "d) Normal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The expression \\(\\frac{r(1-p)}{p^2}\\) is useful for finding out variance of the Pascal probability distribution. We can identify it as it has “r” in the expression of variance."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "\\( \\left(a \\atop b\\right)\\) is expanded as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{a!}{b!}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{a!}{b!(a-b)!}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{a!}{b!(b-a)!}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{b!}{a!}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bernoulli trials are the independent trials having a result either a “success” or a “failure”. They are an important part of binomial probability distribution. The probability distribution is based upon the Bernoulli trials."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "For a Pascal distribution; r=3 and the probability of success is 0.7895. What will be the value of “σ”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0131",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1.0065",
            "d) 1.7320"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: \\( \\left(a \\atop b\\right)\\) is generally acronym for the combination \\(a \\atop b \\)C or  \\(\\frac{a!}{b!(a-b)!}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a discrete probability distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyper geometric Distribution",
            "b) Binomial Distribution",
            "c) Normal Distribution",
            "d) Poisson Distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hyper geometric distribution, Binomial distribution, and Poisson distribution are all part of discrete probability distribution family. But, Normal distribution is a Continuous distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "The mean of hyper geometric probability distribution is expressed as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ=nD/N",
            "b) μ=np",
            "c) μ=r/p",
            "d) μ=nN/D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mean of hyper geometric distribution is given by,\nμ=nD/N."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Probability function for hyper geometric probability distribution is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\) ",
            "b) \\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(n \\atop N\\right)} \\) ",
            "c) \\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(x \\atop D\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\) ",
            "d) \\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(n-x \\atop N-D\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The probability function for the hyper geometric probability distribution is evaluated by following equation,\n\\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\) \nWhere D is a number of interest, N is total no. of items in population, x is the no. of sample falling in the class of interest and n is no. of items in a sample. "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "For N=100, D=5, n=10, and x = 2; probability according to hypergeometric distribution will be _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.58375",
            "b) 0.92314",
            "c) 0.99336",
            "d) 0.99975"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to hyper geometric probability distribution,\n\\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\) \nThis gives P(X≤x)=0.99336 for the mentioned values."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "The independent trials which have either a “success” or a “failure” as an outcome, are called ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal trials",
            "b) Bernoulli trials",
            "c) Poisson’s trials",
            "d) Hyper geometric trials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a process contain a sequence of independent trials which don’t depend on each other’s result, and which have outcome either a “success” or a “failure”, the trials are called Bernoulli trials."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "The binomial distribution is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(p(x) = \\left(n \\atop x\\right) p^x (1-p)^{n-x}\\) ",
            "b) \\(p(x) = \\left(x \\atop n\\right) p^{n-x} (1-p)^x\\) ",
            "c) \\(p(x) = \\left(x \\atop n\\right) p^x (1-p)^{n-x}\\) ",
            "d) \\(p(x) = \\left(n \\atop x\\right) p^{n-x} (1-p)^x\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The binomial distribution is based on Bernoulli trials, which gives the probability distribution as,\n\\(p(x) = \\left(n \\atop x\\right) p^x (1-p)^{n-x}\\). "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Let us take Bernoulli trial of tossing a coin. If there are 70 independent trials, and finding a head is a success, what will be the variance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17.5",
            "b) 18.5",
            "c) 4.8",
            "d) 4.18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Variance of the binomial distribution,\nσ2=np(1-p)\nFor tossing a coin and finding a head, p = 0.5, which gives variance = 17.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Poisson distribution is given by ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(p(x) = \\frac{e^{-λ} λ^x}{x!}\\) ",
            "b) \\(p(x) = \\frac{e^{-x} λ^x}{x}\\) ",
            "c) \\(p(x) = \\frac{e^{-λ} λ^x}{x}\\) ",
            "d) \\(p(x) = \\frac{e^{-λ} λ^x}{λ!}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Poisson distribution probability is given by the following equation,\n\\(p(x) = \\frac{e^{-λ} λ^x}{x!}\\) \nWhere λ is a parameter and λ > 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "The mean of a Poisson distribution is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than λ",
            "b) Lesser than λ",
            "c) Equal to λ",
            "d) Having no relation with λ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Poisson distribution, the mean and the variance, both are always equal to the parameter used in the Poisson probability distribution, i.e. λ."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "For a company, which uses Poisson distributions to describe all the defects in its product, which has the parameter λ=4, what will be the probability of finding the selected product from a sample that will have 2 or less than 2 defects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2381",
            "b) 0.2561",
            "c) 0.2104",
            "d) 0.3310"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Poisson probability distribution which has λ=5, we can determine the above stated probability using,\nP{x≤2} = \\(\\sum_{x=2}^2 \\frac{e^{-4} 4^x}{x!}\\) = 0.018316 + 0.73263 + 0.146525 = 0.238104."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "For a experiment following binomial distribution, the mean is 54.3, and the number of independent trials is 121. What will be the probability of failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.55123",
            "b) 0.51000",
            "c) 0.44877",
            "d) 0.45700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: μ=54.3, n=121. We know that, p=μ/n\np=0.44876.\nSo probability of failure = 1-p = 0.55123."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "A lot follows hyper geometric distribution for defects found in its items. It contains 100 items out of which, 5 are defective. If 10 items are selected without replacement in a random order, what is the probability of finding 0 defective items?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5837521",
            "b) 0.4162479",
            "c) 0.5708992",
            "d) 0.4522222"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to hyper geometric probability distribution,\n\\(p(x) = \\frac{\\left(D \\atop x\\right)\\left(N-D \\atop n-x\\right)}{\\left(N \\atop n\\right)} \\) \nPutting values from the question, we get, p(x) = 0.5837521."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of these cannot be shown on the continuous distributions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length dimension measurement of a box",
            "b) Volume measurement of the box",
            "c) Area measurement of one face of the box",
            "d) Number of defects on the surface of the box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Continuous distributions are used to describe the variation in the values of variables which are continuous, i.e. which take values on continuous scale. Number of defects is discrete not continuous parameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of these is a continuous distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pascal distribution",
            "b) Lognormal distribution",
            "c) Binomial distribution",
            "d) Hyper geometric distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pascal, binomial, and hyper geometric distributions are all part of discrete distribution which are used to describe variation of attributes. Lognormal distribution is a continuous distribution used to describe variation of the continuous variables."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of these distributions has an appearance of bell-shaped or unimodal curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lognormal distributions",
            "b) Normal distribution",
            "c) Exponential distribution",
            "d) Cumulative exponential distributions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Out of all continuous distributions, Normal distributions are the only distributions, which have a shape of curve as a bell. The curves of them are mostly unimodal."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The rule of multiplication of probability is possible only ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) When events are independent",
            "b) When events are mutually exclusive",
            "c) When events are Bayesian",
            "d) When events are Empirical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rule of multiplication of probability is possible only when the events are independent.\nP(A and B)=P(A).P(B)"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of these equations describe the normal continuous distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sigma \\sqrt{2π}} e^{-0.5(\\frac{x-μ}{σ})^2}, -\\infty < x < -\\infty\\) ",
            "b) \\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2π}} e^{-0.5(\\frac{x-μ}{σ})^2}, -\\infty < x < -\\infty\\) ",
            "c) \\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sigma \\sqrt{π}} e^{-0.5(\\frac{x-μ}{σ})^x}, -\\infty < x < -\\infty\\) ",
            "d) \\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sigma \\sqrt{2π}} e^{-0.5(\\frac{x-μ}{σ})^x}, -\\infty < x < -\\infty\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normal distribution is a part of continuous distributions, which is described by the following equation,\n\\(f(x)=\\frac{1}{\\sigma \\sqrt{2π}} e^{-0.5(\\frac{x-μ}{σ})^2}, -\\infty < x < -\\infty\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "“ϕ(∙)” is said to be cumulative distribution function of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard binomial distribution",
            "b) Standard normal distribution",
            "c) Standard exponential distribution",
            "d) Standard gamma distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the standard normal distribution, “ϕ(∙)” is described as the cumulative distribution function, which has the value of mean equal to zero and the corresponding standard deviation equal to unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The probability that the normal random variable x is less than or equal to some value a is said to be the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard normal distribution",
            "b) Lognormal distribution",
            "c) Exponential distribution",
            "d) Cumulative normal distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The normal distribution has several important special cases, out of which, the cumulative normal distribution is defined as the probability that the normal random variable x≤a."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which of these is true for the normal distributions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(μ_y = a_1 μ_1 + a_2 μ_2 +⋯+ a_n μ_n\\) ",
            "b) \\(μ_y = a_1 μ_1^2 + a_2 μ_2^2 +⋯+ a_n μ_n^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(μ_y^2 = a_1^2 μ_1^2 + a_2^2 μ_2^2 +⋯+ a_n^2 μ_n^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(σ_y^2 = a_1^2 σ_1^2 + a_2^2 σ_2^2 +⋯+ a_n^2 σ_n^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From property, for any normal distribution which has,\n\\(y = a_1^2 x_1 + a_2^2 x_2 +⋯+ a_n^2 x_n\\) \nWe have,\n\\(μ_y = a_1 μ_1 + a_2 μ_2 +⋯+ a_n μ_n\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The central limit theorem is true for _______ distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal distribution",
            "b) Lognormal distribution",
            "c) Exponential distribution",
            "d) Gamma distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The central limit theorem uses an assumption that, the normal distribution is an appropriate distribution for a random variable. That’s why; the central limit theorem is true only for Normal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "If a variable x is having its value equal to the exponential function of another variable w, i.e. “x=exp⁡(w)”, and w has normal distribution; the distribution of x is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal distribution",
            "b) Exponential distribution",
            "c) Lognormal distribution",
            "d) Gamma distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a random variable x, which has “x=exp⁡(w)” where w is having a normal distribution; the distribution of such a random variable x, is said to be the Lognormal distribution. It is a continuous distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "For a lognormal random variable, what is the value of mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(μ=e^{\\theta+\\frac{w^2}{2}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(μ=e^{\\frac{w^2+\\theta}{2}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(μ=e^{w+\\frac{\\theta^2}{2}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(μ=e^{\\theta+w^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: if for x, which has x=ew, and w has a normal distribution with mean θ and variance w2; x is a lognormal random variable with mean expressed as\nμ=e(θ+ w2/2)."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The exponential distribution is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) f(x)=xeλ",
            "b) f(x)= e-λx",
            "c) f(x)= λe-λx",
            "d) f(x)=ew"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The continuous probability distribution is said to be exponential if the distribution follows this equation,\nf(x)= λe-λx."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The cumulative distribution function for the lognormal distribution is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\phi[\\frac{ln⁡(a)-\\theta}{\\omega}]\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\phi[\\frac{ln⁡(a)-\\theta}{a}]\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\phi[\\frac{ln⁡(a)-\\omega}{\\omega}]\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\phi[\\frac{ln⁡(a)-\\theta}{\\theta}]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lognormal cumulative distribution function defines the probability that the variable x is less than or equal to a is given by,\n\\(\\phi[\\frac{ln⁡(a)-\\theta}{\\omega}]\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "If a card is chosen from a deck of cards, what is the probability that it is either 7 or 9?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4/52",
            "b) 7/52",
            "c) 9/52",
            "d) 8/52"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 8 cards in the deck which are either 7 or 9. There are total 52 cards in the deck, so the probability that the card is either a 7 or a 9 is 8/52; based upon the outcomes of interest divided by the total possible outcomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The rule of multiplication of probability is possible only _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) When events are independent",
            "b) When events are mutually exclusive",
            "c) When events are Bayesian",
            "d) When events are Empirical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rule of multiplication of probability is possible only when the events are independent.\nP(A and B)=P(A).P(B)"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The display of possible outcomes of an event with their corresponding probabilities is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probability Plot",
            "b) Contingency table",
            "c) Bayesian Table",
            "d) Frequency Plot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The graphical representation of possible outcomes of an event with their corresponding probabilities; is called Probability plot."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which one of these is not one of the conditions for the binomial distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only two outcomes must be there for an event",
            "b) Independent trials must be there",
            "c) Trials must be more than 4",
            "d) The probability of failure must be constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a binomial distribution, Bernoulli trials are necessary, i.e. the outcomes of an event must be either a success or a failure, and this means the probability of failure must be constant. "
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "For mean=7 and standard deviation=2, what will be probability that a variable, which follows normal distribution, will have a value less than or equal to 10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.93319",
            "b) 0.94520",
            "c) 0.96409",
            "d) 0.91924"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here μ=7, σ=2, we know that, P[x≤a] = P[z≤\\(\\frac{a-\\mu}{σ}\\)] \nSo, P[x≤10]=P[z≤\\(\\frac{10-7}{2}\\)]= P[z≤1.5]=φ[1.5]=0.93319.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The variance of lognormal distribution is given by ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ2 = e2θ+w (\\(e^{w^{2}}\\)-1)",
            "b) σ2 = e2θ+w2 (ew-1)",
            "c) σ2 = e2θ+w2 (\\(e^{w^{2}}\\)-1)",
            "d) σ2 = e2θ+w2 (\\(e^{w^{2}}\\)-2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The variance of a variable having a lognormal distribution is given by,\nσ2= e2θ+w2 (ew2-1)."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "The relationship between the mean and variance of the exponential distribution is expressed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ = λσ2",
            "b) μ = σ2/λ",
            "c) σ2=λ2 μ",
            "d) σ2=μ/λ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For an exponential distribution, μ=1⁄λ and σ2 =  1/λ2\nSo, for an exponential distribution,  μ = λσ2."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "(1-e-λa) is the cumulative ______ distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gamma",
            "b) Normal",
            "c) Lognormal",
            "d) Exponential"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The cumulative distribution for standard exponential distribution is given by following equation,\nF(a)=(1-e-λa)."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "The exponential distribution is used in reliability engineering as a model of the time to failure of a system. The parameter λ is called _____ in this application.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Failure rate",
            "b) MTF",
            "c) Hazard rate",
            "d) MTBF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The parameter λ in the reliability engineering application of the exponential distribution is called the failure rate of the system. The application uses it as a model of time to failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The mean of the gamma distribution is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ=1/λ",
            "b) μ=r/λ",
            "c) μ=r2/λ",
            "d) μ=1/r"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In reliability engineering, the exponential distribution is used as a model of the time to failure of a system. The mean of the distribution is called MTF or mean time to failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The relationship between the mean and the standard deviation of the gamma distribution is given as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\mu}{\\sigma} = \\sqrt{r}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{\\mu}{\\sigma} = r\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{\\mu}{\\sigma} = r^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{\\mu}{\\sigma} = \\sqrt[3]{r}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a gamma distribution,\nμ=r/λ\nWhere r and λ are the shape parameter and the scale parameter, respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "If the shape parameter of the gamma distribution is twice the scale parameter, what will be the value of the mean of the distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the shape factor r=1, in the case of a gamma distribution, gamma distribution reduces to an exponential distribution which has only the scale parameter λ."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "For an exponential distribution, what is the probability that the value of the exponential random variable with parameter λ=3.2; will be having a value higher than 0.2353?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5290",
            "b) 0.4710",
            "c) 0.2213",
            "d) 0.3452"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mean of a gamma distribution = \\(\\frac{r}{λ}\\) and standard deviation σ = \\(\\frac{\\sqrt{r}}{λ}\\); so,\n\\(\\frac{\\mu}{\\sigma} = \\sqrt{r}\\).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of these will not be distributed on a discrete distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The number of houses in a colony",
            "b) The number of bedrooms in a house",
            "c) The number of scratches on a car hood",
            "d) The diameter of a car tire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As for a gamma distribution, mean μ=r/λ; putting the value r=2λ from the question, we get,\nμ=2λ⁄λ=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "For a variable distributed log-normally with θ=6, ω=1.2; what is the probability that the variable exceeds a value of 500?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4290",
            "b) 0.5710",
            "c) 0.4990",
            "d) 0.4937"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: P[x>0.2352]=1-P[x≤0.2352]=1-{1-exp⁡(-3.2*0.2353)}=0.4710."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The average value of the quality characteristic corresponding to in-control state is represented by _____ in the control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CL",
            "b) UCL",
            "c) LCL",
            "d) Sample number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control chart contains a centre line (CL) that represents the average value of the quality characteristic corresponding to in-control state. This may be the desired value of that quality characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The highest value that a quality characteristic can take before the process becomes out-of-control, is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Center line",
            "b) Upper control limit",
            "c) Lower control limit",
            "d) Control limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The UCL is the highest value of a quality characteristic at which the process is in-control, i.e. it produces products of desired specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The horizontal line in the control chart which shows the minimum value of a quality characteristic, before the process gets out-of-control, is called the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upper control limit line",
            "b) Lower control limit line",
            "c) Desired value",
            "d) Center line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lowest value for a Critical-to-quality characteristic corresponding to in-control state is shown on the control chart with the lowest horizontal line, which is called the lower control limit line."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "In the horizontal axis of a control chart displays _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample number",
            "b) Time",
            "c) Either sample number or time",
            "d) Neither sample number or time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The horizontal axis of a control chart displays either sample numbers or time elapsed from a certain time or from the time of process starting."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "If for a process, 18 out of 20 points are plotted above the CL but below the upper control limit, and only 2 of 20 are plotted between the center line and the lower control limit, what can we say about the process state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-control",
            "b) Out-of-control",
            "c) Data is not enough to predict",
            "d) Process state is not dependent over this data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above question concludes a systematic pattern. For a process to be perfectly in-control state, the plotted points on the corresponding control chart should have an essentially random pattern. "
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Shifting of mean from the current value to a new value and remaining there, is called _____ shift of the mean.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous",
            "b) Abrupt",
            "c) Random",
            "d) Sustained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to some reason, it may be possible that the process mean shifts from one point to another, and remain there for quite some time. This shifting of mean is called the sustained shift of the mean."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "A process is said to be in the statistical control if it operates with ______ of variation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chance causes",
            "b) Assignable causes",
            "c) Both chance and assignable causes",
            "d) Neither chance nor assignable causes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chance causes of variation produce the natural variability of the stable process. As this natural variability cannot be avoided, so a process is said to be in statistical control if it operates only with chance causes of variation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of SPC’s 7 tools?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pareto chart",
            "b) Histogram",
            "c) Design of Experiments",
            "d) Check sheet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pareto chart, check sheet, histogram, cause-and-effect diagram, scatter diagram, and control chart are all part of SPC (Statistical Process Control). Design of Experiments is not one of them."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "If a process has its operation with _________ causes of variation, it is said to be an out-of-control process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chance",
            "b) Assignable",
            "c) Neither chance nor assignable",
            "d) Out-of-control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only assignable causes of variation are able to shift the process from in-control to out-of-control state. So if a process possesses assignable causes of variation, it is stated to be out-of-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Chance causes of variation are also called ________ and assignable causes are also called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Common causes, special causes",
            "b) Special causes, common causes",
            "c) Variability causes, non-variability causes",
            "d) Non-variability causes, variability causes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chance causes of variation, and assignable causes of variation are also called the common causes, and special causes of variation, respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "The chance and assignable cause terminology was developed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deming",
            "b) Hawthorne",
            "c) ISO",
            "d) Shewhart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The chance and assignable cause terminology was developed by W. A. Shewhart. Now, common and special cause terminology is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "OC curve can be used to determine the probability of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I error",
            "b) Type II error",
            "c) Both type I and type II error",
            "d) Neither type I nor type II error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: OC curve for any process is a very useful tool to find out the probability of a type II error which means, concluding the process in-control when it is actually out-of-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "In the name of the OC curve, OC stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operation Characteristic",
            "b) Operating Characteristic",
            "c) Operator Characteristic",
            "d) Operated Characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The OC curve stands for Operating Characteristic curve which is used to develop an understanding of probability variation of the Type II error in the quality control."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The general theory of Control charts was first developed by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Walter A. Shewhart",
            "b) Deming",
            "c) ISO",
            "d) ASQC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: W.A. Shewhart was the first person to develop an applicable theory for quality control for the processes used in manufacturing a product. This was known as the general theory of Control Charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Control charts are the part of _______ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Measure",
            "c) Act",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The control charts use the data from the measure step to analyze the process situation and then apply the steps to control the quality of the process. So they are used in the control step, analyze step of DMAIC process."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "The size of sample is 5 for a process. If the process standard deviation is 0.15 micron, and the mean of process is 1.5 micron, the standard deviation of the sample average will be _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0500",
            "b) 0.1000",
            "c) 0.6710",
            "d) 0.0671"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standard deviation of the sample average is calculated by,\nσx=σ/√n\nPutting σ=0.15, n=5, we get, σx=0.0671."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "For a process, sample size=5, process standard deviation=0.15, mean=1.5, and the std. deviation of mean is 0.0671. What will be the value of 3σ upper control limit for the construction of control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.70",
            "b) 1.29",
            "c) 1.92",
            "d) 0.170"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know, UCL3σ=;n=5; σ=0.15, \\(\\overline{x}\\) = 1.5; σx=0.0671{from question}\nSo, UCL3σ=1.5+3(0.0671)=1.7013."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "The correct expression for UCL for construction of a control chart is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL = \\(\\overline{x} + Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}} (\\sigma_x)\\) ",
            "b) UCL = \\(\\overline{x} – Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}} (\\sigma)\\) ",
            "c) UCL = \\(\\overline{x} – Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}} (\\sigma_x)\\) ",
            "d) UCL = \\(\\overline{x} + Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}} (\\sigma)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The UCL is defined as the upper control limit for the control chart and it is evaluated as,\nUCL = \\(\\overline{x} + Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}} (\\sigma_x)\\); where \\(\\overline{x}\\) is the mean of process, σx is the std. deviation of mean and \\(Z_{\\frac{\\alpha}{2}}\\) is a arbitrary constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The general model for the lower control limit for a value of quality characteristic “w” will be _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL = μw + Lσw",
            "b) LCL = μw – Lσ",
            "c) LCL = μw – Lσw",
            "d) LCL = μw + Lσ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The general expression for LCL of a quality characteristic “w” is given by,\nLCL = μw – Lσw;\nWhere “L” denotes the distance of control limits from the center line."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "The center line of a control chart will be having a value ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher than mean of quality characteristic",
            "b) Lower than mean of quality characteristic",
            "c) Equal to mean of quality characteristic",
            "d) Which is higher than UCL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The center line of the control chart denotes the value of the process mean of the quality characteristic. It is always the desired value."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Which of these is a part of corrective action process associated with a control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) OCAP",
            "b) DMAIC",
            "c) OC curve",
            "d) LCL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: OCAP (Out-of-control-plan) is an important part of the corrective action process associated with the control charts which uses results of control charts to control the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to estimate capability of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) Process mean",
            "c) Acceptance Sampling",
            "d) Designed Experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Control charts are also used as estimating device as their results can be used to estimate the process capability of a certain process."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Control charts for central tendency and the variability are called _________ control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variables",
            "b) Attributes",
            "c) Acceptance",
            "d) Rejections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is convenient to describe the variables with a measure of central tendency and measure of variability. So the control charts for central tendency and variability are called Variable control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The control charts formed for judgment of conformities and non-conformities are called ______ control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variables",
            "b) Attributes",
            "c) Acceptance",
            "d) Rejections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Attributes are increased on the discrete scale and they give results as either conformity or non-conformity. So the charts plotted for non-conformities and conformities are called Attributes control charts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Control charts with points around mean and in predicted or fixed manner indicate ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stationary variability",
            "b) Non-stationary variability",
            "c) Auto correlated variability",
            "d) Process out of control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control charts which have points around the mean and in a predicted manner indicate that the process has stationary variability. This explains the nature of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Moving the UCL and LCL line far from the Center line means ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreasing the possibility of type I error",
            "b) Increasing the possibility of type II error",
            "c) Increasing the possibility of type I error",
            "d) Decreasing the possibility of type II error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Type I error is, “concluding the process to be out-of-control when it is actually in-control”. So, more distance between UCL and LCL means, a point without an assignable cause will lie in between the UCL and LCL, i.e. in-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "If we decrease the distance between LCL and UCL, what will happen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreasing the possibility of type I error",
            "b) Increasing the possibility of type II error",
            "c) Increasing the possibility of type I error",
            "d) Decreasing the possibility of type II error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Type II error is, “concluding the process to be in-control when it is actually out-of-control”. This means the decreased distance between LCL and UCL will cause a point with assignable cause, lie not in between them, i.e. out-of-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "If “two sets of limits” approach is taken to construct a control chart, what are the outer set of limits called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Action Limits",
            "b) Warning Limits",
            "c) Variable Limits",
            "d) Constant Limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The outer set of limits used in a “two sets of limits” approach of constructing a control chart, are generally called Action limits as action is to be done to correct the assignable cause if any point out-lies the action limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The inner limits in the “Two sets of limits” approach of the construction of control chart are called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Action Limits",
            "b) Variable Limits",
            "c) Constant Limits",
            "d) Warning Limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The “two sets of limits” approach utilizes two different sets of UCL and LCL. In those two sets, the inner set of LCL and UCL is called the warning limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "ARL is termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average Run Length",
            "b) Allocating Run Length",
            "c) Affected Run Length",
            "d) Assumed Run Length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Average Run Length has an acronym of ARL. It provides useful way to make effective decisions for the sample size to be selected for the construction of the control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The probability of a point to exceed the control limits for a control chart is 0.0040. What will be the ARL for this case?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250",
            "b) 278",
            "c) 210",
            "d) 216"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We define ARL as the reciprocal of the probability of a point falling out of the area between control limits. Here,\nARL=\\(\\frac{1}{p}=\\frac{1}{0.0040}\\)=250\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "For an average run length of 370, what will be the probability of a point falling out of the area between the control limits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0027",
            "b) 0.0013",
            "c) 0.0045",
            "d) 0.0040"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know,\nARL = 1⁄p\nPutting value of ARL=370, we get, p=0.0027."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "What is the full-form of ATS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average time to Stop",
            "b) Average Time to Start",
            "c) Average Time to Signal",
            "d) Average Time to Select"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ATS is the abbreviation used for the Average Time to Signal. It is a useful way to express the performance of a control chart very effectively and easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "If for a process, the samples are taken 5 hrs apart and its ARL is 24.24, What will be ATS for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 121.2",
            "b) 110.0",
            "c) 113.3",
            "d) 137.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\nATS=ARL.h\nPutting values h=5,ARL=24.24; we get,\nATS=121.2."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Decreasing sample size will ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the slope of OC curve",
            "b) Increase the slope of OC curve",
            "c) First decrease then increase the slope of OC curve",
            "d) Makes OC curve have 0 slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of OC curve varies inversely with the sample size taken for the control chart construction. The decrease in the size of the sample taken to construct a control chart will increase the slope of OC curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which of these statements, correctly describes the concept of rational subgroups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If assignable causes are present, the chances of difference between subgroups should be largest",
            "b) If assignable causes are present, the chances of difference between subgroups must be lowest",
            "c) If assignable causes are present, the chances of difference between the subgroups must be moderate",
            "d) If assignable causes are present, the chances of difference between the subgroups must be zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rational Subgroups concept says that, for subgroups, if assignable causes are present, the chances of differences between subgroups should be maximized, while the chance for differences due to these causes within a subgroup must be lowest."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "If the ARL is 34.8 for a process which has ATS=69.6 hrs, what is the time interval before taking samples?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 hrs",
            "b) 8 hrs",
            "c) 2 hrs",
            "d) 4 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time interval before taking samples is given by,\nh=\\(\\frac{ATS}{ARL}\\) \nPutting values of ATS and ARL, we get h=2 hrs."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the sensitizing Western Electric rules that indicate “action needed” for Shewhart control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One or more points near a warning limit/control limit",
            "b) One point plots outside 3-sigma control limits",
            "c) Eight consecutive points plot on one side of the control line",
            "d) Two of 3 consecutive points plot beyond the 2-sigma warning limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Western Electric rules which indicate “action needed” for Shewhart control charts do not state that, if one or more points are plotted near a warning limit or control limit will need an action to control the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a part of magnificent seven of SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pareto chart",
            "b) Check Sheet",
            "c) Scatter Diagram",
            "d) 2k factorial design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pareto chart, check sheet, and scatter diagram are all parts of the 7 problem solving tools of SPC or magnificent 7 of SPC (statistical process control). 2k factorial design is a part of design of experiments."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Check sheet shows ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) If a process part is completed",
            "b) If the process components are all checked",
            "c) If the samples of the process are checked",
            "d) Time oriented summary of defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A check sheet is very easy way, to show the time oriented summary of defects in the number of samples taken from a lot of products from a certain process."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The graphical representation of the total frequencies of occurrence of each type of defects type against the various defect types will be called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Check sheet",
            "b) Pareto chart",
            "c) Histogram",
            "d) Control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The graphical representation of frequencies of defects with the information of the names of defects is generally done using a Pareto chart. It is quite useful in analysis of bigger data."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Pareto chart identifies the ____________ defects not the ____________ defects.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The most important, the most frequent",
            "b) The most frequent, the most important",
            "c) The smallest defects, the largest defects",
            "d) The largest defects, the smallest defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is property of a Pareto chart that, it does not automatically identify the most important defects but only the most frequent. There is no information about severity of the defect."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Pareto charts are a main part of _____ steps of DMAIC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measure and Analyze",
            "b) Define and Measure",
            "c) Define and Improve",
            "d) Analyze and Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pareto charts are useful to store a data about frequencies of occurrence of a number defects. This means it is first used in measure step, then in the analyze step to analyze data from the measure step."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Pareto chart is invented by from Italian economist ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alfred Pareto",
            "b) Vilfred Pareto",
            "c) Jon Pareto",
            "d) Paulo Pareto"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pareto charts have their name derived from the name of the Italian economist, Vilfred Pareto (1848-1927) who theorized that in certain economies where the majority of the wealth was held by a disproportionately small segment of population."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "In Cause and Effect diagram, what procedure is adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First defects are identified and then the corresponding effects on working of product is determined",
            "b) First defects in a product are identified and then, the corresponding causes are discovered",
            "c) First causes of defects are plotted then the effects of them, i.e. defects are identified",
            "d) Causes and their effects are identified simultaneously"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To plot a cause and effect diagram, first defects in a product are identified and then, the corresponding causes which are grounds of the origin of those defects."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Defect concentration diagrams are an important part of ____________ step of DMAIC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analyze",
            "b) Define",
            "c) Improve",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Defect concentration diagrams are an important part of the Analyze step of the DMAIC problem solving process as it aims to analyze the defects present in different locations of units."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Phase II of control chart applications contain __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monitoring the process by comparing each sample statistic to control limits",
            "b) Comparison of a set of data from control limits",
            "c) Corrective action only to get data in control the process",
            "d) Initial measurement of data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phase II of control chart application contains monitoring of the process by comparing each sample statistics data of the process production to some finalized control limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of these is a useful plot for identifying a potential relationship between two variables of a process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pareto chart",
            "b) Defect concentration diagram",
            "c) Scatter diagram",
            "d) Stem and Leaf plot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A scatter diagram is a very useful plot between two variables which affects the manufacturing process. To identify any potential relationship between the two variables, scatter diagram is a very useful tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of these is having an important role in regression modeling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stem and Leaf plot",
            "b) Pareto chart",
            "c) Defect concentration diagram",
            "d) Scatter diagram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A Scatter diagram is playing an important role in regression modeling."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Scatter diagram is a technique used in ______ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Analyze",
            "c) Improve",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scatter diagram have an important part in regression modeling which is an important procedure, used in analyze step of DMAIC PSP."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Defect concentration diagram is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Picture of the unit showing all relevant views",
            "b) Graph of defects with their frequency",
            "c) Time oriented summary of defects",
            "d) Graph to determine underlying causes of any defect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Defect concentration diagram is a very useful tool to analyze the whole body of product to find out areas of high defect intensity. It is a picture of the unit showing all relevant views."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Quantities that can be numerically measured, can be plotted on a _________ control chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) X bar",
            "b) P chart",
            "c) C chart",
            "d) np chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A quantity that is measured on a continuous scale, i.e. it is numerically measured, can be plotted on a control chart type named, X bar control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "A single measureable quality characteristic, such as dimension, weight, or volume, is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable",
            "b) Attribute",
            "c) Variable and an Attribute",
            "d) Mean and variablility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A single measurable quality characteristic is that CTQ that can be measured on a continuous scale. So it is also called a variable, be it a dimension or a weight measurement of a product unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "A variable quality characteristic will have both __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean and variability",
            "b) Discrete and continuous values",
            "c) Zero and infinite value",
            "d) One or zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A variable quality characteristic will vary on a continuous scale. So it will have both, a mean and its variability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Control of the process average or mean quality level is usually done with the ___________ control chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) X bar control chart",
            "b) S control chart",
            "c) R chart",
            "d) P chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a quality characteristic has a mean and variability, it is called a variable. If the control of process average or mean quality level is to be done for a variable, an x bar variable control chart is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "S chart is used to monitor _________ of a quality characteristic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean",
            "b) Range",
            "c) Variability",
            "d) Attributes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: S chart is a control chart used to monitor the variability of a process quality characteristic. It is variable chart as it is used for monitor variability of variables."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Toughness of a bolt mount on a tank is  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) An attribute",
            "b) A variable",
            "c) Variable and an attribute",
            "d) Variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A quality characteristic having a numerical measurement on a continuous scale is called a variable. As the toughness of a bolt is a continuous quality characteristic, it is called a variable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "X chart is a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attribute control chart",
            "b) Variable control chart",
            "c) Neither a variable control chart nor an attribute control chart",
            "d) Falls in the category of both variable and attribute control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mean is only an asset of a variable quality characteristic. As x denotes mean of a variable, x chart is counted in the variable control chart category. "
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "If a process is said to be in control, what can we say about the variation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Random",
            "b) Normal",
            "c) Attribute",
            "d) Assignable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a process is said to be in control, its sample data will have a random pattern. So when plotted on a control chart, they will appear to have a random distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Tolerances are said to be ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) limits of natural variability",
            "b) Statistical limits of variability",
            "c) Limits determined by the customers of the product",
            "d) Limits of inherent process variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The natural variability varies from a certain highest value to some lowest value. These limits of natural variability are also called as Tolerance."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Upper control limit for a x chart is expressed by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_2 R \\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} – A_2 R\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_2 \\bar{R}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_3 R\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The expression for the upper control limit of the x chart is \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_2 R \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "The center line for a \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}\\) chart denotes ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean of any sample",
            "b) Mean of means of the sample",
            "c) Mean of any sample + 0.5",
            "d) (Mean of any sample) / 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line for a \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}\\) chart is generally mean of means of all the samples taken from a process. This gives more accurate results than choosing the mean of any sample to be taken as Center line."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Specifications have the same meaning as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control limits",
            "b) UCL",
            "c) LCL",
            "d) Tolerances"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tolerance for a variable quality characteristic is generally having the same meaning as specifications of a product, i.e. the desired values for that quality characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "For a random variable having a normal distribution, the ratio of its range to the standard deviation is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relative range",
            "b) Absolute range",
            "c) Major range",
            "d) Minor range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a normal random variable, the ratio of its range to the standard deviation is called the relative range for that random variable."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "LCL for the R chart is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) D3 R",
            "b) D2 R",
            "c) R – D3 R",
            "d) d2 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LCL for an R chart is always given by the following equation,\nLCL = D3 R. "
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "In the general equation of UCL of a control chart, for any x chart, which of these is used as the estimator of μ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{x}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{R}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{\\bar{R}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: UCL=μ+ Zα/2 σ is the general equation for UCL for any control chart. For any \\(\\bar{x}\\) chart, \\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}\\) is used as the estimator of μ in the above mentioned equation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Which of these gives the correct value of A2 used in the equation for control limits of a x control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{3}{d_2 \\sqrt{n}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{3}{d_2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{d_2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of A2 used in the equation of control limits of a x control chart is given by following equation,\n\\(\\frac{3}{d_2 \\sqrt{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "In phase I application of x and R chart, the control limits obtained  from the equations are treated as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Final limits",
            "b) Trial limits",
            "c) Warning limits",
            "d) Pattern limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The obtained limits from the equation of control limits for a x and R chart, are generally treated as Trial limits. They allow us to determine whether the process was in control when the m initial samples were taken."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which term is having a closest meaning as Sampling Distributions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) On site inspection",
            "c) Whole lot inspection",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term “control charts” is having a closest meaning to “sampling distribution” because, control charts are also plotted on the data obtained from the sample inspection and also, they show variation in sample data."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Process capability generally uses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specifications",
            "b) Control Limits",
            "c) Process standard deviation",
            "d) Mean of any one sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Process capability studies make use of the specifications of any certain Critical-to-quality characteristic or quality characteristic to estimate the performance of any process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The process standard deviation is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R/d2",
            "b) Rd2",
            "c) 1/d2",
            "d) R/d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process standard deviation may be estimated by using the following equation,\n\\(\\hat{σ} = \\frac{\\bar{R}}{d_2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "For any process, the sample ranges are, 1.2,1.5,1.1,1.4,1.5. The subgroup size is 5. What will be the process standard deviation? Given: d2=2.326 and A2=0.577",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.576",
            "b) 2.322",
            "c) 0.511",
            "d) 2.463"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(\\bar{R} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=0}^{i=n} R_i}{n}\\) and “process standard deviation = \\(\\frac{\\bar{R}}{d_2}\\)“, by using the values of R and d2 in the question, we get process standard deviation=0.576\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "A tolerance diagram is also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scatter diagram",
            "b) Defect concentration diagram",
            "c) Histogram",
            "d) Tier chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The run chart of individual observations in each sample is called the tolerance diagram for any process. The tolerance diagram is also called Tier chart of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Is there any relationship between specification limits and control limits of x and R charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yes, Specification limits = Control limits",
            "b) Yes, Control limits=Specification limits/2",
            "c) No",
            "d) Yes, Control limits*0.5 = Specification limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There is no certain relationship defined; between the control limits of x and R charts and the specification limits of any quality characteristic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Control limits are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limits defined by customers",
            "b) Limits driven by the natural variability of the process",
            "c) Limits driven by the inherent variability of the process",
            "d) Statistical limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The control limits are the limits for a quality characteristic for a process to be in-control. They are driven by the natural variability of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The natural variability of the process is measured by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process mean",
            "b) Sample standard deviation",
            "c) Process standard deviation",
            "d) Sample mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The natural variability of any process is the main factor affecting the control limits of any quality characteristic while plotting a control chart. They are measured by process standard deviation, σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "What type of chart will be used to plot the number of defectives in the output of any process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x bar chart",
            "b) R chart",
            "c) c chart",
            "d) p chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of defectives in the samples of the output of a process is monitored by the p chart and the number of defects is monitored by a “c chart”."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Once a set of reliable control limits is obtained, we use the control chart for monitoring future production. This is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase I control chart usage",
            "b) Phase II control chart usage",
            "c) Phase III control chart usage",
            "d) Phase IV control chart usage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The use of reliable control limits to monitor the future production from a process, is generally mentioned as the Phase II application of control chart while, setting the trial control limits to monitor the process is called the Phase I application."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "When R chart is out of control, we __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eliminate the out-of-control points and recalculate the control limits",
            "b) Take one more sample and recalculate the control limits",
            "c) Eliminate the out-of-control points and the nearest two points, and recalculate the control limits",
            "d) Take no action"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When R chart is out of control, we often eliminate the out-of-control points and recompute a revised value of R bar. This will help us recalculate the control limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "When the upper and lower natural tolerance limits are equal to the upper and lower specification limits, the process capability ratio, cp is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) Less than 1",
            "d) Equal to 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the natural tolerance limits are having a equal value to the specification limits for a quality characteristic, the process capability ratio, cp is having a value equal to 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "X bar chart monitors __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between-sample variability",
            "b) Within-sample variability",
            "c) Neither between-sample nor within-sample variability",
            "d) Both between-sample variability and within-sample variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A x chart is only used to monitor the variability of a whole process over time. It does not detect variability within a sample but variability between all the samples of a process output."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Unlike x chart, which measures between-sample variability only, an R chart is used to monitor ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both between-sample variability and within-sample variability",
            "b) Within-sample variability only",
            "c) Between-sample variability only",
            "d) Neither between-sample variability nor within-sample variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A R chart is a chart which uses sample ranges to calculate its center line and control charts. So it only measures within-sample variability, i.e. the instantaneous variability at a given time."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "For standard values of mean and standard deviation used, what does the center line of the R chart represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R bar",
            "b) d2 σ",
            "c) D2 σ",
            "d) d2 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When using the standard values of process mean and standard deviation, A in the equation of UCL for x chart is given by\nA=\\(\\frac{3}{n^{0.5}} = \\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "The control limits obtained by specifying the type I error level for the test, are called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probability limits",
            "b) Trial limits",
            "c) Error limits",
            "d) Unreliable limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the standard values of mean and standard deviation used, the center line for a R chart is determined by the following formula, d2 σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which chart should be interpreted first when both, x chart, and R chart are indicating a non-random behavior?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x chart",
            "b) R chart",
            "c) X and R chart",
            "d) Trial Limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is possible to define the control limits for a control chart by specifying the type I error level. The limits obtained by this way, are called the Probability limits for the control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of these is a cause of trend patterns on a control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradual wearing out of some critical process component",
            "b) Operator fatigue",
            "c) Environmental changes",
            "d) Over-control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a property of control charts for x bar and R, that if they both indicate non-random behavior, and if R chart is interpreted first to delete the assignable causes in it, it will automatically delete assignable causes in x bar chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Shift in process level can be seen on the control charts when __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operator fatigue occurs",
            "b) Temperature changes",
            "c) Over-control of process",
            "d) New workers introduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A trend or continuous movement in one direction on a control chart is generally caused by gradual wearing out of some critical process component like deterioration of a tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Stratification is defined as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tendency for the points to cluster artificially around the center line",
            "b) Shift in the process level",
            "c) Continuous movement of points in one direction",
            "d) When the points fall near or slightly outside the control limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shift in the process level is a phenomenon seen on the control chart patterns. It occurs when there is introduction of new workers, or there is a change of methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Stratification of points on a control chart indicates __________ of natural variability of the process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lack",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Constancy",
            "d) Randomness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stratification is defined as the tendency of the points on a control chart, to cluster around the center line of the control chart. It occurs very frequently while applying control charts to a process."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The 3 sigma limits on x bar control charts imply that the type I error probability is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0012",
            "b) 0.0072",
            "c) 0.0027",
            "d) 0.0037"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stratification makes the points in a control chart to be plotted around the control chart center line; which indicates that the randomness is gone and there is a lack in natural variability of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The assumption that links normality to the control charts is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The underlying distribution of the quality characteristic is normal",
            "b) The normal mean will be equal to the process mean",
            "c) The normal distribution is not the correct distribution for all the quality characteristic",
            "d) Every distribution is a part of normal distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is an assumption that links the normality to the control charts in the development of the performance properties of x bar and R charts; that is, the underlying distribution of the quality characteristic is normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "The probability of not detecting “an in-control shift” of the mean of the process is said to be the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) α – Risk",
            "b) β – Risk",
            "c) γ – Risk",
            "d) δ – Risk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the mean of a process shifts from one value to another value with process being in-control, and shift is not detected on the control chart, the probability of this event is called the β – Risk. "
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "If the sample size is 7 and the Average run length is 122 for a process, what will be the expected number of the individual units sampled?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 850",
            "b) 854",
            "c) 867",
            "d) 844"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know,\nI=nARL\nPutting n=7 and ARL=122, we get, I = 854."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "If β- risk of any process is 0.75, what will be the ARL for that process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 1.33",
            "c) 0.86",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ARL is given by,\nARL=\\(\\frac{1}{1-β}\\) \nPutting β=0.75, we get ARL=4."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Slope of OC curve for x bar chart will _________ when sample size is increased.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Remain same",
            "d) Decrease then increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The OC curve is the curve between the β- risk against the magnitude of the shift in mean expressed in std. deviation units for different sample size. Its slope decreases as the sample size is increased."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "If the probability of one point plotting out of control limits of a X bar control charts is 0.0143, what will be its expected number of individual units sampled with subgroup size 8?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 559",
            "b) 544",
            "c) 530",
            "d) 580"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know, ARL=1⁄α and I=nARL. From question we get, α=0.0143 and n=8.\nUsing this data we get; I≈559."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "A mixture pattern in the control chart points is exhibited when __________ occurs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operator fatigue",
            "b) Change of raw materials",
            "c) Continuous wear of tool",
            "d) Adjustments too often responding to random variation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the “Over-control” occurs, i.e. the operator adjusts the processes very frequently and recurrently, the random pattern of the process data vanishes and a mixed pattern is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "If the means for sample 1 to 4 for a process are, 12.67, 22.32, 14.53, 12.11; what value will be the center line of x chart indicating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15.2",
            "b) 15.4",
            "c) 14.8",
            "d) 14.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line of the x chart, indicates the mean of all means of samples; i.e.,\nCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}} = \\frac{\\sum \\bar{x}}{N}\\)=15.4\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of these should be plotted on the x bar chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Counts",
            "b) Defects",
            "c) Problems Solved",
            "d) Measurements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The permanent change in sample size is not a frequent activity. So it is done because of some major reasons like cost or extraordinary good performance of process on control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "What is the estimator of standard deviation in the x bar and R charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean of one sample",
            "b) Mean of whole process",
            "c) Range",
            "d) Process capability ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In x bar and R charts, process standard deviation is estimated indirectly through the use of the range R. x bar is used as an estimator of mean."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "What does “s” denote in x bar and s charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample",
            "b) Sample standard deviation",
            "c) Process standard deviation",
            "d) Statistics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Process standard deviation in the x bar and s charts, is estimated directly instead of indirectly through the use of Range as in x bar and R charts. Here “s” denotes the sample standard deviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "What is an unbiased estimator of unknown variance of a probability distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample mean",
            "b) Sample standard deviation",
            "c) Sample variance",
            "d) Sample range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If σ2 is the unknown variance of a probability distribution, then an unbiased estimator must be used to estimate σ2. In this case, sample variance is used as the required estimator."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "What is the standard formula of sample variance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i-\\bar{x})^{1/2}}{n-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i-\\bar{x})^{2}}{n-1}\\) ",
            "c) \\([\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i-\\bar{x})^{2}}{n-1}]^{1/2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i-\\bar{x})^{2}}{n}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sample variance is given by the following formula.\ns2 = \\(\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n (x_i-\\bar{x})^{1/2}}{n-1}\\)."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which of these formulas gives the exact equation for the UCL of s chart with a std. value for σ given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B6 σ",
            "b) B5 σ",
            "c) c4 σ",
            "d) c3 σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The UCL parameter of the s chart with a std. value for σ given, is expressed by\nUCL=B6 σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "The center line of the s chart with a standard value for σ given, denotes the value of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) B6 σ",
            "b) c4 σ",
            "c) B5 σ",
            "d) c5 σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line of the s chart with a standard value for σ given, denotes the value equal to,\nCL=B6 σ"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "If the sample standard deviations for a process are 1.567, 1.429, 1.323, 1.525, 1.989, 1.457, what will be the mean standard deviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.548",
            "b) 1.858",
            "c) 1.327",
            "d) 1.967"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mean standard deviation of the sample standard deviations is given by,\n\\(\\bar{s} = \\frac{1}{m} \\sum_{i=1}^m s_i\\) \nWhere si denotes the standard deviation of ith sample. Calculating the mean using the above formaula gives, s=1.548.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "What is the value of B5 in the terms of c4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(c_4-3\\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "b) \\(c_4+3\\sqrt{(1+c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "c) \\(c_4+3\\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "d) \\(c_4-3\\sqrt{(1+c_4^2)}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of B5 in the terms of c4 is given by,\nB5 = \\(c_4-3\\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\)\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The center line of the s chart denotes ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard deviation of the process",
            "b) Mean of m number of standard deviations, where m is the number of samples",
            "c) c4 s",
            "d) B5 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line of the s chart denotes the mean of m number of standard deviations, where m is the number of samples. This is the desired value of the sample standard deviation for the process to be in control."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the value of LCL for the s chart when the standard value for σ is not given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B5 s",
            "b) B4 s",
            "c) B6 s",
            "d) B3 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LCL of the s chart gives the value equal to, B3 s when the standard value for σ is not given. This is the lowest the value of s can be, for the process to be in-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "What is the value of B3 in the terms of c4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(c_4-3\\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "b) \\(c_4+3\\sqrt{(1+c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "c) \\(1-\\frac{3}{c_4} \\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\) ",
            "d) \\(1-\\frac{c_4}{3\\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of B3 in the terms of c4  is given by,\nB3 = \\(1-\\frac{3}{c_4} \\sqrt{(1-c_4^2)}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "What is the formula for UCL for x bar chart when s is known?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(UCL = \\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_3 \\bar{s}\\) ",
            "b) \\(UCL = \\bar{\\bar{x}} – A_2 \\bar{s}\\) ",
            "c) \\(UCL = \\bar{\\bar{x}} – A_3 \\bar{s}\\) ",
            "d) \\(UCL = \\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_2 \\bar{s}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The formula of UCL for x bar and s chart construction when s is known, is given by\n\\(UCL = \\bar{\\bar{x}} + A_3 \\bar{s}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "For mean of all sample standard deviations=0.0094 and the sample size= 5, what will be the estimate of process standard deviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 0.01",
            "c) 0.0094",
            "d) 94"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that estimate of the process standard deviation,\n\\(\\hat{\\sigma} = \\frac{\\bar{s}}{c_4} \\) \nHere for sample size=5, c4=0.94, and s = 0.0094, we get σ = 0.01."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Which of this is a situation when x bar and s charts should be utilized instead of x bar and R charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When sample size is constant",
            "b) When sample standard deviation is less than 1",
            "c) When sample range is more than 1",
            "d) When sample size is variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is not necessary that process standard deviation is the mean of all sample deviations. This is because there is some inherent and natural variability in the process. This may or may not appear in every sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "When the sample size is variable, which one of these can be used to evaluate the value of x double bar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\( \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i \\bar{x_i}}{\\sum_{i=1}^n n_i}\\) ",
            "b) \\( \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n n_i \\bar{x_i}}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}\\) ",
            "c) \\( \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n n_i \\bar{x_i}}{\\sum_{i=1}^n n_i}\\) ",
            "d) \\( \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i \\bar{x_i}}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When sample size is variable, the formula to evaluate the process mean is given by,\n\\( \\bar{\\bar{x}} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i \\bar{x_i}}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which one of these is correct to evaluate the mean standard deviation of the process samples?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{s} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m (n_i-1) s_i^2}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{s} = \\left[\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m (n_i-1) s_i^2}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i-m}\\right]^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{s} = \\left[\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m (n_i-1) s_i^2}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i-m}\\right]^{1/2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{s} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m (n_i-1) s_i^2}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i-m}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mean of sample standard deviations in the case of variable sample size, is evaluated by following formula,\n\\(\\bar{s} = \\left[\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m (n_i-1) s_i^2}{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i-m}\\right]^{1/2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of these is taken as the sample size while estimating process standard deviation, where sample size is variable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ni; Which is the highest among all sample sizes",
            "b) ni; Which is the lowest among all sample sizes",
            "c) ni=5",
            "d) ni; Which is the most frequently occurring among all the sample sizes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When there are samples of variable sample sizes and we have to estimate process standard deviation, we use the sample size which is most frequenty occurring among all sample sizes."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The control charts based directly on the sample variance are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) s Control charts",
            "b) σ2 Control charts",
            "c) s2 Control charts",
            "d) x  Charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The variable control charts are based on the range method or standard deviation method, but some practitioners use charts based directly on the sample variance, which are called the s2 control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "What is the value of the center line of the sample variance control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{s}^2\\) ",
            "b) s2",
            "c) \\(\\bar{s}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\overline{s^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The center line in the case of sample variance control chart or s2 control chart denotes the value of \\(\\bar{s}^2\\)."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of these is a name of s control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) s2 Chart",
            "b) Process standard deviation chart",
            "c) σ Chart",
            "d) σ2 Chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The s chart or sample standard deviation chart is also called σ chart by some practitioners. This is based on the control limits set by calculations using the sample standard deviations."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The Shewhart control charts for sample size n=1 are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single Sample control charts",
            "b) Stationary control charts",
            "c) Control charts for zero variance",
            "d) Control charts for individual measurements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Shewhart control charts for sample size n=1 are called, Control charts for individual measurements. It has no basis of rational sub grouping in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "In the case of automatic manufacturing, the sample size is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) Greater than 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of automated inspection and measurement technology, every unit manufactured is analyzed and so there is no basis of rational sub grouping. So the sample size here, is 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "In the case of individuals control charts, which of these is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relative range",
            "b) Process standard deviation",
            "c) Mean of the highest observations",
            "d) Moving range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the case of individual measurements, we use the moving range of two successive observations as the basis of estimating the process variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "MR (Moving Range) is defined as",
        "Options": [
            "a) The difference of highest observation and the lowest observation",
            "b) The difference between any two successive observations",
            "c) The difference between the highest observation and mean of observations",
            "d) The difference between the lowest observation and mean of the observations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The difference between any two observations in the data is called the Moving range or MR of the two observations. This helps in estimation of the process variability in the case of the individuals control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression for the UCL for an Individuals Control Chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(\\bar{x}+\\frac{3\\overline{MR}}{d_2}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\bar{x}+\\frac{2\\overline{MR}}{d_2}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(\\bar{x}+\\frac{3\\overline{MR}}{d_3}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\bar{x}+\\frac{\\overline{MR}}{d_2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The UCL for any individuals control chart is given by the following expression,\nUCL=\\(\\bar{x}+\\frac{3\\overline{MR}}{d_2}\\)\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "The center line for any individuals control chart represents the value equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The process mean",
            "b) The moving range",
            "c) The mean of moving ranges",
            "d) The process standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The center line of any individuals control chart represents the value equal to x or the process mean for that particular process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "The value of ARL for any x bar control chart having 3-σ limits is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 482",
            "b) 310",
            "c) 370",
            "d) 270"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For any shewhart x bar control chart having 3 – sigma limits, we have p=0.0027. The average run length is calculated by formula,\n\\(ARL=\\frac{1}{p}=\\frac{1}{0.0027}=370\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The average number of points that must be plotted before an out-of-control point is plotted on an Individuals control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARL",
            "b) ATS",
            "c) MTBF",
            "d) Hazard rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average number of points that must be plotted before a point indicating an out-of-control situation is plotted, is called the Average run length of any control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "The ARL for any individuals control chart with the 1 sigma limits, and the β=0.972, is ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 6.3",
            "c) 43.96",
            "d) 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that for any individuals control chart,\nARL=\\(\\frac{1}{1-\\beta}\\) \nPutting the values of β=0.9772, we get ARL=43.96."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of this stands correct for the relation between the ARL for a shewhart control chart and the individual control chart ARL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARLindividual control chart=1/ ARLshewhart control chart",
            "b) ARLindividual control chart= ARLshewhart control chart",
            "c) ARLindividual control chart≪ARLshewhart control chart",
            "d) ARLindividual control chart≫ ARLshewhart control chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Average run length for any individuals control chart with 3 sigma limits is considerably lower than the value of Average run length for any Shewhart control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression for average moving range for any individuals control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\overline{MR} = \\sum_{i=2}^m \\frac{MR_i}{m-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\overline{MR} = \\sum_{i=1}^m \\frac{MR_i}{m}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\overline{MR} = \\sum_{i=2}^{m-1} \\frac{MR_i}{m-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\overline{MR} = \\sum_{i=1}^m \\frac{MR_i}{m-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average moving range for any individuals control chart is given by,\n\\(\\overline{MR} = \\sum_{i=2}^m \\frac{MR_i}{m-1}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The estimator of the process standard deviation for any individuals control chart is written as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\overline{MR}}{2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\overline{MR}/0.8865\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\overline{MR}/1.128\\) ",
            "d) \\(1.128\\overline{MR}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The estimation of the process standard deviation for any individuals control chart is written as,\n\\(\\widehat{σ_1}=\\overline{MR}/d_2\\) \nFor individuals control chart, n=2. For n=2, we have d2=1.128. So we get,\n\\(\\widehat{σ_1}=\\overline{MR}/1.128\\).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The estimation of the process standard deviation for any individuals control chart is expressed as ____ in the terms of sample standard deviation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\widehat{σ_2}=\\frac{s}{c_4}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\widehat{σ_2}=\\frac{s}{c_1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\widehat{σ_2}=\\frac{s}{c_2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\widehat{σ_2}=\\frac{s}{c_3}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The estimation of the process standard deviation for any individuals control chart is expressed as \\(\\widehat{σ_2}=\\frac{s}{c_4}\\) in the terms of sample standard deviation, s."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Defectives word has almost same meaning as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conforming",
            "b) Nonconforming",
            "c) Non-defective",
            "d) Un-conforming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A nonconforming item is an item which does not conform to the specifications defined for its quality characteristics. A defective is having almost same as the nonconforming item."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Quality characteristics which are related to only conforming or non conforming products, are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attributes",
            "b) Continuous characteristics",
            "c) Discrete characteristics",
            "d) Variables"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quality characteristics which are related to only conforming or non conforming products; are called attributes."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The control chart which relates to the fraction of defective product produced by a manufacturing process, is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The control chart for nonconformities",
            "b) Control charts for fraction nonconforming",
            "c) Control charts for conformities per unit",
            "d) Control chart for process mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The control charts which are related to the fraction of nonconforming or defective product produced by a manufacturing process is called the control chart for fraction nonconforming."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "The control chart for fraction nonconforming is also called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) u chart",
            "b) c chart",
            "c) p chart",
            "d) R chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The control chart for fraction nonconforming is also called p chart. This chart is plotted for the fraction of nonconforming products produced by a manufacturing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The control chart designed to deal with the defects or nonconformities of a product, is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) p chart",
            "b) c chart",
            "c) R chart",
            "d) s chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In some situations, it is more convenient to deal with the no of defects rather than the fraction nonconforming. The control charts designed for this purpose are called the c charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The c charts are also called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The control chart for nonconformities",
            "b) Control charts for fraction nonconforming",
            "c) Control charts for conformities per unit",
            "d) Control chart for process mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control charts which are made for the analysis of the defects in a product, are generally called the control charts for fraction nonconforming, or c charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "The control charts used for the analysis of nonconformities per unit of a product, are called _________ charts",
        "Options": [
            "a) p",
            "b) c",
            "c) x",
            "d) u"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The control charts useful in the situations where the average number of defects or conformities per unit, is more convenient basis for process control; are called the u charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "The u charts are also called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The control chart for nonconformities",
            "b) Control charts for fraction nonconforming",
            "c) Control charts for conformities per unit",
            "d) Control chart for process mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The control charts plotted for the conformities per unit are called u charts. They are helpful in the situations where average number of defectives is very important to determine process state."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "The ratio of the number of nonconforming items in a population to total number of items in that population, is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fraction nonconforming",
            "b) Fraction of nonconformities",
            "c) Fraction of conformities per unit of product",
            "d) Fraction of variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fraction nonconforming is delineated by the ratio of nonconforming items in a population to the total number of items in the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The sample fraction nonconforming is expressed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\hat{p}=\\frac{2D}{n}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\hat{p}=\\frac{D}{3n}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\hat{p}=\\frac{D}{2n}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\hat{p}=\\frac{D}{n}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sample fraction nonconforming is expressed by,\n\\(\\hat{p}=\\frac{D}{n}\\) \nWhere D is nonconforming units and n is the sample size."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The center line of control chart of fraction nonconforming represents the value equal to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fraction nonconforming",
            "b) Process mean",
            "c) Process standard deviation",
            "d) Sample mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The center line of the control chart of fraction nonconforming represents the value equal to the fraction nonconforming, i.e. the ratio between the number of nonconforming units to the total sample size."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "If there are 9 items defective in the sample size of 28, what will be the value that the fraction nonconforming chart, will represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2971",
            "b) 0.3214",
            "c) 0.6328",
            "d) 0.8172"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fraction nonconforming chart center line when standards are given, represents the value of fraction nonconforming which in this case, where m=1, D=9, n=28, is,\n\\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^m D_i]}{mn}=\\frac{9}{28}\\)=0.3214\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "If standards are not given, the estimate of the unknown fraction nonconforming of the process, is evaluated by formula ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^{m-1} D_i]}{m}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^{n-1} D_i]}{mn}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^{m} D_i]}{mn}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^{n} D_i]}{mn}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The estimation of the process’ unknown fraction nonconforming is done by taking average of all the sample fraction nonconforming(s), i.e. \\(\\bar{p}\\) \n\\(\\bar{p}=\\frac{[∑_{i=1}^{m} D_i]}{mn}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of these gives a correct equation for the general model for Shewhart control chart for a “w” quality characteristic statistic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL = μw + Lσw",
            "b) UCL = μw – Lσw",
            "c) LCL = μw + Lσw",
            "d) LCL = μw + σw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Upper control limit for constructing a Shewhart control chart for a quality characteristic w, we have;\nUCL = μw + Lσw."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "The value of L=3 in the genera model of control limits for a Shewhart control chart, explains ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are 3 sigma limits taken",
            "b) There are 3 quality characteristics",
            "c) There are 6 quality characteristics",
            "d) There are 6 sigma limits taken"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of L=3 in the general model of control limits for a Shewhart control chart signifies that there are 3 sigma limits taken, i.e. the 3 times shift of the standard deviation, of the mean will be measured on either side."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "When the Lower control limits for a p chart are less than zero, what is done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The value LCL<0 is utilized in control chart",
            "b) There is a certain constant C added to both UCL and LCL, i.e. UCLnew=UCLold+ C and LCLnew=LCLold+C",
            "c) There is certain constant value added to LCL only, i.e. LCLnew=LCLold+C",
            "d) LCL=0 is taken and assumed that control chart only has the upper control limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of LCL is taken to be zero when there is a value less than 0 found for LCL. It is also assumed that the control chart only has the upper control limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "LCL for any p chart when the standard values are given are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(p+\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(p+3 \\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(p-3\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(p-\\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LCL for any p chart or control chart for fraction nonconforming, when the standard values are given, are written as,\nLCL=\\(p-\\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The UCL for any p chart, when the standard values are not given, for 3 sigma limits, is written as ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(\\bar{p}+\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\bar{p} – \\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(\\bar{p}+\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\bar{p}-\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The upper control limit for a 3 sigma limit p-chart is expressed by\nUCL=\\(\\bar{p}+\\sqrt[3]{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) \nwhen the standard values are not given."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "What is done when there is a sample plotted out of control limits for a p-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sample is investigated for an assignable cause and then the sample data is eliminated to develop a new p-chart",
            "b) The sample is only investigated for an assignable cause",
            "c) The sample is not investigated at all (It is assumed that there was no assignable cause present)",
            "d) All the samples are investigated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a sample plots out of control in p-chart, it is investigated for an assignable cause and then the sample data is eliminated to develop a new p-chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Even if the process is in control according to p-chart and the fraction nonconforming is too high, it states that _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The process is not stable",
            "b) The process is stable but there are no operator controllable problems",
            "c) The process is stable but there are some operator controllable problems",
            "d) The process is out of control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the process is in control according to p chart but the fraction nonconforming is too high, it states that the process is stable with no operator controllable problems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "If the fraction nonconforming for 7 samples are 0.11,0.24,0.21,0.14,0.24,0.21,0.17, what is the value for the center line for a p-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.19",
            "b) 0.21",
            "c) 0.12",
            "d) 0.13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The center line of a p chart represents the average of the all the fraction nonconforming. This means,\n\\(CL=\\bar{p}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=0}^n p_i}{n}\\) \nThis gives, CL=0.19 for the above question."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "If the sample size for a p-chart is 50 and the value for the center line of the chart is 0.2313, what will be the value of the LCL of the chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4108",
            "b) 0.0524",
            "c) 0.0762",
            "d) 0.0389"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The LCL of the p chart is given by expression,\nLCL=\\(p-\\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) \nWhen we put the value of CL=p=0.2313, we get LCL=0.0524."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "The control limits for p-chart found from the use of estimated unknown fraction non conforming, are regarded as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Final limits",
            "b) Concluded limits",
            "c) Trial limits",
            "d) Absolute limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The control limits for p chart, which are not found using the standard values of p, are generally regarded as trial limits. The finalized limits are calculated by first implementing the trial limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the parameters which need to be specified for fraction nonconforming control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample Size",
            "b) Frequency of sampling",
            "c) Width of control limits",
            "d) Units to be produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: the fraction nonconforming chart has 3 parameters which need to be specified: the sample size, the frequency of sampling, and the width of control limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "If δ is the magnitude of the process shift, n must specify __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\delta=nL\\sqrt{\\frac{pn(1-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\delta=nL\\sqrt{\\frac{p(n-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\delta=L\\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\delta=L\\sqrt{\\frac{np(1-np)}{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The magnitude of process shift and the sample size n must satisfy,\n\\(\\delta=L\\sqrt{\\frac{p(1-p)}{n}}\\) \nfor a process to be in control."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Which of these is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(n=(\\frac{L}{\\delta})^2 p(1-p)\\) ",
            "b) \\(n=(\\frac{L}{\\delta})^2 p(1-np)\\) ",
            "c) \\(n=(\\frac{L}{\\delta})^2 (1-p)\\) ",
            "d) \\(n=(\\frac{L}{\\delta})^2 p(1+p)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value for sample size of a p-chart is determined by the following expression,\n\\(n=(\\frac{L}{\\delta})^2 p(1-p)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "For LCL for the p-chart to be higher than zero, what condition should the sample size fulfill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(n>\\left[\\frac{(1-p) L^2}{p}\\right] \\) ",
            "b) \\(n>\\left[\\frac{(1-p) L^2}{2p}\\right] \\) ",
            "c) \\(n<\\left[\\frac{(1-p) L^2}{2p}\\right] \\) ",
            "d) \\(n<\\left[\\frac{(1-p) L^2}{p}\\right] \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the LCL of the p-chart to be higher than zero, the sample size n should fulfill the following condition.\n\\(n>\\left[\\frac{(1-p) L^2}{p}\\right] \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "For what value of sample size, will the p-chart will have a LCL value higher than 0 when p=0.05 and 3 sigma limits are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) n>121",
            "b) n>100",
            "c) n>125",
            "d) n>171"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know for a p chart having LCL value higher than zero, we have,\n\\(n>\\frac{1-p}{p}*L^2 \\) \nFor p=0.05 and L=3, we get, n>171."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "For narrower limits of control, which of this is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chart becomes insensitive to small shift",
            "b) Chart becomes more sensitive to small shift but gives false alarms",
            "c) Chart becomes more sensitive to small shift but gives accurate alarms",
            "d) Chart gives no alarms at all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the narrower limits like 1-sigma limits or 2 – sigma limits are chosen for p-chart, the chart becomes more sensitive to small shifts. But in addition, it also gives more numbers of false alarms."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "If the probability of a unit being conforming or nonconforming, depends on the previous unit being conforming or nonconforming, can p-chart be applied on the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yes",
            "b) No",
            "c) This depends on the sample size",
            "d) This depends on the operator changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In processes where nonconforming units are clustered, i.e. the probability of one unit to be conforming or nonconforming depends on the previous unit being defective or not, p-chart can’t be applied to them, as p-charts are designed on the basis of binomial probability or independent trials."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "The number nonconforming chart is also called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) np-chart",
            "b) p-chart",
            "c) c-chart",
            "d) s-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number nonconforming chart is also called the np-chart. This uses the number of nonconforming items in a sample instead of the fraction nonconforming."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The center line of the np-control chart represents the value equal to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) p",
            "b) p",
            "c) np",
            "d) 1-np"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The center line of the np chart or the number nonconforming chart represents the value equal to np or np."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "If the p=0.2313 for a np chart, and the number of items in a sample are 50, what will be the center line value of the np chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.34",
            "b) 11.56",
            "c) 10.11",
            "d) 13.21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line of the np chart represents the value equal to,\nCL=np\nHere, n=50 and p=0.2313, putting these values in the CL value, we get, CL=11.565."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "For a control chart data having the average sample fraction nonconforming= 0.2313 and the sample size=50, what will be the value of the UCL for the np control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.62",
            "b) 20.510",
            "c) 11.56",
            "d) 11.892"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that for a np chart,\nUCL=\\(n\\bar{p}+3\\sqrt{n\\bar{p} (1-\\bar{p})}\\) \nPutting the values, we get, UCL=20.51."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What is the expression to calculate the variable-width control limits for the p-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{p} \\pm \\frac{1}{2} \\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{p} \\pm \\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{p} \\pm 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{p} \\pm \\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: The variable-width control limits of the p-chart, when the sample size is varying, are,\n\\(\\bar{p} \\pm 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "For a process, there are 25 samples taken from its output of variable sample size. There are total 234 defects in all the samples combined. If the total of all the sample sizes is 2450, what will be the value of the UCL in the case of variable-width control limits of p-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(0.096+3\\sqrt{0.096*\\frac{0.904}{n_i}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(0.087+3\\sqrt{0.087*\\frac{0.913}{n_i}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(0.096-3\\sqrt{0.096*\\frac{0.904}{n_i}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(0.087-3\\sqrt{0.087*\\frac{0.913}{n_i}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The UCL of variable-width control limits of p-chart is written as,\n\\(\\bar{p} + 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/n_i}\\) \nHere \\(\\bar{p} = \\frac{234}{2450}\\)=0.096. Putting this value in UCL formula, we get,\n\\(0.096+3\\sqrt{0.096*\\frac{0.904}{n_i}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which one of these is not a method to plot the variable sample size data on p-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable-width control limits",
            "b) Control limits based on average sample size",
            "c) Tolerance diagram",
            "d) Standardized Control Chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The three approaches to deal with variable sample size are: variable-width control limits, control limits based on average sample size, and standardized control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "In the case of average sample size based control limits, which of these states the correct expression for average sample size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{∑_{i=0}^m n_i}{m}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{∑_{i=1}^m n_i}{m}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{∑_{i=1}^m n_i}{m-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{∑_{i=1}^m n_i}{1-m}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average sample size in the case of control limits based on average sample size, is expressed by,\n\\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{∑_{i=1}^m n_i}{m}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The approximate upper control limit calculated for control chart limits based on an average sample size, is expressed by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(\\bar{p} + 0.5\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/\\bar{n}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\bar{p} + \\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/\\bar{n}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(\\bar{p} – 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/\\bar{n}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\bar{p} + 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/\\bar{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The approximate upper control limit for control limits of p-chart based on an average sample size, is expressed by,\nUCL=\\(\\bar{p} + 3\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})/\\bar{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The standardized control chart has the center line at ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 σ",
            "b) 2 σ",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) -1σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standardized control chart used for control charts for fraction nonconforming with variable sample size, has its center line at the value zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "To deal with the variable sample size, the standardized chart is used, which has its upper limit at ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) -3",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standardized control chart, which has been used over quite some time to handle the situations of variable sample size, has its upper limit at +3."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "A type II error is also called a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) α Error",
            "b) δ Error",
            "c) β Error",
            "d) ∅ Error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A type II error is concluding a process in-control when it is actually in out-of-control state. A type II error is also called an β error. "
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "An OC curve is a display of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) β Error against defectives in a process output over a limited period of time",
            "b) β Error against time",
            "c) β Error against the process fraction nonconforming",
            "d) Fraction nonconforming against β Error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An OC curve or Operation characteristic curve for a p-chart is a graphical representation of β Error against the process fraction nonconforming computed."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "ARL (Average run length) for the fraction nonconforming control chart, is calculated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARl=1/β",
            "b) ARL=β/α",
            "c) ARL=1/βn",
            "d) ARL=\\(\\frac{1}{probability\\, of \\,sample \\,point\\, plots\\, out\\, of\\, control}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The average run lengths for the fraction nonconforming control charts are calculated by the following formula,\nARL=\\(\\frac{1}{probability\\, of \\,sample \\,point\\, plots\\, out\\, of\\, control}\\)."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "If the process is in control, the ARL for the fraction nonconforming chart, is calculated by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ARL_0=\\frac{1}{\\alpha}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ARL_0=\\frac{1}{1-\\alpha}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ARL_0=\\frac{\\beta}{\\alpha}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ARL_0=\\frac{1}{\\alpha \\beta}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average run length, for the process of Fraction nonconforming control chart for processes in-control, is expressed by,\nARL0=1/α."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "If the for a fraction nonconforming chart, the probability of a sample point plotting out of control is 0.0531, what will be the ARL for this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12.31",
            "b) 8.16",
            "c) 18.83",
            "d) 22.78"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fraction nonconforming chart which has the probability of a sample point plotting out of control as p, the ARL is given by,\nARL = 1⁄p\nPutting p=0.0531, ARL=18.83."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "If a process is out of control, what will be its ARL for the fraction nonconforming chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ARL_1=\\frac{1}{1-β}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ARL_1=\\frac{1-β}{1+β}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ARL_1=\\frac{1}{1+β}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ARL_1=\\frac{1+β}{1-β}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the process is out of control, it has possibility of β error. The Average run length for the fraction nonconforming chart of this process, is calculated by following formula,\n\\(ARL_1=\\frac{1}{1-β}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "If type II error probability for a process is 0.8594, its ARL will be ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know,\n\\(ARL_1=\\frac{1}{1-β}\\) \nWe have, β=0.8594, so ARL1≅7 "
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The event of a specification not satisfied at one point of a product, is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nonconformity",
            "b) Non-defectiveness",
            "c) Un-specification",
            "d) Non-specification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each event, in which a specification is not satisfied or an error occurs in approaching the specification value, is called nonconformity or a defect."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "A nonconforming item has at least ____________ conformities.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A nonconforming item is defined as the item or product, which has at least one defect. It is necessary that a nonconforming item has one or more than one defects."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "The c-control chart is plotted for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fraction nonconforming",
            "b) Number of nonconformities per unit",
            "c) Number of defects observed",
            "d) Deviation from median of the defects in samples"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The c-control chart is based on the total number of nonconformities in a product unit of a process output. So a c-chart is also called control chart for nonconformities."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of these is an assumption made for designing a control chart for noncorformities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal Distribution",
            "b) Poisson Distribution",
            "c) Lognormal Distribution",
            "d) Weibull Distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The control charts for nonconformities, make an assumption that the sample taken is well modeled by the Poisson distribution. This is a necessary assumption to deal with these control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an assumption of the c-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of potential locations for nonconformities should be large",
            "b) Probability of occurrence of nonconformities should be small",
            "c) Probability of occurrence of nonconformities should be variable",
            "d) Probability of occurrence of nonconformities should be constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The assumption of Poisson distribution of nonconformities in the samples of constant size, for c-charts, makes it necessary that, number of potential locations for nonconformities should be large, and the probability of occurrence of nonconformities should be small and constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What will be the value of the 3-sigma Upper control limit for the c chart when standard is given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL = c + 3√c",
            "b) UCL = c – √c",
            "c) UCL = c + √c",
            "d) UCL = c + 2√c"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 3 – sigma upper control limit for the c-chart is expressed algebraically by\nUCL = c + √c."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "The center line for the control chart for nonconformities is representing the value equal c, which is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The total number of nonconformities",
            "b) The average number of conformities in a preliminary sample",
            "c) The total number of nonconforming products",
            "d) The total number of conforming products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If there is no standard given for the c-chart, the center line represents the estimation of standard, c which is equal to the average number of nonconformities in a preliminary sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "When there is no standard given, the value of LCL for the c-chart is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(\\bar{c}-3\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(\\bar{c}+2\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(\\bar{c}-2\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(\\bar{c}+3\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When there is no standard given for the number of conformities (c), for the c chart, the lower control limit is given by,\nLCL=\\(\\bar{c}+3\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "If the average number of nonconformities in a preliminary sample of a process is 19.67, which of these represents the value of UCL for a c-chart for this process output?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 19.67",
            "b) 6.37",
            "c) 32.97",
            "d) 25.77"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The UCL for the c-chart is given by,\nUCL=\\(\\bar{c}-3\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) \nNow UCL=32.97."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "For c=13.11, what will be the value of LCL for the c-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 23.97",
            "b) 10.86",
            "c) 8.84",
            "d) 2.24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LCL for c-chart is expressed by\nLCL=\\(\\bar{c}+3\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) \nPutting c=13.11, we get LCL for the control chart for nonconformities = 2.24. "
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "With c-chart, which of these is used to analyze nonconformity data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X bar charts",
            "b) R charts",
            "c) Cause and Effect diagram",
            "d) Tolerance Diagram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The c-chart is usually used to analyze the nonconformity data to get more information about the process state. Cause and effect diagram are also a good way to analyze nonconformity data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "The control chart used to inspect the process state by using the average number of nonconformities per unit data, is called _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) u-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) R-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control chart, which uses the average number of nonconformities per unit data to analyze the process state, is generally termed as the Control chart for Average number of Nonconformities per Unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "If xi=total number of nonconformities in a sample of ni inspection units, and there are N samples of different sample size, and x varies according to a Poisson distribution, what will be the value of center line of the u-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{u} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{2x_i}{n_i}}{N}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{u} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{x_i}{2n_i}}{2N}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{u} =  \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{x_i}{n_i}}{N}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{u} = \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{x_i}{n_i}}{2N}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As u-chart uses the value of the average number of nonconformities per unit, the center line of the u-chart is given by,\n\\(\\bar{u} =  \\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^N \\frac{x_i}{n_i}}{N}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Count rate of a defect is defined as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defects per unit",
            "b) Average number of defects per unit",
            "c) Total number of nonconformities",
            "d) Occurrence of n defects in N number of units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a control chart for nonconformities, sample size can be greater than 1. This increases the area of opportunity for the occurrence of nonconformities. This can be used to obtain a positive lower control limit also."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "The 3 – sigma upper limit for a control chart for average number of nonconformities per unit, is expressed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(\\bar{u} + 3\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\bar{u} – 3\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(\\bar{u} – 2\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\bar{u} – \\frac{3}{2} \\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 3 – sigma upper control limit for a control chart for average number of nonconformities per unit,  is expressed by the following expression.\nUCL=\\(\\bar{u} + 3\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "If the average number of nonconformities per unit per sample is 0.074, what will be the lower control limit for the u-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0414",
            "b) 0.0221",
            "c) 0.0",
            "d) -0.0513"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lower control limit for the u-chart is expressed by,\nLCL = \\(\\bar{u} – 3\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\) \nPutting \\(\\bar{u}\\)=0.074 we get, LCL=-0.0414. As LCL is less than 0, we use LCL=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The control chart for total number of events is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) g-charts",
            "b) R-charts",
            "c) h-charts",
            "d) c-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control charts, which are developed for the total number of events, are called the g-charts. They were first developed by Kaminski et al in 1992. "
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The control charts developed for the average number of events is generally called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) g-chart",
            "b) h-chart",
            "c) s-chart",
            "d) s-square-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The control charts, which are based on the average number of events data, are called the h-charts. They were also developed by Kaminski et al."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "What will be the center line value for a Kaminski et al h-chart when standards are given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{1-p}{p}-a\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{1+p}{p}+a\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{1+p}{p}-a\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The center line value for the Kaminski et al h-chart is given by the equation,\nCL = \\(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is the value of the Upper control limit for the g-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}-a)+L\\sqrt{n(1-p)}{p^2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)+L\\sqrt{n(1+p)}{p^2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)+L\\sqrt{n(1-p)}{p^2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)+L\\sqrt{(1-p)}{p^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of upper limit for the g chart given by Kaminski et al is,\n\\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)+L\\sqrt{n(1-p)}{p^2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "What is the value of the center line of g-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(n(\\frac{1+p}{p}+a)\\) ",
            "b) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)\\) ",
            "c) \\(n(\\frac{1+p}{p}-a)\\) ",
            "d) \\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}-a)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line value for the g-chart construction is calculated by following formula,\n\\(n(\\frac{1-p}{p}+a)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "What is the value of center line of g-chart when there is no standard given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{t}+3\\sqrt{\\bar{t}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{t}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{t}-3\\sqrt{\\bar{t}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{t}+0.5\\sqrt{\\bar{t}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center line value for the g-chart, when there is no standard given is given by,\nCl=\\(\\bar{t}=\\frac{t_1+t_2+t_3+⋯+t_m}{m}\\) \nwhere t1, t2, t3,…,tm  are the total numbers of events in m subgroups each."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "What is the center line value for the average number of events control chart, when there is no standard given?",
        "Options": [
            "a) t/n",
            "b) 2t/3n",
            "c) 2 t/n",
            "d)  t/2n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The center line value for the average number of events control chart or h-chart, when there is no standard given, is expressed by,\nCL= t/n."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of these is used in the standardized chart for u-chart with variable sample size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zi",
            "b) Mi",
            "c) Ui",
            "d) Ai"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the standardized control chart for a u-chart with variable sample size, the construction of the standardized control chart requires plotting a standard statistic written as Zi."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What is the value of Zi in the standardized control chart for u-chart with variable sample size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{u_i+\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{\\bar{n}}}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{u_i+\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n_i}}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{u_i-\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n_i}}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{u_i-\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{\\bar{n}}}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of a standard statistic used to plot the standardized chart for the u-chart with a variable sample size, is written as,\n\\(\\frac{u_i-\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n_i}}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "What is the Upper control limit for the standardized control chart for u-chart with variable sample size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The upper control limit for the standardized control chart, which is designed for u-chart with variable sample size, is generally set to value 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "The center line of the standardized control chart designed for u-chart, is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) -3",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The center line for the standardized control chart is set to zero. That is why this control chart is named the standardized control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "The OC curve of the c-chart is a curve which plots β-risk against _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of defectives per sample",
            "b) True mean number of defects",
            "c) Total number of defects",
            "d) Demerits per unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Upper and lower control limits of the standardized control chart designed for u-chart with variable sample size, have a value of 3 and -3, respectively.  So the distance between them is 6 units."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "If there is variable sample size to be used with the u-chart or average number of nonconformity per unit chart, which of these methods, is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DMAIC",
            "b) Designing of Experiments",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Standardized control chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the sample size is variable, for a u-chart, the method of using the standardized chart is used to deal with the variable sample size. This makes it easy to use all the sample size data with the nonconformity data."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The method of average sample size is used when there is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable sample size",
            "b) Constant sample size",
            "c) Sample size=1",
            "d) Sample Size=10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the sample size is variable and the u-chart or the control chart for nonconformity data is to be used, the approach of average sample size is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "In the average sample size approach to design u-chart with variable sample size, which of these is used to calculate the average sample size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=0}^m n_i}{m}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m u_i}{2m}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}{m}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^n u_i}{m}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average sample size for the u-chart with variable sample size is calculated using the following formula,\n\\(\\bar{n}=\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^m n_i}{m}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "In a demerit system for defects, how many classes are defined for defects to be classified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The demerit system for attribute data; classifies the defects in 4 classes; class A, class B, Class C, and Class D."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Serious defects are put into which class according to the Demerit system for attribute data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class C",
            "b) Class D",
            "c) Class A",
            "d) Class B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Serious Defects are put into the class B. In serious defects reduce the effective life of the component or increase the maintenance costs to be applied for the use of that component."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "The Class A defects are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moderate",
            "b) Minor",
            "c) Serious",
            "d) Very Serious"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The class A defects contains all the defects which are very serious to be present in the part. These defects either make the part totally unfit for use or will fail in service causing property damage with it."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "The minor defects are put into class ____________ of the demerit system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) C",
            "d) D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minor defects are the defects which do not affect the service of part effectively. They are classified in the Class D of the Demerit system for attribute data."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The minor finish, appearance, or quality of work defects are generally classified in _____ of the demerit system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class A",
            "b) Class D",
            "c) Class C",
            "d) Class B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minor defects in finish, quality of work, and appearance are generally not serious. They do not affect the life of product effectively. So they are classified into class D of the demerit system."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Moderate defects are classified into which class of demerit system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class B",
            "b) Class C",
            "c) Class D",
            "d) Class A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moderate defects are the defects which cause trouble that is less serious than operating failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The number of demerits in a system having ciA,ciB,ciC,and ciD  defects in classes A, B, C, and D respectively is expressed by ______ It is assumed that the probability of each defect varies according to a Poisson distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) di = 100ciD + 50ciB + 10ciC + ciA",
            "b) di = 100ciA + 50ciB + 10ciC + ciD",
            "c) di = 100ciB + 50ciA + 10ciC + ciD",
            "d) di = 100ciA + 50ciC + 10ciB + ciD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of demerits in a system is expressed by the following expression.\ndi = 100ciA + 50ciB + 10ciC + ciD."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "If there are 8, 12, 11, 3, 6 demerits in sample number 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 respectively, what will be the demerits per units for the mentioned output?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The demerits per unit are calculated by using the following formula,\n\\(u_i=\\frac{D}{n}\\) \nWhere D=\\(\\sum_{i=1}^n d_i\\) = 40 and n=5. We get ui=8\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The upper control limit for the demerits per unit chart is given by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL = \\(\\bar{u}-3\\widehat{σ_u}\\) ",
            "b) UCL = \\(\\bar{u}+3\\widehat{σ_u}\\) ",
            "c) UCL = \\(\\bar{u}+\\widehat{σ_u}\\) ",
            "d) UCL = \\(\\bar{u}-\\widehat{σ_u}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The upper control limit for the demerits per unit chart is given by the following formula,\nUCL = \\(\\bar{u}+3\\widehat{σ_u}\\) \nWhere \\(\\bar{u}=100\\overline{u_A}+50\\overline{u_B}+10\\overline{u_C}+\\overline{u_D}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "What is the value of the center line of the demerits per unit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{u}+3\\sqrt{\\bar{u}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{u}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{u}+\\frac{1}{2}\\sqrt{\\bar{u}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{u}-3\\sqrt{\\bar{u}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the center line of the demerits per unit chart is given by,\nCL = u\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "The defects which affect the proper working of the unit in the service arena, are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Appearance Defects",
            "b) Functional Defects",
            "c) Specification Defects",
            "d) Aspect defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The defect which makes the unit totally unfit for use, is called a very serious defect, and it is categorized in Class A demerit of the demerit system of the attribute data."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "The number of defects per unit of a casting process output, is plotted on _____________ chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) x bar",
            "b) s-chart",
            "c) u-chart",
            "d) p-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average number of defects or nonconformities per unit of a process output is always plotted on a u-chart or the control chart for average number of nonconformities per unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "What type of control chart can be used to plot “number of defectives in the output of a process for making a machine part” data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) u-chart",
            "d) s-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The p-chart or the Control Chart for Fraction Nonconforming is used to plot “the number of defectives in the output of any manufacturing process” data, on a control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Which of the control chart is used to find out variability in the data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) s-chart",
            "b) x-chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) c-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: s-chart or the control charts based on the sample standard deviation, are a useful method to find out the variability in the data. They are only used for Variable data, not for attribute data."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of the charts are more efficient to find out variability in the data when the sample size is more than 10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) s-chart",
            "d) p-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To find out variability in the data, R-charts and s-charts are used. But when the sample size is more than 10 or 12, the efficiency of s-charts to find variability in the data, is more than the R-charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of these is an advantage of attribute control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Much useful information about the process performance can be gathered",
            "b) Mean and variability is obtained directly",
            "c) One quality characteristic is observed at a time",
            "d) Several quality characteristics can be considered jointly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The attribute control charts have a main advantage of consideration of many quality characteristics to be jointly analyzed. This is because a defect can be produced by one or more quality characteristics, which are out of control."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of these is an advantage of variable control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Numerous quality characteristics considered at a time",
            "b) To achieve the information very easily about the mean and variability",
            "c) To have analyses of units nonconforming",
            "d) To analyze the defects in one unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main advantage of a variable control chart is that they provide much useful information about the process performance. They give more functional information about the process mean and variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "X bar and R charts are __________ indicators of trouble.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trailing",
            "b) Inferior",
            "c) Leading",
            "d) Secondary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: x and R charts are leading indicators of trouble in the process. We conclude this because; they indicate the out-of-control process before the process has made defective products, unlike p-chart, which indicates the out-of control process after the process has made defectives."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The efficiency of variable control charts is _________ the efficiency of the p-charts when p is small and far away from 0.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lesser than",
            "b) More than",
            "c) Equal to",
            "d) Non-predictable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The efficiency of variable control charts is considerable higher than the efficiency of the p-charts when the value of p is small or away from 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The efficiency of p-charts is __________ the efficiency of the x bar and R charts when p is closer to 0.5.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to",
            "b) More than",
            "c) Less than",
            "d) Non-predictable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The efficiency of p-charts become higher or just more than the efficiency of x-bar and R charts, when the value of p comes closer to 0.5 or higher than 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of these is most economical in long term?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x And R charts",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) u-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The variable charts are more economical in long term, because they indicate process state out-of-control, before we have paid to make a nonconforming product. Attribute charts become costly because the same indication from them comes, when defectives are already produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "When a change in product specification is desired, which of these control charts should be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) x And R charts",
            "c) c-charts",
            "d) u-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The variable control charts should be used whenever a new process is coming on stream, or a new product is being manufactured by an existing process, or a change in product specification is desired."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "When we want to troubleshoot the out-of-control process, we use _________ control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) x",
            "b) p",
            "c) c",
            "d) u"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Whenever a process is out-of-control and it is known to us, we use variable control charts to troubleshoot the process. It is because; we can focus on each quality characteristic individually using variable control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "In regulated industries, where process stability and process capability must be continually demonstrated __________ charts are used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) x And s",
            "b) p",
            "c) c",
            "d) u"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A regulated industry needs continuous information about the process stability and capability. As variable control charts are more efficient to find out these, they are used in the regulated industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of these is a condition where attributes control charts should be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) New product manufacturing from existing process",
            "b) Troubleshooting a out-of-control process",
            "c) When it is necessary to reduce process fallout",
            "d) Change in product specification is required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When it is necessary to reduce process fallout, and when the operators control the assignable causes, Attributes control charts are chosen over the Variables control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "When the process is a complex assembly operation, and the product quality can only be judged in terms of occurrence of nonconformities, the ______ are more helpful.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only x Charts",
            "b) R-charts",
            "c) s-charts",
            "d) p-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the process is a complex assembly operation and the product quality is assessed only on basis of occurrence of defects, the p-charts are more helpful."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "When process needs to be controlled but the measurement data cannot be obtained, the control charts to be formed are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) Only x Charts",
            "c) s-charts",
            "d) R-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When process needs to be controlled but the measurement data can’t be acquired, the attributes charts are the better choice than the variables control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "When there are very tight specifications, overlapping assembly tolerances problems, which of the control charts are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attributes control charts",
            "b) Variables control charts",
            "c) Both, attributes control charts and the variables control charts can be used",
            "d) Neither one of attributes or variables control charts can be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Variable control charts are more favored when there are very tight specifications, overlapping assembly tolerances problems. This is because variables control charts deal better with specifications of quality characteristics than the attributes control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "When destructive testing is required, which type of control should be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) x And R charts",
            "d) u-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When destructive testing is required or any other expensive testing procedure is needed, variable control charts are more suitable than the attributes control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "When attributes charts are used when _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Destructive testing is required",
            "b) Process must be continuously stabilized and monitored for its capability",
            "c) Historical summary of process performance is needed",
            "d) Existing process but in chronic trouble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When historical summary of process performance is needed for the variables control charts, attributes control charts are used to develop the summary data."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "When there is a need to reduce acceptance-sampling or other downstream testing to a minimum when the process can be operated in-control, which type of control charts should be preferred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attributes control chart",
            "b) Variable control chart",
            "c) Both can be used",
            "d) None of the both types can be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the acceptance sampling is to be reduced to minimum, the variables charts reveal better results and efficiency than the attributes control chart. "
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Which of these does not require SPC implementation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When Specifications change without notice",
            "b) When customer demands both control and capability",
            "c) When process is stable",
            "d) When the process is estimated to reduce its capability in near future"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SPC implementation is required when the specifications change without notice, and customer demands both control and capability, and when the process is predicted to reduce its capability in near future."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "When it is inconvenient to obtain more than one measurement per sample output of any process, which of these is the best choice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x bar and R charts",
            "b) x bar and s charts",
            "c) c-charts",
            "d) Control charts for individuals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The times when, it is inconvenient or impossible to obtain more than one measurement per sample, or repeat measurements will only be affected by lab or analysis error, the control charts for individuals are the best choice, e.g.  Often in chemical processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of these should be carried out if the process is in-control and capable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SPC only",
            "b) Experimental design",
            "c) Change process",
            "d) Investigate specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the process currently studied is in control and also capable, the control and capability of the process are maintained as it is, by using the statistical process control only."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Process capability refers to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changes in process",
            "b) Variability in process",
            "c) Uniformity in process",
            "d) Unevenness in process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Process capability refers to the uniformity of the process. This uniformity in the process is always measured in the terms of the variability in the processs."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The process of usage of statistical methods to determine the variability in a process and to reduce or completely eliminating the variability, is called ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process capability",
            "b) Process capability Analysis",
            "c) Process variability",
            "d) Process variability analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The method of using the statistical methods to determine the variability in a process and to reduce it to the minimum level, is generally known as the Process Capability Analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Determining process capability is an important part of _____________ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analyze",
            "b) Define",
            "c) Control",
            "d) Measure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Determining process capability is an important part of analyze step of DMAIC process. It is generally done in the analyze step majorly but it is also used in improve step."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of these is used as the measure of process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process mean",
            "b) Process standard deviation",
            "c) Sample standard deviation",
            "d) Six-sigma spread in the distribution of the product quality characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is customary to take the six – sigma distribution of the product quality characteristic, as the measure of the process capability, in the process capability analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "For a six–sigma spread in the distribution of the product quality characteristic, the upper natural control limit will fall at _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ + 2σ",
            "b) μ + 3σ",
            "c) μ + 4σ",
            "d) μ + 6σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For six sigma distribution of the product quality characteristic, the upper natural tolerance control limit will fall at,\nUNTL = μ + 3σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "μ – 3σ, is the LNTL for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-sigma spread in distribution of CTQ characteristic",
            "b) 1-sigma spread in distribution of CTQ characteristic",
            "c) 6-sigma spread in distribution of CTQ characteristic",
            "d) 4-sigma spread in distribution of CTQ characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The six-sigma spread in the distribution of the CTQ characteristic of a process, is generally having its lower natural tolerance limit at,\nLNTL = μ – 3σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "0.27 percent outside the normal tolerances can be obtained using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6-sigma both sides of mean",
            "b) 3-sigma both sides of mean",
            "c) 2-sigma both sides of mean",
            "d) 8-sigma both sides of mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When there is NTL (s) of μ±3σ, i.e. 3-sigma both sides of the mean of the variable, the 99.73% products are between the specification limit. So there are 0.27% outside the normal tolerances."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": " Which of these is not necessary to find the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean",
            "b) Standard deviation",
            "c) Spread",
            "d) Design of Experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the process capability analysis, we need to have the following to start the study; mean of the process, spread or the standard deviation of the process, and the specified shape of the probability distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "When we don’t have the mean, spread and the shape of probability distribution of one CTQ characteristic of a process, we can use ___________ for process capability analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) Design of experiment",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) Specifications on the quality characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case we don’t have any information about the mean, spread and the shape of the probability distribution of one CTQ characteristic of a process, we can use specifications on the CTQ characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a major use of the PCA (Process Capability Analysis)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prediction of how well the process will hold the tolerances",
            "b) Reduction of variability in process",
            "c) Establishing an interval between sampling",
            "d) Stating the need of the Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCA or the Process Capability Analysis is used to predict how well the process will hold the tolerance and to reduce the variability. It also gives us an interval between sampling."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "When in PCA, we have only the sample unit of product without any direct observation of the process or the time history of the production, the PCA is also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Product inspection",
            "b) Product characterization",
            "c) Product sampling",
            "d) Process design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the studies of PCA, when we have availability of only the sample units of product without any direct observation of the process or the time history of the production, PCA study is now called Product Characterization. "
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "In product characterization, we cannot say anything about _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic behavior of the process",
            "b) Distribution of quality characteristic",
            "c) Process yield",
            "d) Fraction conforming to specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In product characterization, we can only state the process yield information or the information about the distribution of the product quality characteristic or the fraction conforming to specifications data."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the primary techniques used to find out the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Probability plots",
            "c) Control charts",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Histogram or probability plots, control charts and designed experiments are the 3 primary techniques used to find out process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "PCA (process capability analysis) can’t be used _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the process state of statistical control",
            "b) To reduce the variability in the process",
            "c) For specifying the location of defect",
            "d) For modifying or selecting a process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PCA can’t be used to specify the location of defect. It can be used to determine the process state, to reduce the variability present in it and to select or modify any process."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "How many primary techniques are there which are used in PCA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 3 primary techniques, which are used in process capability analysis. These are; histogram or probability plots, control charts, and designed experiments."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Which can be used as an alternative for histogram for PCA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Check sheet",
            "b) Defect concentration diagram",
            "c) Stem-and-Leaf Plot",
            "d) Scatter Diagram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stem-and-leaf plots can be used alternatively for the process capability analysis, instead of using the histogram plots. It needs almost more than 100 observations."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "How many observations are needed at least, to plot a histogram which gives proper information about the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 120",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There must be at least 100 observations or more, to plot a histogram or a stem-and-leaf plot to be stable enough, which gives efficient information about the process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Which of these is needed with the histogram to estimate the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) Scatter diagram",
            "c) Sample average",
            "d) Check sheet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The histogram, when used along with the sample average x and sample standard deviation s, provides the sufficient information about the process capability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which is not an advantage of histogram to check the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immediate impression of process",
            "b) Visual impression of process",
            "c) Fast interpretation",
            "d) Easy to find the location of defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By using the histogram, to determine the process capability, we can get an immediate and visual impression of process. We can also interpret the data very quickly. But it cannot tell the location of defects."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "When the number of product units outside the LSL and the number of product units outside USL are same, the process is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centered process with poor process capability",
            "b) Centered process with great process capability",
            "c) Poorly centered process with poor process capability",
            "d) Poorly centered process with great process capability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the numbers of product units outside the LSL, and the USL, are same. This means the process is centered, but there are some product units lying outside the specification limits. This gives poor process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Probability plotting is an alternative of _________ to find process capability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) Histogram",
            "c) Designed experiments",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Probability plotting is an alternative to the histogram to find out the capability of the process which produces the product, which is to be used in the industry."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Probability plotting is not used to find __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The shape of distribution",
            "b) The center of distribution",
            "c) The spread of distribution",
            "d) The origin of defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By using the probability plots instead of the histogram, find out the process capability, we can determine the shape, center, and the spread of the distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Which is more efficient in the case of small samples to find out the shape and spread of the distribution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Probability plots",
            "c) Designed experiments",
            "d) PDCA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The advantage of probability plotting is that, it is unnecessary to divide the range of the variable into class intervals, and it often produces reasonable results for moderately small samples (which histogram will not)."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Histogram generally is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphical representation of intervals of data plotted against frequency",
            "b) Ranked data versus the sample cumulative frequency",
            "c) Ranked data versus the frequency",
            "d) Diagram of unit giving the location of defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A histogram is generally described as a graphical representation of range of data divided into intervals plotted against the frequency of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Probability plots are graph of ranked data plotted against the cumulative frequency, with a vertical scale chosen so that the cumulative distribution of assumed type is a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parabola",
            "b) Straight line",
            "c) Hyperbola",
            "d) Pulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Probability plots are the graphs of the ranked data versus the sample cumulative frequency on special paper. These plots have the vertical scale so chosen, that the cumulative distribution of the assumed type is a straight line."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of these is a disadvantage of probability plot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are not an objective procedure",
            "b) They don’t tell about the defect",
            "c) They are hard to interpret",
            "d) They can’t tell about mean of the data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Probability plots are quite useful but, they have a major disadvantage that they are not an objective procedure. There can be many conclusions for same set of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Process capability ratio is expressed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_p=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_p=\\frac{USL-2LSL}{6σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_p=\\frac{2USL-LSL}{6σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_p=\\frac{USL+LSL}{6σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Process capability ratio (PCR) is denoted as Cp  and expressed as,\n\\(C_p=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6σ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "USL in the formula of PCR is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upper safe limit",
            "b) Ultimate safe limit",
            "c) Upper specification limit",
            "d) Ultimate specification limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: USL in the formula of PCR or process capability ratio is the Upper Specification Limit. This denotes the maximum tolerable value for a quality characteristic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "The LSL in the Cp is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower safe limit",
            "b) Largest safe limit",
            "c) Largest specification limit",
            "d) Lower specification limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LSL, in the formula of the Process Capability Ratio, Cp is the Lower Specification Limit value of the quality characteristic. It specifies the lowest possible value for the quality characteristic for the process to be in statistical control."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "When the process standard deviation σ is unknown for a process, to calculate the PCR we use _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mean",
            "b) The variance",
            "c) The sample average",
            "d) The estimate of σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is common that the process standard deviation is not known for the process. In this case, to calculate the PCR, we use the estimate of the process standard deviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "We use _____________ to calculate the estimate of the process standard deviation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample standard deviation",
            "b) Sample average",
            "c) Sample variance",
            "d) Sample mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the process standard deviation is not known, we use the estimate of the process standard deviation. This estimate is calculated by using the sample standard deviation, s."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "How is s (Sample standard deviation) calculated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) s = R/2",
            "b) s = R/2d2",
            "c) s = R/d2",
            "d) s = 2R/d2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sample standard deviation, s, used for the estimation of the process standard deviation, is calculated by the formula:\ns = R/d2."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The estimate of the Cp is calculated by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\hat{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{3\\hat{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{\\hat{\\sigma}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{12\\hat{\\sigma}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The estimate of the process capability ratio Cp  is calculated by,\n\\(\\widehat{C_P} = \\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\hat{\\sigma}}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "If the estimate of the process standard deviation is 0.1368, and the USL for the quality characteristic is 2.00, and the LSL=2.00, what will be the value of the estimate of PCR Cp is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.21",
            "b) 1.19",
            "c) 1.13",
            "d) 1.31"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(\\widehat{C_P} = \\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\hat{\\sigma}}\\) \nSo, when we put values, we get, \\(\\widehat{C_P}\\)=1.192.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The percentage of the specification band used by the process is calculated by formula _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P=Cp",
            "b) P=\\(\\frac{1}{C_p}\\)*100",
            "c) P=Cp*100",
            "d) P=\\(\\frac{1}{C_p}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The percentages of the specification band used by any process is calculated by the following formula,\nP=\\(\\frac{1}{C_p}\\)*100"
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "If the process capability ratio Cp is 1.532, what percentages of the specification band will be used by the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65.27%",
            "b) 75.11%",
            "c) 44.21%",
            "d) 21.42%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The percentages of specification band used by the process is calculated by,\nP=\\(\\frac{1}{C_p}\\)*100\nWhen we put values, we get,  P=65.27%."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "The one sided process capability ratio that uses the USL of the quality characteristic, is written as ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL+μ}{3σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL+μ}{6σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL-μ}{6σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL-μ}{3σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The one sided process capability ratio that uses the USL of the quality characteristic is written as,\n\\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL-μ}{3σ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "For a process, the process standard deviation is 32. If the mean of the process is 364, and the upper specification limit is 400, what will be the one side process capability ratio which uses USL of the quality characteristic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.242",
            "b) 1.135",
            "c) 1.125",
            "d) 0.991"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(C_{pu}=\\frac{USL-μ}{3σ}\\) \nPutting values, we get, Cpu=1.125."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "What is the formula to calculate the one sided process capability which uses lower specification limit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_{pl}=\\frac{μ+LSL}{σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_{pl}=\\frac{μ-LSL}{6σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_{pl}=\\frac{μ-LSL}{3σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_{pl}=\\frac{μ-LSL}{6σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formula to calculate the one sided process capability which uses lower specification limit of the quality characteristic,\n\\(C_{pl}=\\frac{μ-LSL}{3σ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "If the Lower specification limit for one quality characteristic of one product, is 200, and the mean of the process is estimated to be 264 with an estimate of one sided process capability ratio \\(\\widehat{C_{pl}}\\), what will be the estimate of the process standard deviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43",
            "b) 59",
            "c) 32",
            "d) 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that,\nWe know that,\n\\(\\widehat{C_{pl}} = \\frac{\\hat{μ}-LSL}{3\\hat{σ}}\\) \nPutting values, we get, The process standard deviation estimate, \\(\\hat{σ}\\)=32.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "If the LSL of the quality characteristic increases, the process capability ratio Cp will ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Will remain same",
            "d) Can’t say (can increase as well as decrease)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(C_p=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6σ}\\) \nSo an increase in the LSL value will decrease the PCR."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "PCR is a measure of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ability of the process to manufacture the products that meet the specifications",
            "b) The ability of the operator to remove the variability",
            "c) The probability of the mean to be equal to the USL",
            "d) The probability of the mean to be equal to the LSL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Process capability ratio is used as the measure of the ability of the process to manufacture the products, which meet the specifications set for it."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "The process fallout (in ppm) ___________ with increase in the process capability ratio Cp, for a normally distributed process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Can’t be described an increase or decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process fallout in ppm decreases with increase in the Process Capability Ratio Cp. This relation can only be applied to the normally distributed processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "A PCR Cp=1.00 indicates the fallout rate of ___________ ppm for two-sided specifications.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 967",
            "d) 2700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A process capability ratio is a measure of the ability of a process to produce products, which meet their specifications. A PCR Cp=1.00 indicates a fallout rate of 2700 ppm for two-sided specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "A process capability ratio Cp=____________ indicates the fallout rate of 1 ppm for one-sided specifications for a normally distributed process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2",
            "b) 1.8",
            "c) 1.9",
            "d) 1.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A process capability ratio Cp=1.6 indicates the fallout rate of 1 ppm for the one – sided specifications. It also indicates the fallout rate of 2 ppm for two-sided specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "A correct interpretation of the PCR Cp does not need the consideration of ___________ of process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operator",
            "b) Mean",
            "c) Variance",
            "d) Stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct interpretation of the Cp does not need the consideration of the operator of the process, as this factor is already included in the earlier steps taken before this interpretation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "What is generally the minimum value of two sided specification PCR Cp for a existing process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.11",
            "b) 1.33",
            "c) 1.89",
            "d) 1.60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum value of the two sided specifications PCR Cp for an existing process is generally taken as 1.33. For one sided specifications, PCR Cp  is taken as 1.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is the minimum value of Process Capability Ratio Cp  for one sided specifications, for a new process which is normally distributed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.45",
            "b) 1.19",
            "c) 1.72",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum value of the Process Capability Ratio Cp for one sided specifications, is taken as 1.45 for any new process which is assumed to be normally distributed."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "If the quality characteristic in consideration is a strength parameter of the existing process, what will be the minimum value of Cp for two sided specifications for this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.22",
            "b) 1.52",
            "c) 1.50",
            "d) 1.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the quality characteristic in consideration is a strength parameter of the existing process, the minimum value of Process Capability Ratio Cp for two sided specifications 1.50. "
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of these is a necessary assumption made for the calculation of the PCR Cp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The quality characteristic has a normal distribution",
            "b) The quality characteristic has a lognormal distribution",
            "c) The quality characteristic has an exponential distribution",
            "d) The quality characteristic has a Poisson distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the calculation of the Process capability ratio, it is assumed that the quality characteristic, for which the PCR is to be calculated, should have a normal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "What is the minimum two – sided specification PCR for the safety parameter for a new process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.48",
            "b) 1.45",
            "c) 1.67",
            "d) 1.32"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a new process, a two – sided specification Process Capability Ratio for the safety parameter should have a minimum value of 1.67."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "What is the value of process fallout in defectives ppm for one sided specifications of a PCR Cp= 1.10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 484",
            "b) 201",
            "c) 2700",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of process fallout in defectives ppm for the one – sided specifications of a PCR Cp=1.10  is 484. This value for two sided specifications of the same PCR Cp  is 967."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "What should be the minimum value of PCR Cp for a six-sigma company?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.0",
            "b) 1.0",
            "c) 3.0",
            "d) 1.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  A six-sigma company would require the process mean, when in control, will not be closer to than the six-sigma deviations from the nearest specification limit. For this, Cp≥2.0"
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "What should be the position of the process mean for the calculation of the PCR Cp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near to the USL",
            "b) Near to LSL",
            "c) Centered between LSL and USL",
            "d) Cp Does not take this into account"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The process capability ratio PCR Cp does not take into account where the process mean is located relative to the specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What is the function of Cp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To measure the value of process mean",
            "b) To measure the value of the process standard deviation",
            "c) To measure the USL and LSL of the quality characteristic",
            "d) To measure the spread of the specifications relative to the six sigma spread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The process capability ratio Cp does not take into account the process centering. It simply measures the spread of the specifications relative to the six sigma spread of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Which one of the processes performs the best?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The one which operates near the USL",
            "b) The one which operates near the LSL",
            "c) The one which operates at the midpoint of the interval between the specifications",
            "d) The one which operates outside the specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process which operates at the midpoint of the interval between the specifications, has the best performance among all the processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "4 processes have same value of Cp and the USL and LSL values equal to 62 and 38 respectively. Which one of those performs the best?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centered at 50",
            "b) Centered at 44",
            "c) Centered at 54",
            "d) Centered at 63"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process, which is centered at the midpoint of the interval between the specifications limits, has the maximum probability of performing the best.\nmidpoint=\\(\\frac{USL+LSL}{2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "If Cp=Cpk which of these is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process is centered at the LSL of the specifications",
            "b) Process is centered at the USL of the specifications",
            "c) Process is centered at the midpoint of the specification",
            "d) Process is centered at the outside the specification limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally, when Cp=Cpk, the process is centered at the midpoint of the specifications. This means the process performance is a lot better."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which of these gives the best performance of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp = Cpk",
            "b) Cp – Cpk = Cpk",
            "c) Cp > Cpk",
            "d) Cp < Cpk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the process capability ratio Cp is equal to the process capability ratio Cpk, it is generally stating that the process is centered at the midpoint of the specifications. This gives the best performance of the process at a particular value of Cp."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of these is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cpk=min⁡(Cpu, Cp)",
            "b) Cpk=min⁡(Cpu, Cpl)",
            "c) Cpk=max⁡(Cpu, Cp)",
            "d) Cpk=max⁡(Cp, Cpl)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process capability ratio Cpk  is the minimum of the two, Cpu and Cpl. So,\nCpk=min⁡(Cpu, Cpl)"
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of these is a correct definition for the Cpk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cpk is the one sided PCR for the specification limit nearest to the standard deviation of the process",
            "b) Cpk is the one sided PCR for the specification limit farest to the standard deviation of the process",
            "c) Cpk is the one sided PCR for the specification limit farest to the average of the process",
            "d) Cpk is the one sided PCR for the specification limit nearest to the average of the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cpk is the one sided PCR for the specification limit nearest to the standard deviation of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "If Cp>Cpk what conclusion can be carried out about the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The process has its operation at the midpoint of the interval between the specifications",
            "b) The process operates off-center",
            "c) The process performance is the best possible for that Cp",
            "d) The process can’t perform any better for same Cp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, if Cp > Cpk, we can say that the process is not centered at the midpoint of the specifications, i.e. the process operates off-center."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "For a process, the upper specification limit and lower specification limits are 62 and 38 respectively. If the process has its mean equal to 53, and its standard deviation 2, what is the value of Cpk for this process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 1.0",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that,\nCpk=min⁡(Cpu, Cpl)\nCalculating the values of Cpu  and Cpl, we get Cpu=1.5 and Cpl=2.5. So we get Cpk=1.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "If  Cp=2.0,Cpu=1.5,Cpl=2.5 what will be the value of Cpk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 2.0",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process capability ratio Cpk is expressed by the following equation,\nCpk=min⁡(Cpu, Cpl)\nHere Cpu=1.5(minimum), so Cpk=1.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "If Cpk=1.0 and Cp=2.0, what will be the actual fallout for the process in ppm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200",
            "b) 2700",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 1350"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If Cpk < Cp, Cpk is considered to evaluate the process fallout as the process is off center and the one sided process capability must be used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "To remove the errors in the estimation of the PCR, the _________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance Sampling",
            "b) Sample mean",
            "c) Sample variance",
            "d) Confidence intervals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In actual practice, we only observe the estimate of PCR, not the real PCR. As the estimate can have a large error probability, it is always a good idea to use confidence intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which of these measures the actual capability of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp",
            "b) Cpu",
            "c) Cpk",
            "d) Cpl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cpk always shows the actual capability as by interpretation of it, we can sense the potential improvement possible in the process by centering it.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of these measures the potential capability of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp",
            "b) Cpu",
            "c) Cpk",
            "d) Cpl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Actual process capability can only be measured using the process capability ratio Cp as it does not take process centering into account. It ignores the potential improvement possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "If a process actual fallout is 1350 ppm, and its Cp=2.0, what will be its fallout after centering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 ppm",
            "b) 4 ppm",
            "c) 0.009 ppm",
            "d) 0.0018 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Process fallout is 1350, so its Cpk=1.0. So after potential improvement, when its Cpk = Cp, we get the process fallout = 0.0018 ppm."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to analyze the process capability of the process which has the quality characteristic distributed non-normally?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp",
            "b) Cpk",
            "c) Cpl",
            "d) Cpc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There have been many attempts to extend the definition of the standard capability indices to the case of non-normal distribution. One of them is Cpc."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "How is Cpc  expressed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_{pc}=\\frac{USL+LSL}{6\\sqrt{\\frac{π}{2} E|X-T|}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_{pc}=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6 \\sqrt{\\frac{π}{2} E|X-T|}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_{pc}=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6 \\sqrt{\\frac{π}{2} E|X+T|}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_{pc}=\\frac{USL-LSL}{\\sqrt{\\frac{π}{2} E|X-T|}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cpc is expressed as,\n\\(C_{pc}=\\frac{USL-LSL}{6 \\sqrt{\\frac{π}{2} E|X-T|}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "What is the value of T in the expression of Cpc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(USL+LSL)",
            "b) T=(USL+LSL)",
            "c) T=\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)(USL+LSL)",
            "d) T=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(USL-LSL)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of T in the expression of Cpc is as follows.\nT=\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(USL+LSL)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "What does the second subscript in Cpc?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Course",
            "b) Capability",
            "c) Confidence",
            "d) Clarity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the process capability index Cpc, designed by Lucin ̃o, which takes process non-normality into account, the second subscript denotes confidence as in Confidence intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which of these is not desirable to be worked alone with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp",
            "b) Cpc ",
            "c) Cpk",
            "d) Cpu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two processes having different centering can have a same Cpk. So we need to evaluate Cp to check the equality of PCR Cpk with it. This way we get perfect centering between the specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "For any fixed value between LSL and USL, Cpk depends _________ on σ.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inversely",
            "b) Directly",
            "c) Negatively",
            "d) Positively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know,\nCpc=min⁡(Cpu,Cpl)\nWhere, Cpu  and Cpl, both vary inversely according to σ. So Cpc is inversely dependent on σ."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "What will be the value of Cpc as σ approaches to zero?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) One",
            "c) Infinity",
            "d) Minus Infinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As Process Capability Ratio Cpc varies inversely with σ, when the value of σ approaches zero, the value of the PCR Cpc becomes infinity."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which of these besides the PCR Cpc can be used to know more about the process centering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cp",
            "b) Cpm",
            "c) Cpu",
            "d) Cpl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As Cpc also needs some complementary process capability ratio such as Cp, to know more about process centering, another PCR Cpm is developed to know more about process centering."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "What is the value of Cpm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_{pm}=\\frac{USL+LSl}{6σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_{pm}=\\frac{USL-LSl}{6σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_{pm}=\\frac{USL+LSl}{6τ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_{pm}=\\frac{USL-LSl}{6τ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of Cpm Process capability ratio is given as,\n\\(C_{pm}=\\frac{USL-LSl}{6τ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Kotz and Lovelace were in strong opposition of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pp",
            "b) Cp",
            "c) Cpk",
            "d) Cpm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cpk and Cp are based on an assumption that the quality characteristic varies on a normal distribution. So we cannot use the process capability ratio Cpk to determine the process capability of the non-normal data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What is the value of τ in the expression of Cpm process capability ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(τ=\\sqrt{[E\\big\\{x-T)^2]}\\) ",
            "b) \\(τ=\\sqrt{E[{x+T}^2]}\\) ",
            "c) \\(τ=\\sqrt{E[(x-T)^2]}\\) ",
            "d) \\(τ=\\sqrt{E[(x+T)^2]}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of τ in the expression of Cpm is the square root of expected squared deviation from target T, i.e.\n\\(τ=\\sqrt{[E\\big\\{x-T)^2]}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Which of these is equal to the squared value of τ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ2-(μ+T)2",
            "b) σ2+(μ-T)2",
            "c) σ2-(μ-T)2",
            "d) σ2+(μ+T)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of squared value of τ,\nτ2=E[(x-T)2]=E[(x-μ)2 ]+(μ-T)2=σ2+(μ-T)2."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Which of these is having same value as Cpm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2-(μ-T)^2}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{USL+LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2-(μ-T)^2}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2+(μ-T)^2}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{USL+LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2+(μ-T)^2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As we know,\nτ2=σ2+(μ-T)2\nWe may write,\n Cpm = \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2+(μ-T)^2}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "What is value of ξ in the expression for Cpm Process Capability Ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{μ+T}{3σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{μ-T}{6σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{μ+T}{σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{μ-T}{σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of ξ in the expression of Cpm is given by,\nξ = \\(\\frac{μ-T}{σ}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "If standard values are not given, the value of Cpm is estimated by expression _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\widehat{C_{pm}}=\\frac{C_p}{\\sqrt{1+V^2}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\widehat{C_{pm}}=\\frac{C_p}{\\sqrt{1-V}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\widehat{C_{pm}}=\\frac{C_p}{\\sqrt{1+V}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\widehat{C_{pm}}=\\frac{C_p}{\\sqrt{1-V^2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The estimate of Cpm, when the standard values of σ, μ are not given, is calculated by expression,\n\\(\\widehat{C_{pm}}=\\frac{C_p}{\\sqrt{1+V^2}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "What is the value of V in the expression of the estimate of Cpm Process Capability Ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{\\bar{x}-T}{s}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{\\bar{x}+T}{s}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{\\bar{x}-T}{s^2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{\\bar{x}-T}{σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of V is used at the place of ξ in the case when the standard values of σ and μ are not available. The value of V is equal to,\nV = \\(\\frac{\\bar{x}-T}{s}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "What is the value of Cpm when the value |μ-T|→∞ ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) ∞",
            "d) -∞"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of Cpm approaches to zero asymptotically as the value |μ-T|→∞. This is because,\n Cpm = \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2+(μ-T)^2}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "What is the value of Cpm  when the value μ=T?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cpm=1",
            "b) Cpm=0",
            "c) Cpm=Cp",
            "d) Cpm<Cp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As we know,\n Cpm = \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6\\sqrt{σ^2+(μ-T)^2}}\\) \nWhen, μ=T we get Cpm=Cp. "
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "What is the value of Cpkm  process capability ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_{pkm}=\\frac{C_{pk}}{\\sqrt{1-ξ}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_{pkm}=\\frac{C_{pk}}{\\sqrt{1+ξ^2}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_{pkm}=\\frac{C_{pk}}{\\sqrt{1+ξ}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_{pkm}=\\frac{C_{pk}}{\\sqrt{1-ξ^2}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of PCR Cpkm is given by\n\\(C_{pkm}=\\frac{C_{pk}}{\\sqrt{1+ξ^2}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is the value of ξ in the expression for Cpkm  PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{μ-T}{6σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{μ-T}{σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{μ+2T}{3σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{μ+T}{6σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of ξ in the expression of Cpkm is given by,\nξ = \\(\\frac{μ-T}{σ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Cpkm is also called _________ generation process capability ratio.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Third",
            "b) Fourth",
            "c) Second",
            "d) First"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cpkm is sometimes called third generation process capability ratio since it is constructed from the second generation PCR Cpm and Cpk."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Cp is called the _________ generation PCR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) First",
            "b) Second",
            "c) Third",
            "d) Fourth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cp is called the first generation process capability ratio as it was designed before any other process capability ratio like Cpk  or Cpm."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which of these is one of the first generation process capability ratios?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cpk",
            "b) Cpm",
            "c) Cpc ",
            "d) Cpu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As we know, the first Process capability ratios, that were designed, were Cp, Cpu, Cpl. So they are called the first generation process capability ratios."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "What does usage of s instead of R/d2 in the confidence intervals indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) s=1",
            "b) Process must be in control",
            "c) Process may be in the out-of-control state",
            "d) d2<1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cpk and Cpm were designed after the first generation capability ratios, which were not able to consider the process centering fact into their evaluation. So they are called the second gen. process capability ratios."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Pp is a ___",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process capability ratio",
            "b) Process stability ratio",
            "c) Process prediction index",
            "d) Process performance index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the estimates of the process capability ratios are point estimates. This means there is a strong possibility of error due to statistical fluctuation. So confidence interval is needed also for \\(\\widehat{C_{pkm}}\\).  "
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "What is the value of process performance index estimate (Pp)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{4s}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{USL+LSL}{4s}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{USL-LSL}{6s}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When process is not in control, the value of s has a big difference with the value of R/d2. So for the calculation of confidence interval s is used. This means, for a PCR to have a meaning, the process must be in control."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which one of these tells explicitly about the potential capability of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Probability plots",
            "c) PCRs",
            "d) Control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Histogram, process capability ratios and the probability plots all can only summarize the performance of process. They don’t necessarily display the process potential capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which one of these addresses the issue of statistical control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of process experiments",
            "b) Probability plots",
            "c) Control charts",
            "d) Histogram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The probability plots, histogram and PCRs are just tools to summarize the process performance. They don’t address the issue of statistical control. Control charts only, are capable of doing that."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which one these show that, if the systematic pattern in process output is eliminated, it would produce a lesser variability in the quality characteristic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probability plots",
            "b) Control Charts",
            "c) Histogram",
            "d) PCRs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As control charts address the issue of statistical control of the process, they ensure that there must be random patterns in the process output, so that variability is reduced. "
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which one of these is primary technique of the process capability analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histogram",
            "b) Process capability ratios",
            "c) Probability plots",
            "d) Control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As control charts are main technique to reduce variability, by taking the statistical control into consideration, control charts are regarded as the primary technique of the process capability analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which chart should be used, if possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x & R Charts",
            "b) u Charts",
            "c) p Charts",
            "d) c Charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As x & R charts are the variable control charts and the others are attribute control charts, taking the fact “variable charts give better information than the others” into consideration, x & R charts are favored over the others."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which one of these charts doesn’t need the specification of the quality characteristic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x  & R Charts",
            "b) p-charts",
            "c) c-charts",
            "d) u-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The variable control charts don’t need the specification of the quality characteristic, so x & R charts don’t need the specifications of the quality characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which one of these helps us to find both instantaneous and the variability across time variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) np-charts",
            "c) x & R Charts",
            "d) c-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The charts for x & R are quite useful in determination of the instantaneous and the variable across time variability of a quality characteristic."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "What is the second name of instantaneous variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long term variability",
            "b) Short term variability",
            "c) Long distance variability",
            "d) Variability across time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Instantaneous variability is the variability for a small tenure of process operation. It is also known as the short term variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which one of these is similar to the long-term variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instantaneous variability",
            "b) Variability across time",
            "c) Large variability",
            "d) Large distance variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The variability across time phrase is also known as the long term variability, as this phrase is used for the variability calculated for a big interval of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which control charts will be useful if the process output data for the process capability study are collected in different time periods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x & R Charts",
            "b) p-charts",
            "c) c-charts",
            "d) u-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As variable control charts are capable of determining the process capability of both types, i.e. the instantaneous variability, and the variability across time, they are used, when the data for process capability analysis is collected in different shifts."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "If the Cpl of a safety-related parameter, is 0.69, what can we say about the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process is capable",
            "b) Process is not capable",
            "c) Process is capable but will become not-capable in sooner time",
            "d) Process is not-capable but will become capable in sooner time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For a safety-related parameter, we know that the one-sided process capability ratio must be greater than, 1.50 for an existing process, or 1.67 for a new process. So the above mentioned process capability is inadequate."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which one of these can be used as the monitoring device to show the effect of changes in the process on process performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) Designed experiments",
            "c) Histogram",
            "d) Probability plots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Control charts give the time to time data about the process output in a visual display. So we can use them as a monitoring device to show the effect of changes in the process, on process performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "If Cpu=1.82 for strength quality characteristic for a new process, can we use the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process is capable",
            "b) Process is not capable",
            "c) Process is capable but will improve in sooner time",
            "d) Process is not capable but will improve in sooner time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As strength is a safety parameter, the minimum value for Cpu for it for a new process is 1.67. So we can use the above mentioned new process."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "In the design of experiments, the ____________ variables are adjusted first.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Output controllable",
            "b) Output uncontrollable",
            "c) Input uncontrollable",
            "d) Input controllable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the design of experiments, the value of input controllable variables is varied to find the desired output quality of a process."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which of these can be varied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input Controllable variables",
            "b) Input uncontrollable variables",
            "c) Output controllable variables",
            "d) Output uncontrollable variables"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only the input controllable variables can be varied. This is because all the other variables are uncontrollable like input uncontrollable variables etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not done in the designing of experiments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Varying the input variables (controllable)",
            "b) Observation of the output",
            "c) Making a relationship between input and output",
            "d) Process control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the design of experiments, the controllable inputs of a process are varied, and the output of the process is observed simultaneously, then a relationship between the inputs and the outputs, is made."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a function of designing of experiments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To find the set of process variables influential on output",
            "b) To determine the optimum level of the variables",
            "c) To estimate maximum output possible with optimum value of variables",
            "d) To eliminate some uncontrollable inputs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Designed experiments are helpful in finding, which set of process variables is influential on the output, and at what levels these variables should be held to optimize the process performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of these is the easiest method for finding the sources of variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Designed Experiments",
            "b) p-charts",
            "c) n-charts",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Designed experiments are useful in determining the optimum level of the process variables for a better process performance, so we can find the sources of variability simultaneously."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a method to judge the process capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) Attributes data",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Designed experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Process capability can be determined by the usage of either of control charts, or attributes data or designed experiments. The process capability ratios, histogram and the probability plots also can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "DPU is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrement per unit",
            "b) Defects per unit",
            "c) Design per unit",
            "d) Decimals per unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term “DPU” is used in the determination of process capability by using the attribute data. Here, DPU stands for Defects per unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "DPMO stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defects per million opportunities",
            "b) Decrement per minute opportunity",
            "c) Defects per minute opportunity",
            "d) Designation per million opportunities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DPMO represents the defects per million opportunities. It takes the complexity of an unit into account when calculating the process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of these is the correct formula to calculate DPMO which uses the number of opportunities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number\\, of \\,units \\,* 0.5 *\\, Number\\, of \\,Opportunities}\\) ",
            "b) DPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number \\,of \\,units \\,* \\,3Number\\, of \\,Opportunities}\\) ",
            "c) DPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number \\,of \\,units \\,* \\,2Number \\,of \\,Opportunities}\\) ",
            "d) DPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number \\,of \\,units \\,* \\,Number \\,of \\,Opportunities}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DPMO is calculated by using the following formula,\nDPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number \\,of \\,units \\,* \\,Number \\,of \\,Opportunities}\\) \nAs this formula contains the number of opportunities, it takes the number of times that an error can be occurred. So it is much accurate."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "If there are 85 defects in the lot containing 150 units, what is the value of DPU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.45",
            "b) 0.57",
            "c) 0.89",
            "d) 1.52"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DPU is calculated by using the following formula,\nDPU =  \\(\\frac{Total \\,number \\,of \\,defects}{Total \\,number \\,of \\,units}\\) \nBy calculating the DPU, we get, DPU=0.57."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "If the DPMO for a sample containing 45 units is 0.237. If the total number of defects is 32, what will be the number of opportunities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DPMO is calculated using the formula,\nDPMO=\\(\\frac{Total\\, number \\,of \\,units}{Number \\,of \\,units \\,* \\,Number \\,of \\,Opportunities}\\) \nPutting the values, we get, the number of opportunities= 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an objective of most measurement systems capability studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determining how much of variability is due to the gauge or instrument",
            "b) Isolating the components of variability in measurement system",
            "c) Assessing whether the instrument is capable",
            "d) Checking whether the instrument can make defective pieces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Most measurement system capability studies are having objectives like determination of the amount of variability due to the gauge or instrument, to isolate the components of variability in the measurement system etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Which of these is one of the two R’s of measurement systems capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reducibility",
            "b) Recyclability",
            "c) Reproducibility",
            "d) Reusability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two R’s of the measurement systems capability are “Reproducibility” and “Repeatability”. They play very important role in the measurement system capability studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "What is repeatability of a measurement instrument?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Getting the maximum value of the measured dimension",
            "b) Getting the minimum value of the measured dimension",
            "c) Getting the exact value of the measured dimension",
            "d) Same observation value for same measured dimension for several times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Repeatability of a measurement instrument is defined as getting the same observed value if we measure the same unit several times under identical conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "What is reproducibility of a measurement system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference between the observed values when the measuring conditions are same",
            "b) Difference between the observed values when the measuring conditions are different",
            "c) Ease in measurement when the measuring conditions are same",
            "d) Ease in measurement when the measuring conditions are different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reproducibility is how much difference we get in observed values, when the units are measured under different conditions like different operators, time periods etc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Measurement system capability ____________ when the good unit is judged to be defective.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Does not change",
            "d) Can’t be evaluated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capability of a measurement system decreases substantially when the good unit in the output of a process is judged to be defective. This is a fault of the measurement system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Measurement system capability increases if the bad unit is judged to be _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conforming",
            "b) Nonconforming",
            "c) Not defective",
            "d) Satisfying the specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a measurement system identifies a bad unit by classifying it as nonconforming, the measurement system capability is increased."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "If a good unit is judged to be conforming, what will be the effect on the measurement system capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remain same",
            "d) Can’t be calculated in this case"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a good unit is judged to be conforming to the standards and specifications, it indicates the efficiency of the system. So the capability of the measurement system is increased in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "What is the linearity of a measurement system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Differences in observed accuracies and/or precision over a range of measurements made",
            "b) Differences in theoretical accuracies and/or precision over a range of measurements made",
            "c) Differences in products dimensions of products from a same process",
            "d) Differences in the product quality from a same process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Linearity of a measurement system is defined as the differences in observed accuracy and/or precision, experienced over the range of the measurements made by the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "When the measurement system is not linear ____________ is needed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process to be changed by which the units are made",
            "b) Calibration of the measurement system",
            "c) Change in the process parameters",
            "d) No change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If there are problems with linearity of the measurement system, they can be due to calibration or maintenance issues, so proper calibration or the replacement of the measurement system can solve the problems."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a cause of the stability defects in the measurement systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Warm up effects",
            "b) Environmental factors",
            "c) Inconsistent operator performance",
            "d) Maintenance errors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stability or different levels of variability in different operating regimes, can result from warm-up effects, environmental factors, inconsistent operator performance, and inadequate standard operating procedures."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Bias of a measurement instrument is defined as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The difference between the observed value and the true value",
            "b) The difference between the observed value and the lowest possible value",
            "c) The difference between the observed value and the estimated value",
            "d) The difference between the observed value and the highest possible value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bias of a measurement system reflects the difference between the observed value and the true value obtained from a master or gold standard, or from a different measurement technique reliable to produce accurate values."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "It becomes very difficult to monitor, control, improve, or effectively manage a process with  _____________ measurement system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A passable",
            "b) A satisfactory",
            "c) An adequate",
            "d) An inadequate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the measurement system is not capable to produce good results, it becomes very difficult to monitor, control, improve, or effectively manage a process with an inadequate measurement system."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "MSA stands for ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Million standards analysis",
            "b) Major system analysis",
            "c) Measurement system analysis",
            "d) Master system analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MSA is an acronym used for Measurement System Analysis, which is done in the measurement system capability analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "What of these can be used as a reasonable model for measurement system capability studies? Here y,x and ε denote the observed measurement, true measurement, and the measurement error respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) y=x-2ε",
            "b) y=x+ε",
            "c) y=x-ε",
            "d) y=x+2ε"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reasonable model, which can be used for measurement system capability is expressed as,\ny=x+ε"
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "The variance of the total observed measurement is expressed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P^2-\\sigma_{Gauge}^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P+\\sigma_{Gauge}^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P^2+\\sigma_{Gauge}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P^2+\\sigma_{Gauge}^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The variance of the total observed measurement uses the value of the sum of the variances of product errors, and the gauge errors. It is calculated by,\n\\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P^2+\\sigma_{Gauge}^2\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "The P/T ratio stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probability to tolerance ratio",
            "b) Precision to time ratio",
            "c) Probability to total ratio",
            "d) Precision to tolerance ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The P/T ratio is used in the measurement system capability analysis. In P/T ratio, P/T refers to Precision to tolerance ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "What is the value of the P/T ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{1.5k\\hat{σ_p}}{USL-LSL}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{k\\hat{σ}_{gauge}}{USL-LSL}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{2k\\hat{σ_p}}{USL+LSL}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{k\\hat{σ}_{gauge}}{USL+LSL}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The P/T ratio is calculated for the evaluation of the gauge capability. It uses the value of the \\(\\hat{σ_{gauge}}\\) The value of P/T ratio is given by,\n\\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{k\\hat{σ}_{gauge}}{USL-LSL}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "If the number of standard deviations between the usual natural tolerance limits of a normal distribution, what is the value used for k in the P/T ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.15",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 5.60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value k=6 in the P/T ratio corresponds to the number of standard deviations, between the usual natural tolerance limits for a normal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "For a process, which has, USL and LSL equal to 60, and 5 respectively, and the value of \\(\\hat{σ}_{gauge}\\) = 0.887, what will be the value of P/T ratio when k=6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.087",
            "b) 0.077",
            "c) 0.067",
            "d) 0.097"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(\\frac{P}{T}=\\frac{k\\hat{σ}_{gauge}}{USL-LSL}\\) \nPutting the values in the question, we get P/T=0.097."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Which of these indicate an adequate measurement system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{P}{T}≤0.1\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{P}{T}≤0.5\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{P}{T}≥0.1\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{P}{T}=0.3\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the value of P/T ratio is lesser than or equal to 0.1, the measurement system used is predicted to be adequate for the selected process."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "The options are the P/T ratios for different measurement systems. Which of these shows an adequate measurement system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.21",
            "b) 0.13",
            "c) 0.18",
            "d) 0.06"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A P/T ratio lesser than 0.1 indicates an appropriate measurement system for any process. So here, 0.06<0.1, so it is an example of acceptable measurement systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "The cause of calling a measurement system adequate because it has P/T ratio lesser than 0.1, is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A measurement device should be calibrated in units one-tenth large as the accuracy required in final measurement",
            "b) A measurement device should be calibrated in units one-third large as the accuracy required in final measurement",
            "c) A measurement device should be calibrated in units one-fourth large as the accuracy required in final measurement",
            "d) A measurement device should be calibrated in units three-tenth large as the accuracy required in final measurement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Values of estimated P/T ratio of 0.1 or less indicate adequate measurement system. It’s based upon the general rule, which requires the measurement device to be calibrated in units one-tenth large, as the accuracy required in the final measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used as the estimate of standard deviation of total variability which is including both product variability, and the gauge variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sample mean",
            "b) The sample variance",
            "c) The sample standard deviation",
            "d) No of defects in the sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sample variance can be used as the estimate of the standard deviation of the total variability, which includes both, the product variability, and the gauge variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "If the sample variance of a process is, 10.05, and the gauge capability standard deviation is estimated to be 0.79. What will be the value of the estimate of the standard deviation of the product variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.26",
            "b) 3.04",
            "c) 2.03",
            "d) 8.91"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As we know that,\n\\(\\sigma_{Total}^2=\\sigma_P^2+\\sigma_{Gauge}^2\\) \nIf the estimates are to be used, the same equation can be written for the corresponding estimate values. Putting the values as mentioned, we get, \\(\\hat{\\sigma}_p^2\\)=3.04.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Which of these show a correct expression for the ρp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_p^2}{2σ_{Gauge}^2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{σ_{Total}^2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_P^2}{σ_{Gauge}^2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{2σ_{total}^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gauge capability ratio ρp is the ratio of the variances of the product error and the gauge errors. It is expressed as,\n\\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_P^2}{σ_{Gauge}^2}\\)\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "The gauge capability ratio ρM is expressed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_p^2}{2σ_{Gauge}^2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{σ_{Total}^2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_P^2}{σ_{Gauge}^2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{2σ_{total}^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of gauge capability ratio ρM is a ratio of the variances of the gauge errors and the total observed errors. It is expressed as,\n\\(ρ_p=\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{σ_{Total}^2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "SNR represents __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sign to noise ratio",
            "b) Sample to nonconforming ratio",
            "c) Size to noise ratio",
            "d) Signal to noise ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A measure of measurement system adequacy is defined by AIAG, which is called SNR or signal to noise ratio. It is used to check the satisfactoriness of the measurement system."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "SNR is equal to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{2ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{3ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{2ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SNR is the measure of measurement system adequacy. It uses the gauge capability ratio ρp. It is expressed as,\nSNR=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{2ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "What is the correct definition of SNR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The number of signals for 30 noise indications on control chart",
            "b) The number of signals for single noise indication on control chart",
            "c) The number of signals with no noise from the measurements",
            "d) The number of distinct levels or categories that can be reliably obtained from the measurements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SNR is defined by AIAG as the number of distinct levels or categories that can be reliably obtained from the measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "If the estimate of pp is 0.9214, what will be the estimate of SNR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.84",
            "b) 6.87",
            "c) 9.12",
            "d) 2.13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\nSNR=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{2ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}}\\) \nBy putting the value of the estimate of ρp  we get SNR estimate = 4.84."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the gauge capability ratios?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SNR",
            "b) Cp",
            "c) ρM",
            "d) ρp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SNR, ρp and ρM are some examples of the gauge capability ratios, which are used to check the adequacy of the measurement system used."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "What is the full-form of DR in the context of gauge capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease rate",
            "b) Direction ratios",
            "c) Discrimination ratios",
            "d) Dimension rates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Like the other gauge capability ratios like SNR, ρp, and ρM; DR is also a measure of gauge capability. Its full-form is known as discrimination ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "What is the value of DR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DR=\\(\\frac{1-2ρ_p}{1+ρ_p}\\) ",
            "b) DR=\\(\\frac{1+ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}\\) ",
            "c) DR=\\(\\frac{1+2ρ_p}{1-ρ_p}\\) ",
            "d) DR=\\(\\frac{1-ρ_p}{1+ρ_p}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the discrimination ratio, which is used as a measure of adequacy of a measurement system, and which uses the ratio ρp, is used to evaluate the gauge capability. It is expressed as,\nDR=\\(\\frac{1-ρ_p}{1+ρ_p}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "For a measurement system ρp=0.8914. What will be the value of DR for that?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17.416",
            "b) 0.0571",
            "c) 24.46",
            "d) 0.0652"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\nDR=\\(\\frac{1-ρ_p}{1+ρ_p}\\) \nPutting the values, we get DR=17.416."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "For a gauge to be capable, generally DR must be greater than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0.4",
            "c) 0.1",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is generally stated that the DR for a capable gauge is, generally having a value higher than 4. This means for a gauge to be capable, the DR must exceed 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of these tells about the inherent variability of the gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accuracy",
            "b) Precision",
            "c) DR ratio",
            "d) SNR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Precision of a measurement system can be a measure of the inherent variability of the gauge. This is because the inherent variability moves the output of a gauge strongly to one direction or to a point."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The standard model for a gauge R & R study is also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Random effects model analysis of variance",
            "b) Continuous effects model analysis of variance",
            "c) Discrete effects model analysis of variance",
            "d) Attribute effects model analysis of variance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average of the observed values is almost equal to the true value. So from the definition of accuracy, we can say this gauge is more accurate than precise."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The more the gauge capability, the more are the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tolerances",
            "b) Specifications",
            "c) Chances of rejection",
            "d) Chances of no error in measurements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard model for a gauge R & R study is also called a random effects model analysis of variance. It is generally used while calculating the gauge capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "What is reproducibility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variability due to different operators using the gauge or different time periods, or environments",
            "b) Variability due to error in process",
            "c) Variability reflecting the basic inherent precision of the gauge itself",
            "d) Variability reflecting the basic inherent precision of the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reproducibility is defined as the variability due to different operators using the gauge, or different time periods, or different environments, or in general, different conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "What is repeatability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variability due to different operators using the gauge or different time periods, or environments",
            "b) Variability due to error in process",
            "c) Variability reflecting the basic inherent precision of the gauge itself",
            "d) Variability reflecting the basic inherent precision of the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Repeatability is defined as reflecting the basic inherent precision of the gauge itself, through which we are measuring the unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "What can we write the variance in measurement error or gauge in the terms of variance in repeatability, and variance of reproducibility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2=\\sigma_{repeatability}^2-\\sigma_{reproducibility}^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2=\\sigma_{repeatability}^2+\\sigma_{reproducibility}^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2=\\sigma_{repeatability}+\\sigma_{reproducibility}^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2=\\sigma_{repeatability}-\\sigma_{reproducibility}^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We can write the measurement error or gauge error variance as follows,\n\\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2=\\sigma_{repeatability}^2+\\sigma_{reproducibility}^2\\). "
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of these is called an R & R study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Experiment used to measure components of \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2\\) ",
            "b) Experiment used to measure components of \\(\\sigma_{Total}^2\\) ",
            "c) Experiment used to measure components of \\(\\sigma_{P}^2\\) ",
            "d) Experiment used to measure components of \\(\\sigma_{repeatability}^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The experiment used to measure the components of \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2\\) is usually called a gauge R & R study, for two components of \\(\\sigma_{gauge}^2\\)."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "What is the other name of random effects model analysis of variance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ANOVA",
            "b) RENOVA",
            "c) FNOVA",
            "d) MENOVA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The random effects model analysis of variance is also called the ANOVA model analysis. This is a part of analysis of variance method."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "If the value of the variance of the product variability increases, what will be the effect on the variance of the gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Can’t be predicted (no dependency over each other)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As there is no dependency of the variance of the gauge on the product variability, even if the product variability increases, we cannot predict the changes in gauge variability variance."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "If the variance of the total observed measurement is constant and the gauge capability ratio ρ_M is increased, what will be change in the gauge measurement variance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Can’t be predicted (no dependency over each other)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know,\n\\(ρ_M=\\left(\\frac{\\sigma_{gauge}^2}{\\sigma_{Total}^2}\\right)\\) \nSo if the variance of the total observed measurement is kept constant with the gauge capability ratio ρM increasing, the variance of gauge measurement will be increased."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "If the variance of product variability is increased while keeping the total observed measurement variance constant, what will be effect on the gauge capability ratio ρP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Can’t be predicted (no dependency over each other)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know,\nρP∝ σp2\nSo, the gauge capability ratio ρP will increase with increase with increase in the variance in product variability σp2."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Cusum control charts were originated in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1950s",
            "b) 1960s",
            "c) 1920s",
            "d) 1980s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The emphasis on more and more variability reduction, yield enhancement and process improvement, forced people to create new process monitoring techniques. Cusum charts were originated due to the same reason in 1950s."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the control charts are used in phase I application of SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shewhart control charts",
            "b) Cusum control charts",
            "c) Both, Shewhart control charts and Cusum control charts",
            "d) Neither one of the Shewhart control charts or the Cusum control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shewhart control charts are used for preliminary process monitoring, so the Shewhart control charts are used in the phase I implementation of SPC. "
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the phenomenons likely to occur while the phase I application of SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process likely to be out of control",
            "b) Process changing its state continuously between in-control and out-of-control",
            "c) Experiencing assignable causes",
            "d) Large shifts in the monitored parameters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shewhart control charts are used in phase I implementation of the SPC, where process is likely to be out-of-control, and experiencing assignable causes, which may result in large shifts in the monitored parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of these is a disadvantage of Shewhart control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can be for both attributes and variables",
            "b) Gives process information",
            "c) Using only the information about the last sample observations",
            "d) Uses every information about the process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major disadvantage of a Shewhart control chart is that, it uses only the information about the process contained in the last sample observation, and it ignores the information given by the entire sequence of points."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Shewhart control charts are insensitive to ________ process shifts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small (<1.5σ)",
            "b) Medium (1.5 σ<shift<3 σ)",
            "c) Big (>6 σ)",
            "d) Very Big"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the Shewhart control charts ignore the information about the entire sequence of the points, it ignores the small process shifts, say on the order of 1.5σ or less."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Which of these is a reason why the Shewhart control charts are not used in phase II application of SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because they can count larger shifts in process",
            "b) Because they can analyze information about the last sample observation",
            "c) Because they become insensitive to lower order process shifts",
            "d) Because they are impractical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shewhart control charts are insensitive towards small process shifts. As the process shifts in the phase II application are of very less order, Shewhart control charts are not generally used for phase II application of SPC. "
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Which of these can be applied to Shewhart control charts to enhance their performance in the phase II application of the SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control limits",
            "b) Mean of the process",
            "c) Standard deviation of the process",
            "d) Warning limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To enhance the performance of the Shewhart control charts in the phase II application of the SPC, we can use the warning limits and other sensitizing rules with the Shewhart control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "What is the effect of warning limits and other sensitizing rules over the average run length of the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Does not change the ARL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The warning limits and the other sensitizing rules are used to improve the performance of Shewhart control charts, to get better results in the Phase II applications of the SPC. But it also decreases the ARL of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of the error types are likely to occur when the warning limits are used with Shewhart control charts the phase II of SPC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I",
            "b) Type II",
            "c) Type I and Type II",
            "d) Type III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As ARL of the process reduces, due to the use of warning limits with the Shewhart control charts, we conclude a process out-of-control when it is actually in-control, which is actually type I error."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "What is the full form of the Cusum control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curetted sum control charts",
            "b) Corrected sum control charts",
            "c) Compressive sum control charts",
            "d) Cumulative sum control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Cusum chart is an alternative of the Shewhart control charts. Its full name is cumulative sum control chart, which is used in the place of the Shewhart control charts with warning limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "In which phase of SPC are the Cusum control charts are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase I",
            "b) Phase II",
            "c) Both, phase I and II",
            "d) Neither in phase I nor in phase II"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Cusum control charts, or the cumulative control charts were originated due to the degraded performance of Shewhart control charts in the phase II of SPC. So they are used in the phase II only."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "What is the value of the quantity plotter on the Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j-μ)\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j+2μ)\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j-2μ)\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j+μ)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cusum control charts are plotted instead of Shewhart control charts in phase II applications of SPC. The quantity plotted on the charts is written as,\n\\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j-μ)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "What is the name of the quantity plotted Cion Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cumulative sum from ith sample",
            "b) Cumulative sum to ith sample",
            "c) Cumulative sum to and ith sample",
            "d) Cumulative sum from and ith sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quantity plotted on the Cusum charts or the cumulative sum control charts is Ci. It is called, Cumulative sum to and ith sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Which of these is a reason, why the Cusum charts are better than the Shewhart control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because they are having information about only one sample",
            "b) Because the quantity plotted on the Shewhart control charts is variable",
            "c) Because the quantity plotted on the Cusum chart contains information about more than one sample",
            "d) Because the quantity plotted on the Cusum control charts is containing information about a single sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The quantity plotted in the Cusum charts, contains more information as it contains information about more than one samples (Ci cumulative sum to and including an ith sample)."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Which charts are particularly more effective for sample size one?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) c-charts",
            "c) X bar and s charts",
            "d) Cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Because of the reason that Cusum control charts can detect small process shifts easily, and they contain information about more than one sample, they are better used for sample size=1."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Which charts are more effective for the chemical and process industries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) c-charts",
            "c) X bar and s charts",
            "d) Cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cusum charts are more effective when the rational subgrouping with sample size 1 concept is used. As chemical and process industries use the concept of rational subgrouping with sample size 1, Cusum charts are more productive in them."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "The processes where discrete part manufacturing is done, which charts are better?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-charts",
            "b) c-charts",
            "c) Cusum charts",
            "d) X bar and R charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process where discrete part manufacturing is done, the sample size is usually 1. As the Cusum charts are better and more effective than Shewhart control charts when it comes to sample size 1, they are used in the mentioned situations."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which of these control charts will have a better performance in the discrete part manufacturing assembly, where automatic measurement of each part is done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X bar charts",
            "b) Cusum charts",
            "c) u-charts",
            "d) c-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As automatic measurement of each part is indicating a sample size of 1 unit, the Cusum charts are used for the processes of such type. The reason behind it being that, they are effective for the industries having a sample size, mostly 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Cumulative control charts were first presented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shewhart",
            "b) ASQC",
            "c) ASQ",
            "d) Page"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The initial proposal for the use of the cumulative sum control charts, was first introduced by Page in the year of 1954. Then the improvements and the use of the charts started in the industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "If the mean changes to a higher value, what will be the effect on the cumulative sum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Can decrease or increase",
            "d) Can’t be predicted."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the value of the mean of the process shifts to a higher value i.e. a positive drift, we note form the formula of Cusum,\n\\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_i-μ)\\) \nThat it will introduce a positive drift in the cumulative sum too."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "If the value of the cumulative sum shifts to a lower value what is likely to be the reason for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The decrease in the value of the mean",
            "b) The increase in the value of the mean",
            "c) No change in the value of mean",
            "d) Decrement in the value of the standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is noted while operating on the Cusum chart that, whenever there is a downward drop in the process mean, there is a negative drop in the value of the cumulative sum."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "How are the changes in the conditions of the process, known using the Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By the change in Cusum value",
            "b) By the change in the sample standard deviation",
            "c) By plotting a s chart first",
            "d) By plotting an R chart first"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As a positive drift, and a negative drift in the Cusum or cumulative sum value indicates a shifting of mean in positive or negative direction respectively, we can sense the shifting of mean continuously by checking the Cusum value, and hence the process state."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "A significant trend upwards in the process cumulative sum chart indicates ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shifting of mean in the positive direction",
            "b) Shifting of mean in the negative direction",
            "c) No shift in the process condition",
            "d) No shift in the mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A significant trend developed in the Cusum chart due to the positive drift of the Cusum value, points toward the positive shift of the mean of the process. An assignable cause is present in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Which of these conditions don’t describe an assignable cause in the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A positive shift in the Cusum value",
            "b) A negative shift in the Cusum value",
            "c) Random change in Cusum value",
            "d) Continuous upward drift of Cusum value after a continuous downward drift in the Cusum value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A random change in the Cusum value indicates that the mean is shifting randomly. This indicates an in-control process condition, of the process for which the Cusum chart is made for."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Which of these is another form of the cumulative sum value plotted on the cumulative sum chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i=(x_i-μ)+\\sum_{j=1}^{i-1} (x_j+μ)\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i=(x_i-μ)+C_{i-1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i=(x_i-μ)+\\sum_{j=1}^{i-1} (x_j+2μ)\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i=(x_i-μ)-C_{i-1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As we know,\n\\(C_i=\\sum_{j=1}^i (\\bar{x}_j-μ_0) \\) \nThis can be written as,\n\\(C_i=(x_i-μ)+\\sum_{j=1}^{i-1}(x_j-μ)=(x_i-μ)+C_{i-1}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "If the value of xi=9.29, and Ci-1=-2.56, what will be the value of the cumulative sum for this sample, if the value of μ0=10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -3.27",
            "b) -5.13",
            "c) 3.27",
            "d) 5.13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\nCi=(xi-μ)+Ci-1\nPutting the values from the question, we get,\nCi=-3.27 "
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "How many ways are there to represent the Cusum on the Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are two ways invented for the representation of the Cusums on the Cusum charts; namely Tabular Cusum, and V-mask form of the Cusum."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of these is a name of any way to represent the Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Logarithmic",
            "b) Algorithmic",
            "c) Exponential",
            "d) Normal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two ways of representing the Cusums. The first one is the tabular (or Algorithmic) Cusum, and the second one is the V mask form of Cusum. "
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The tabular Cusums are made to monitor the ____________ of the process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variance",
            "b) Mean",
            "c) Standard deviation",
            "d) Capability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tabular Cusum is generally made to monitor the changes occurring in the mean of the process with respect to the time. This is preferred over the V-mask type."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the assumptions made for the construction of Tabular Cusum charts for the individual measurements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The selected variable varies according to a lognormal distribution",
            "b) The selected variable varies according to a normal distribution",
            "c) The selected variable varies according to a binomial distribution",
            "d) The selected variable varies according to an exponential distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the construction of the tabular cusum charts, it is assumed that the variable for which the Cusum charts are to be plotted, varies on a normal distribution."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an assumption made for the construction of the tabular Cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The selected variable varies on a normal distribution",
            "b) The mean of the normal distribution is available",
            "c) The estimate or the exact value of the standard deviation of the variable",
            "d) The assumptions are very inconsistent with phase II application of SPC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tabular Cusum charts are made with the assumptions that, the selected variable varies on normal distribution with a known mean and standard deviation. The standard deviation estimate may also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "If the process standard deviation increases, how will the cusum chart for monitoring process variability indicate the out-of-control state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The value of Si+ will increase",
            "b) The value of Si+ will decrease",
            "c) The value of Si– will decrease with decrease in the value of Si+",
            "d) The value of Si– will increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the process standard deviation increases, Si+ value will be increased consequently. It will eventually exceed the decision interval h and we will get an out-of-control signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of these is an indication of out-of-control process with low standard deviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in the value of Si+",
            "b) Decrease in the value of Si+ with increase in the value of Si–",
            "c) Increase in the value of Si–",
            "d) Decrease in the value of Si– with decrease in the value of Si–"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the process becomes out-of-control with low value of the process standard deviation, the value of Si–  will increase and eventually exceed the decision interval, h."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to recommend plotting the cusum charts for mean and standard deviation on same graph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hawkins",
            "b) Roberts",
            "c) Atkinson",
            "d) Crowder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Although it is customary to plot the cusum charts for mean and cusum charts for standard deviation on different graphs, Hawkins (1993a) was the first person who recommended to plot them on same graph."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "If the deployment of the cusum is extended to the case of averages of the rational subgroups where sample size n>1, what will be done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The value of xi be replaced by xi",
            "b) The value of xi be replaced by xi",
            "c) The value of Ci+ be replaced by value of Ci–",
            "d) The value of Ci– be replaced by the value of Ci+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the rational subgrouping procedure is adopted with sample size n>1, the cusum charts are built by simply replacing xi by xi and σ by  σ/√n."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "A cusum for normal variance is having the value of upper cusum equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^+ + S^2 – k)\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^+ + S^2 + k)\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^+ – σ^2 + k)\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^+ + σ^2 + k)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the upper cusum for the cusum for normal variance has the value of σ2 replaced by the sample variance Si2. It is expressed as,\n\\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^+ + S^2 + k)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "A cusum for a normal variance has the value of lower cusum equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=min⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^+=max⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^-=min⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the lower cusum for the normal variance is denoted by \\(C_i^-\\). It is expressed by the following formula,\n\\(C_i^-=min⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "If the value of C–i-1+S2+k is lesser than (-1), what will be the value of Ci– equal to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lesser than -1",
            "b) Higher than 1",
            "c) Lower than 0",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that\n\\(C_i^+=min⁡(0,C_{i-1}^- + S^2 + k)\\) \nAlso the cusum values, whether it is the upper cusum, or lower cusum, are either zero or positive. So even if the value of C–i-1+S2+k is lesser than (-1), the value of Ci– will be zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "The V-mask procedure was proposed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crowder",
            "b) Roberts",
            "c) Brinson",
            "d) Barnard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are two procedures to plot the cusum charts. One is called the tabular cusum, and the other is called the V-mask procedure. The V-mask procedure was first introduced by Barnard (1959)."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Which of these is a correct expression for the one sided upper cusum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=min⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^+]\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^+=max⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^+]\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^+=min⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^+ ]\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^+=max⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^+]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tabular cusum works by accumulating derivations from mean that are above target with one statistic Ci+, which is called one sided upper cusum. It is expressed as,\n\\(C_i^+=max⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^+]\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "What is the value of one sided lower cusum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^-=min⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^-]\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-=max⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^-]\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^-=min⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-]\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^-=max⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tabular cusum works also by accumulating derivations from the mean that are below the target with one statistic Ci–. The value of this value is called the one sided lower cusum and its expressed as,\n\\(C_i^-=max⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-]\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "What is K called in the expressions of the one-sided Cusums?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regarded value",
            "b) Related value",
            "c) Resultant value",
            "d) Reference value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The values of the statistics used in the construction of a tabular cusum are called one sided upper and lower Cusums. K is used in their expressions which is called Reference value."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Which of these is another name of the reference value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regarding value",
            "b) Stoppage value",
            "c) Stack value",
            "d) Assignable value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The constant K in the expression of the one-sided Cusums, is called the reference value. It is also called slack value, or allowance. "
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The value of the reference value is chosen ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3/4 ways between mean and the out-of-control mean towards the mean",
            "b) 1/2 ways between mean and the out-of-control mean",
            "c) 3/4 ways between mean and the out-of-control mean towards the out-of-control mean",
            "d) 1/4 ways between mean and the out-of-control mean towards the mean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value of the reference value or K is chosen such that, it stay halfway between the target mean and the out-of-control value of the mean, that we are interested in finding out quickly."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "What is the value δ is called, when used in the expression of K?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The shift of mean in standard deviation units",
            "b) The shift of variance in standard deviation units",
            "c) The shift of standard deviation in mean units",
            "d) The shift of mean in variance units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value δ is used in the expression of K or the reference value.\nK=\\(\\frac{\\delta\\sigma}{2}\\) \nHere this value δ is called the shift of mean in standard deviation units."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "What is the value of μ1(out-of-control mean) in the terms of the actual target mean μ0, and the shift?",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ1=μ0+δσ",
            "b) μ1=μ0+2δσ",
            "c) μ1=μ0+\\(\\frac{δ}{2}\\)σ",
            "d) μ1=μ0-δσ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value μ1 is called the out-of-control mean. It is the value of mean when process changes its state to out-of-control. Its value is,\nμ1=μ0+δσ."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "What is the value of K in the terms of out-of-control mean and the target mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(K=\\frac{|μ_0-μ_1|}{2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(K=\\frac{|μ_1-μ_0|}{2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(K=\\frac{|μ_1-μ_0|}{4}\\) ",
            "d) \\(K=3\\frac{|μ_1-μ_0|}{4}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The value K is called the allowance. This is used in the one-sided upper and lower Cusums expressions. It is expressed as,\n\\(K=\\frac{|μ_1-μ_0|}{2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "What is the starting value of one-sided upper cusum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The one-sided upper cusum is expressed as follows,\n\\(C_i^+=max⁡[0,x_i-(μ_0+K)+C_{i-1}^+]\\) \nThe starting value of this would be C0+ which is always taken as 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "What is the starting value of the one-sided lower cusum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) -1.5",
            "c) 0",
            "d) .3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lower one sided cusum is expressed as follows,\n\\(C_i^-=max⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-]\\) \nThis value is called the starting value of lower one-sided cusum when the value of i=0. The value of C0–=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "If the value of the quantity ”\\((μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-\\)” becomes negative, what will be the value of the value Ci–?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Negative",
            "b) Positive",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Can be both, ±1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(C_i^-=max⁡[0,(μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-]\\) \nSo, as the value of quantity \\((μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-\\) becomes negative, it becomes lesser than 0. So we take the maximum value between zero and it, i.e. Ci–=0"
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Which of these is always correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^-≥0 \\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-≤0\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^->1.323\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^-<-1.323\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the value of Ci–  is chosen as the maximum between zero and quantity \\((μ_0-K)-x_i+C_{i-1}^-\\), we always have Ci–≥0."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "After the value of Ci– increasing than the value of _____ the process is said to be out-of-control.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control interval",
            "b) Decision interval",
            "c) Distribution interval",
            "d) Calculation interval"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a certain value decided for both Ci– and Ci+, after increasing from which, the process is said to be out-of-control. It is called decision interval."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "What are the graphical displays of tabular cusum called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cusum regular charts",
            "b) Cusum regulated display",
            "c) Cusum level display",
            "d) Cusum status charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is useful to present a graphical display for the tabular cusum. These charts are sometimes called the cusum status charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Which of these is a correct statement for cusum status charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A plot between Ci+ or Ci– and the sample number",
            "b) A plot between the Ci+ or Ci– and the sample mean",
            "c) A plot between the Ci+ or Ci– and the sample variance",
            "d) A plot between the Ci+ or Ci– and the sample standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cusum status charts are constructed by plotting Ci+ or Ci– versus the sample number. These are used to get an quick information about the process from the displayed chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Each vertical bar in cusum status chart represents __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The value of Ci+ and Ci–",
            "b) The value of Ci–",
            "c) The value of Ci+",
            "d) Neither the value of Ci+ nor Ci–"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cusum status charts are the charts made to represent the cusum data on a graphical display, where each vertical bar in the cusum status charts, represents the value of Ci+ and Ci–."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "What is analogous to the control limits as in Shewhart control charts, in the cusum status charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The reference value",
            "b) The allowance value",
            "c) The value of the decision intervals",
            "d) The value of Ci+ and Ci–"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the decision interval H can be used as the control limits in the cusum charts as in the Shewhart charts. This gives us an indication about when the process is out-of-control."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "In the Minitab version of the cusum control charts, which of these is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,x_i-μ_0+k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-=min⁡\\left\\{0,x_i-μ_0+k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,x_i-μ_0-k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^-=min⁡\\left\\{0,x_i-μ_0-k-C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Minitab version of the tabular cusum charts uses the negative of Ci– i.e. it uses the following expression for Ci–,\n\\(C_i^-=min⁡\\left\\{0,x_i-μ_0+k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Which of these is true for the Minitab version of tabular cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^-≥0\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-≥9\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^-≤0\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^-≤5\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Minitab version of the tabular cusum uses the negative expression for the Ci–, so the value of Ci– always remains less than or equal to zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of these steps, is not carried out when the process becomes out-of-control when using the cusum control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Search for an assignable cause",
            "b) Taking corrective action",
            "c) Restarting the control chart from zero",
            "d) Continuing the control chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When an out-of-control situation is encountered while using the cusum control charts, we use the same procedure, used as in the Shewhart control charts. First, identifying the assignable cause, then second, taking corrective action, and then restarting the control chart from zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which of these control charts may accurately tell when the assignable cause has occurred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cusum control charts",
            "b) p-charts",
            "c) c-charts",
            "d) x bar and s charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the pattern changes in the cusums due to an assignable cause, the changed pattern gets recorded in all the next cusums. So, we can identify from which cusum, the pattern changed, and hence the assignable cause location can be known. "
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to calculate the estimate of mean of the process in the case of the tabular cusums when Ci+ > H?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0-K+\\frac{C_i^+}{N^+}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K+\\frac{C_i^+}{N^+}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K-\\frac{C_i^+}{N^+}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K+\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cases when a manipulative variable is required to take an out-of-control process back to target valueμ0, we use the new process mean estimate, which is written as,\n\\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K+\\frac{C_i^+}{N^+}\\right\\}\\) "
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of these following expressions can be used to calculate the estimate of mean of the process in the case of the tabular cusums when Ci– > H?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K+\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0-K-\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0-K+\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0+K-\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cases when there is a need to estimate the changed process mean, the expression of new process mean estimate is written as,\n\\(\\hat{μ}=\\left\\{μ_0-K-\\frac{C_i^-}{N^-}\\right\\}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "What of these can be used as the decision interval for the tabular cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2σ",
            "b) 1σ",
            "c) 5σ",
            "d) 4σ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is a generalized rule that, the decision intervals should always be five times of the standard deviations of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "What is the expression for the two sided cusum ARL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{1}{ARL}=\\frac{1}{2ARL^-}+\\frac{1}{2ARL^+}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{1}{ARL}=\\frac{1}{ARL^-}±\\frac{1}{ARL^+}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{1}{ARL}=\\frac{1}{2ARL^-}-\\frac{1}{2ARL^+}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{1}{ARL}=\\frac{1}{ARL^-}+\\frac{1}{ARL^+}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The expression for the ARL of the two sided cusum from the ARLs of the two one sided statistics, is written as,\n\\(\\frac{1}{ARL}=\\frac{1}{ARL^-}+\\frac{1}{ARL^+}\\) \nIt is used to estimate the average time till an out-of-control signal comes from the cusum chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of these is an expression for Siegmund’s approximation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ARL=\\frac{exp⁡(-2∆b)+2∆b-1}{2∆^2}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ARL=\\frac{exp⁡(-2∆b)+2∆b-1}{2∆}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ARL=\\frac{exp⁡(-2∆b)-2∆b+1}{2∆^2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ARL=\\frac{exp⁡(-2∆b)-2∆b-1}{2∆^2}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Siegmund’s approximation is used to evaluate the average run length for the cusum charts. It is expressed as,\n\\(ARL=\\frac{exp⁡(-2∆b)+2∆b-1}{2∆^2}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "What is the standardized value used for xi in the standardized cusum chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(y_i=\\frac{x_i-μ_0}{3σ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(y_i=\\frac{x_i-μ_0}{σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(y_i=\\frac{x_i-μ_0}{2σ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(y_i=\\frac{x_i-μ_0}{6σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many users of the cusum prefer to standardize the variable xi, before performing the calculations. The standardized value of the variable is,\n\\(y_i=\\frac{x_i-μ_0}{σ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "What is the value of one sided upper cusum of the standardized cusum chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,y_i-k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,y_i+k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^+=min⁡\\left\\{0,y_i+k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^+=min\\left\\{0,y_i-k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standardized cusum chart uses the standardized value of variable xi, i.e. yi, so the value of the one-sided upper cusum of the standardized cusum chart will be,\n\\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,y_i-k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "What is the value of the one-sided lower cusum of the standardized cusum chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,-y_i-k+C_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(C_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,y_i-k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(C_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,-y_i-k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(C_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,-y_i-k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standardized cusum uses the different variable to calculate the upper and lower cusums. The lower cusum of the standardized cusum chart is expressed as,\n\\(C_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,-y_i-k+C_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Which of these is an advantage of the standardized cusum chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There can be same means chosen for different processes",
            "b) There can be same standard deviations chosen for different processes",
            "c) The choices of k and h parameters are not scale dependent",
            "d) No variability at all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As in the standardized cusum charts, many charts can now have the same values of k and h, and because of the fact that the choice of k and h is dependent over the value of process standard deviation in normal cusum, the standardized cusum has k and h not scale dependent or σ dependent."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Combined Cusum-Shewhart procedure is applied _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) On-line control",
            "b) On-line measure",
            "c) Off-line control",
            "d) On-line measure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As Combined Cusum-Shewhart procedure is used while using the cusum charts to detect the large process shifts while keeping the process continued, this is called an on-line control."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "To apply Shewhart-cusum combined procedure, the Shewhart control limits should be applied almost _________ standard deviation from the center.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 3.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Combined Cusum-Shewhart procedure is an on-line control method. It is used to detect larger process shifts. The Shewhart control limits in the procedure are put approx. 3.5 standard deviations away from center."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FIR feature in the cusum charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First initial response",
            "b) Fast initial response",
            "c) First initiation response",
            "d) Free initial response"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cusum control charts sensitivity at the process start-up is improved by the means of the FIR feature of the cusum charts. It means the Fast Initial Response."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "What is the meaning of the 50% headstart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The value of C0–  equal to H/2",
            "b) The value of C0+ equal to H/2",
            "c) Both the values of C0+ and C0– equal to H/2",
            "d) Both the values of C0+ and C0– lesser than H/2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The FIR feature of the cusum charts essentially sets the starting values of both, the values of C0+ and C0– equal to typically, H/2. This is called 50% headstart."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "What is the standardized variable value for the cusum charts from Hawkins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(v_i=\\frac{\\sqrt{|y_i|}-0.822}{0.349}\\) ",
            "b) \\(v_i=\\frac{\\sqrt{|y_i|}-0.822}{0.500}\\) ",
            "c) \\(v_i=\\frac{3\\sqrt{|y_i|}-0.822}{0.349}\\) ",
            "d) \\(v_i=\\frac{2\\sqrt{|y_i|}-0.822}{0.349}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hawkins presented a new standardized variable vi to be used in the standardized cusum chart. It had a value equal to,\n\\(v_i=\\frac{\\sqrt{|y_i|}-0.822}{0.349}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The standardized variable vi was subjected to vary more with respect to ____________ than process mean.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample mean",
            "b) Sample variance",
            "c) Process variance",
            "d) Process standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hawkins had presented the std. variable vi to construct a cusum chart, which could possibly monitor process variability, by the variation of the variance of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "The two-sided standardized scale, i.e. standard deviation cusums will have its upper cusum value equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(S_i^+=max⁡⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k+S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(S_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,v_i+k-S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(S_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k-S_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(S_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k+S_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two-sided standardized scale cusums was first presented by Hawkins. This has the upper cusum value equal to,\n\\(S_i^+=max⁡⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k+S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "What is the value of lower cusum in the standardized scale cusum chart for process variability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(S_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k+S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "b) \\(S_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,v_i-k+S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\) ",
            "c) \\(S_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,-v_i-k+S_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\) ",
            "d) \\(S_i^+=max⁡\\left\\{0,-v_i-k+S_{i-1}^+\\right\\}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the lower cusum used in the standardized scale cusum chart, used for monitoring the process variability, is having the negative value of what was used in the normal cusum. This is written as,\n\\(S_i^-=max⁡\\left\\{0,-v_i-k+S_{i-1}^-\\right\\}\\)"
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "The values of Si+ or Si– at the starting are ____ if the FIR feature is not used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) H",
            "c) H/2",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The values of Si+ or Si– are H/2 mostly when the fast initial response feature is used. When it is not used the values of them become zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "What is the full form of E in the EWMA chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponentially",
            "b) Experimentally",
            "c) Exactly",
            "d) Estimated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWMA charts are a better alternative to the Shewhart control charts. The full form of E in the EWMA chart is exponentially."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "What is the full form of EWMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponentially weighted moving average",
            "b) Exponentially weighted measured approximate",
            "c) Exponentially weighted moving approximate",
            "d) Exponentially weighted measured average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWMA charts were developed after the cusum charts. They have a full form of Exponentially Weighted Moving Average charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "EWMA charts are better than Shewhart control charts in detecting the ___________ shifts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large process",
            "b) Medium process",
            "c) Small process",
            "d) Every process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EWMA charts and Cusum charts are used instead of the Shewhart control charts as the capability of these charts to find small process shifts, is greater than the Shewhart control charts’ capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an advantage of EWMA control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Almost equivalent performance to the cusum charts",
            "b) Easier set up than cusum charts",
            "c) Easier to operate than cusum charts",
            "d) Intricacy is a little higher than cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EWMA control charts are the control charts, which have almost equivalent performance to the cusum charts, and in some ways, they are easier to set up and operate."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Who did first introduce the EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lucas (1990)",
            "b) Saccucci (1990)",
            "c) Roberts (1959)",
            "d) Crowder (1987a, 1989)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The EWMA charts, which are also called the Exponentially Weighted Moving Average charts, were first introduced in the year of 1990 by Roberts. It was a revolutionary step towards process control."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "What is the correct expression for the EWMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) zi = λxi + (1-λ) zi-1",
            "b) zi = λxi – (1-λ) zi-1",
            "c) zi = λxi + (1-λ) zi+1",
            "d) zi = λxi + (1+λ) zi-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWMA charts use the exponentially weighted moving average as the quantity plotted. The EWMA used is expressed as,\nzi = λxi + (1-λ) zi-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Which of these is correct for λ in EWMA expression?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 > λ",
            "b) 1 < λ",
            "c) 1 ≤ λ",
            "d) 0 < λ ≤ 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EWMA expression is written as,\nzi = λxi + (1-λ) zi-1\nWhere λ is a constant, and it is having a value, 0 < λ ≤ 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "What is the starting value of the EWMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Process target mean",
            "c) Process target variance",
            "d) Process target standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The starting value of the exponentially weighted moving averages is z0 and its starting value is equal to the process target (mean). So,\nz0 = μ0."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which of these is another name of EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GMA charts",
            "b) AMA charts",
            "c) EMA charts",
            "d) RMA charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of the fact, that the weights decline geometrically when connected by a smooth curve, EWMA charts are also called the GMA charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "GMA stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geosum moved average",
            "b) Geometric Moving average",
            "c) Geometrically moved average",
            "d) Geocentric moving average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GMA stands for Geometric moving average. It is another name of the EWMA charts because the weights decrease geometrically when connected by a smooth curve. "
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of these is the use of the EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In time series modeling",
            "b) In Real-time processing",
            "c) In acceptance sampling",
            "d) In designing of experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWMA charts are better at forecasting future results and predicting future trends in the control chart. So they are used in time series modeling and in forecasting future process behavior."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Which of these is an ideal chart for individual measurements among these all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-chart",
            "b) Cusum charts",
            "c) EWMA charts",
            "d) x bar and R chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since EWMA can be viewed as a weighted average of all past and current observations, it is very sensitive to the normality assumption. It is therefore an ideal control chart to use with individual observations."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "If the observations xi are independent random variables with variance σ2 then according to the EWMA charts, the variance of zi will be ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sigma_{zi}^2 = \\sigma^2 (\\frac{λ}{2-λ})[1+(1+λ)^{2i}]\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sigma_{zi}^2 = \\sigma^2 (\\frac{λ}{2-λ})[1+(1-λ)^{2i}]\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sigma_{zi}^2 = \\sigma^2 (\\frac{λ}{2-λ})[1-(1-λ)^{2i}]\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sigma_{zi}^2 = \\sigma^2 (\\frac{λ}{2+λ})[1-(1-λ)^{2i}]\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The variance of the variable zi when used with EWMA, we get to know that, weights decline geometrically. So the variance becomes,\n\\(\\sigma_{zi}^2 = \\sigma^2 (\\frac{λ}{2-λ})[1-(1-λ)^{2i}]\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "The EWMA charts are constructed by plotting _______________ versus the sample number i or the time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sample observation, xi",
            "b) The sample variance, σ2",
            "c) The variance of variable zi i.e. \\(\\sigma_{z_i}^2\\) ",
            "d) The variable zi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EWMA charts are the plots for knowing the trends in data due to assignable causes. They are constructed by plotting the variable zi versus the sample number i or time."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "The UCL of the EWMA charts is given by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The upper control limit of the EWMA charts is L times the standard deviation of the variable zi added, to the variable zi starting value μ0. It is expressed by,\nUCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "What is the center line value of the EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) x",
            "d) μ0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The center line value of the EWMA charts is the target value, i.e. the mean without shift. It is expressed as,\nCL=μ0"
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "What is the value of L=2.27 upper control limit for a EWMA chart which has value of λ=0.10 and the value of the standard deviation σ=1 and the value of μ0=10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.41",
            "b) 9.59",
            "c) 10.27",
            "d) 10.10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that,\nUCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) \nPutting the values, we get UCL=10.27."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "What is the value of LCL of EWMA control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that the LCL of the EWMA charts are just L times the standard deviation. So the LCL of the EWMA charts is given by,\nLCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{[\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}]}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "When the EWMA charts are in operation for quite a long period, what will be the value of the UCL of the chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(μ_0-3Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(μ_0+2Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: EWMA charts, when are in operation for a long period, the term, 1-(1-λ)2i becomes unity as i becomes large. So the UCL can be written as,\nUCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "What will be the value of the UCL for a control chart, which has the value of λ=0.10, L=2.7, σ=1 and μ0=10? The value of i can be assumed quite large.",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=10.67",
            "b) UCL=10.62",
            "c) UCL=9.38",
            "d) UCL=9.37"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that when the value of i is high, we calculate UCL by the following expression.\nUCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) \nPutting the values, we get UCL=10.62."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "What is the LCL value when the value of i  becomes high in the EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(μ_0-6Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(μ_0+3Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(μ_0+Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that the difference between the UCL and the CL is the same as the difference between the CL and the LCL. So we can write the expression for LCL when the process is running for quite a long period as,\nLCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "After some time, i  in the equation of LCL becomes high. What will be the value of λ when this occurs? You may use, LCL=9.38, the standard deviation= 1 and the target mean = 10.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 2.8",
            "c) 3.0",
            "d) 6.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that,\nLCL=\\(μ_0-Lσ\\sqrt{\\left\\{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}\\right\\}}\\) \nHere, we consider the high value of i. When we put the given values, we get, λ=0.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of the parameters are chosen wisely in the case of EWMA charts to get a desired ARL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only L",
            "b) Only σ",
            "c) Both, L and λ",
            "d) Only λ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that in the parameters used for constructing EWMA charts, only L and λ are the design parameters. So we choose them wisely to obtain desired ARL."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "When the value of λ is small, and if the value of EWMA is on one side of the CL and the shift of mean occurs in the opposite direction, EWMA takes several periods to react to that shift. This is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weight effect",
            "b) Stationary effect",
            "c) Inertia effect",
            "d) Tendency effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The staying of EWMA on a side till a very heavy shift occurs in the process mean; is called the inertia effect of the EWMA charts. This occurs only when the value of λ is very small."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "How is the effectiveness of EWMA charts by inertia effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) No change",
            "d) Can either decrease or increase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As inertial effects increase the time for EWMA to react to a process mean shift, it ultimately is influencing the effectiveness of EWMA charts. This decreases the effectiveness of EWMA."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of these values of λ gives the weights given to current and previous observations matching as closely as possible the weights when these observations give by a Shewhart chart with the WE rules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.7",
            "b) 0.9",
            "c) 0.2",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of λ is recommended by Hunter to be equal to 0.4 to get the weights given to current and previous observations, matching closely to the weights when these observations give by a Shewhart chart, with Western Electric rules."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "The largest standard deviation of the sample mean from the target, not leading to an immediate out-of-control signal, is called _______________ of a control chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARL",
            "b) UCL",
            "c) Signal resolution",
            "d) Signal resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Signal Resistance is a very important property of any control chart. It is defined as the maximum standard deviation of the sample mean from the target or in-control value, not leading to an immediate out-of-control signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "For a Shewhart control chart, what is the value of SR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zα/2",
            "b) 2",
            "c) L",
            "d) 2L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of SR is the maximum standard deviation of mean off-target without any out-of-control signal. This is L for the Shewhart control chart, i.e.\nSR(x)=L\nWhere L is the multiplier used to obtain the control limits."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Which of these is a having a constant SR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A x chart",
            "b) A Cusum chart",
            "c) An EWMA chart",
            "d) Every control chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Shewhart control charts have the signal resistance value equal to the multiplier used to obtain the control limit, which is constant. As a x chart is also a Shewhart control chart, so for this also, “ SR=constant”."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of these is not having a constant SR value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) c-chart",
            "b) R-chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) EWMA chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that only Shewhart control chart have the SR value equal to constant. As EWMA chart is not a Shewhart chart, it does not have a constant SR value."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "What is the value of SR for an EWMA chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}+(λ-1)w}{λ}\\) ",
            "b) SR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}-(1-λ)w}{λ}\\) ",
            "c) SR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}-(λ-1)w}{λ}\\) ",
            "d) SR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}+(1-λ)w}{λ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We have derived an equation of an EWMA chart SR which includes the value of the EWMA statistic. The SR is given by,\nSR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}-(1-λ)w}{λ}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "What is the value of the term “w” called in the SR value of a EWMA chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First EWMA value",
            "b) Last EWMA value",
            "c) Value of EWMA statistic",
            "d) Weight average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SR value of EWMA chart is given by,\nSR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}-(1-λ)w}{λ}\\) \nHere, w is called the value of EWMA statistic."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of these is the maximum value of the SR averaged over all values of EWMA statistic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(SR_{max} (EWMA)=L \\frac{(2-λ)}{λ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(SR_{max}(EWMA)=L\\sqrt{\\frac{(2-λ)}{λ}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(SR_{max} (EWMA)=L+\\sqrt{\\frac{(2-λ)}{λ}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(SR_{max} (EWMA)=L-\\sqrt{\\frac{(2-λ)}{λ}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the chart has asymptotic limits, then the maximum value of the signal resistance averaged over all values of EWMA statistic is,\n\\(SR_{max}(EWMA)=L\\sqrt{\\frac{(2-λ)}{λ}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Small values of λ gives ______ values of the SR (EWMA).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Larger",
            "b) Lower",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Both, larger and smaller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As we know that,\nSR(EWMA)=\\(\\frac{L\\sqrt{\\frac{λ}{2-λ}}-(1-λ)w}{λ}\\) \nWe get the inference that, SR(EWMA)∝1/λ, so SR(EWMA) will be larger for smaller values of λ."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which of these methods can be used to counteract the signal resistance in case of small values of λ with EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To use a cusum chart paralleled",
            "b) To use a Shewhart control chart paralleled",
            "c) To just wait for EWMA chart to be plotted till 50 observations",
            "d) To increase the value of process mean target"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To counteract the signal resistance’s higher value in the case of low λ value, we use the Shewhart control charts in conjunction with an EWMA chart. "
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Who were the first persons to recommend the use of Shewhart control charts with the EWMA charts with low values of λ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Woodall and Mahmoud",
            "b) Woodall and Roberts",
            "c) Roberts and Mahmoud",
            "d) Roberts and Crowder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Woodall and Mahmoud (2005) recommended to always use a Shewhart control chart with a EWMA chart (especially when λ is small), as one way to counteract the signal resistance’s high value."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an advantage of using a Shewhart control chart with the EWMA chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detection of larger process shifts",
            "b) ARL adjustment",
            "c) Counteraction to the high signal resistance value",
            "d) No defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that Shewhart control charts are used with the EWMA control charts. They provide advantages like easy ARL adjustment, counteraction to high signal resistance value, and detection of larger process shifts, without lowering the ability to find lower process shifts."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an advantage of low value of λ in the case of EWMA charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good ARL performance",
            "b) Insensitivity to the normality of the data",
            "c) Good ability to detect the larger process shifts",
            "d) Easy detection of small process shifts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Low values of λ are quite helpful in finding small process shifts, good AR performance, and in increasing the insensitivity of the EWMA charts to the normality of the data. They don’t give the charts ability to detect the larger process shifts."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "In the case of Shewhart charts, if the data is not according to the normal distribution, the actual in-control ARL (ARL0) will be ____________ the expected value.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Considerably higher than",
            "b) Considerably lower than",
            "c) Equal to",
            "d) Almost equal to"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is experimentally determined that if the process data does not follow the normal distribution, then the Shewhart control charts ARL value will be quite less than the value expected based on the normality assumption."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "What is the initial S in EWMS stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Severity error",
            "b) Signal error",
            "c) Square error",
            "d) Simple error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The EWMS charts were used to monitor the variability in the process. They are variants of EWMA chart. EWMS stands for Exponentially Weighted Mean Square error."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Who were the first people to introduce the EWMA charts to monitor process standard deviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) McGregor and Harris",
            "b) Harris and Roberts",
            "c) Crowder and Roberts",
            "d) Harris and Roberts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It was Macgregor, and Harris (1993), who were the first people to identify the importance of EWMA charts to monitor process std deviation. They recommended using EWMS charts to do so."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "What is the value of EWMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(S_i^2= λ(x_i-μ)^2-(1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(S_i^2= λ(x_i-μ)^2-(1+λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(S_i^2= λ(x_i-μ)^2+(1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(S_i^2= λ(x_i-μ)^2+(1+λ) S_{i-1}^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: EWMS is defined as the exponentially weighted mean square error. It is expressed as,\\(S_i^2= λ(x_i-μ)^2+(1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "“Si2/σ2” has an approximate __________ distribution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal",
            "b) Lognormal",
            "c) Exponential",
            "d) Chi-square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the observations in EWMS are independent and normally distributed, then Si2/σ2 will have an approximate chi-square distribution, with v=(2-λ)/λ degrees of freedom."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "EWRMS chart plots __________ on the control chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponentially weighted root moving square error",
            "b) Exponentially weighted root mean square error",
            "c) Exponentially weighted root mean signal error",
            "d) Exponentially weighted root moving signal error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If we have a target value for the mean, and if we want to monitor process standard deviation, we use the EWRMS charts which use Exponentially Weighted Root Mean Square error."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "EWRMS charts have the upper limit of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\frac{σ_0}{2} \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{2v}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWRMS chart is plotted by obtaining the value of Exponentially Weighted Root Mean Square error, which has an approximate chi-square distribution. It has an upper limit of,\nUCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "What is the lower limit of the EWRMS chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(3σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,1-\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,1-\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{2v}}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,1-\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(\\frac{σ_0}{2} \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,1-\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that the EWRMS chart has an approximate chi-square distribution when the observations are independent and normally distributed. So LCL of the EWRMS chart will be,\nLCL=\\(σ_0 \\sqrt{\\frac{χ_{v,1-\\frac{α}{2}}^2}{v}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "EWRMS chart is sensitive to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process mean only",
            "b) Process standard deviation only",
            "c) Neither process mean nor standard deviation",
            "d) Both, process mean and standard deviation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EWRMS chart is constructed to monitor the process standard deviation. But this also, is considered that the process mean is also a factor affecting the EWRMS chart. So EWRMS chart is sensitive to both, the process mean and the standard deviation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "EWMV is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exponentially weighted mean variability",
            "b) Exponentially weighted moving variance",
            "c) Exponentially weighted mean variance",
            "d) Exponentially weighted moving variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EWMV is the exponentially weighted moving variance. It is a term derived from the EWRMS and it is used in measuring variability of the process with EWMA charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What is the value of EWMV?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(S_i^2=λ(x_i-z_i)^2- (1+λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(S_i^2=λ(x_i-z_i)^2± (1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(S_i^2=λ(x_i-z_i)^2- (1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(S_i^2=λ(x_i-z_i)^2+ (1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The EWMV is said to be the exponentially weighted moving average. It is expressed by the following expression,\n\\(S_i^2=λ(x_i-z_i)^2+ (1-λ) S_{i-1}^2\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "What is the upper limit for the EWMA for Poisson data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(μ_0+A_U \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(μ_0-A_U \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(μ_0-A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(μ_0+A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EWMA is generally plotted for normal data. It is also said that the EWMA chart with low value of λ is nonparametric. When EWMA is plotted for Poisson data, the UCL is,\nUCL=\\(μ_0+A_U \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "LCL for EWMA chart for Poisson distribution is written as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LCL=\\(μ_0-A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "b) LCL=\\(μ_0+A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1+λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "c) LCL=\\(μ_0+A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\) ",
            "d) LCL=\\(μ_0-A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EWMA charts are made to monitor the process mean shift. The EWMA chart for Poisson distribution is plotted with an assumption that, the data from the process follows Poisson distribution, It has LCL of,\nLCL=\\(μ_0-A_L \\sqrt{\\frac{λμ_0}{2-λ}\\big\\{1-(1-λ)^{2i}\\big\\}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "“AL” in the expression of the LCL of EWMA charts for Poisson distribution, is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower control limit factor",
            "b) Lower allowance factor",
            "c) Life Allowance factor",
            "d) Last Allowance factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The factors AU and AL are included in the expressions of UCL and LCL of the EWMA charts plotted for Poisson data, respectively. They are called upper and lower control limit factors respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used as a forecast of where the process mean will be at the next time period?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) EWMA chart",
            "d) R-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The recursion of EWMA is the property of the EWMA statistic. That is why, the EWMA charts show trend due to an assignable cause. This recursion is always same, whether the EWMA charts are plotted for normal data or for the Poisson data."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "The moving average span w at a time I is defined as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(M_i=\\frac{x_i+x_{i-1}+⋯x_{w+1}}{w}\\) ",
            "b) \\(M_i=\\frac{x_i+x_{i-1}+⋯x_{w+1}}{i}\\) ",
            "c) \\(M_i=\\frac{x_i+x_{i-1}+⋯x_{i-w+1}}{w}\\) ",
            "d) \\(M_i=\\frac{x_i+x_{i-1}+⋯x_{i-w+1}}{i}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As Poisson EWMA has a better ability of detecting small process shifts in the phase II applications of SPC, they are also having a better ability to detect assignable causes than Shewhart c-chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which of these is the correct expansion of DNOM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deviation from Lognormal",
            "b) Derived from normal",
            "c) Deviation from normal",
            "d) Deviation from normality"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DNOM in DNOM control chart denote the deviation from normal. This technique is used for the process quality control in the case of short process run or production runs."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Which of these is used as a technique for process control for short production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using deviation from nominal to plot the control chart",
            "b) Using the variable value to plot the control chart",
            "c) Using the variable change to plot the control chart",
            "d) Using the variable decrease or increase to plot the chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The short production runs are having very wide applications in modern industries. The statistical process control technique used for the short production runs is generally measuring deviation from nominal value to plot the control chart, instead of the variable control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "If the Mi is the actual sample measurement, and TA is a nominal value, what will be the DNOM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) xi = Mi – 2TA",
            "b) xi = Mi – TA",
            "c) xi = 2TA – Mi",
            "d) xi = TA + Mi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The deviation from the normal or nominal value (DNOM) is used for the plotting of DNOM control chart. The deviation from the normal is evaluated as,\nxi = Mi – TA."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "The mean of the variable measured is replaced by the mean of ________ value in the case of the DNOM chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal value",
            "b) Deviation from normal",
            "c) Range",
            "d) Deviation from normal range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The DNOM chart is used for short production runs, which used DNOM or deviation from normal as the xas in the case of x chart. SO the mean of variable measured is replaced by the mean of the DNOM values."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "If in a manufacturing process, the measurements for a certain dimension for a part are, 50, 51 and 52; where the nominal value of the dimension measured is 50, what will be the DNOM mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 51",
            "d) 0.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that the deviations from nominal are,\nxi = Mi – TA\nBy putting values, we get DNOM’s 0, 1 and 2. The mean DNOM will be 1.0."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "How many samples are generally taken before calculating the control limits for the DNOM x bar and R charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We use the DNOM mean for the plot of the x bar and R charts using the deviation from the normal. It is recommended that we should take almost 20 samples before calculating the control limits for DNOM x bar and R chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which of these assumptions are made while using the DNOM approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The process standard deviation is same for all parts",
            "b) The process standard deviation is different for all parts",
            "c) The samples size is variable",
            "d) The sample size is 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DNOM approach is defined as the method to plot control charts by calculating the deviation from the nominal value. While using this approach, it is assumed that, the process standard deviation is same for all parts. "
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of these is true for DNOM approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sample size is variable",
            "b) The process standard deviation is different for all parts",
            "c) The sample size varies from one part to another",
            "d) The sample size remains same for all parts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is desirable that, the sample sizes, which are used to find out the observations data, should be constant, when the DNOM approach is to be used for the control charting."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "What is used instead of Nominal values when the nominal value is not given in the case of DNOM approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Historical process standard deviation",
            "b) New standard deviation",
            "c) Historical process average",
            "d) Historical process variance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DNOM approach is based on using the deviation from normal data instead of the variable itself. When the nominal value is not given for this, the historical process average is used instead of the nominal value."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of these does not need to have the nominal value specified frequently?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When part has two-sided specifications",
            "b) When part has one-sided specifications",
            "c) When the part can’t have one sided specifications",
            "d) When the part has either one-sided or two sided specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is generally very obvious that the DNOM approach needs the nominal value quite frequently but, when the part has one-sided specifications, the nominal is not specified frequently."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Standard hypothesis testing procedures are used to compare __________ process average to a desired process target to determine whether the process mean is different from the target.",
        "Options": [
            "a) New",
            "b) Historical",
            "c) Correct",
            "d) Disturbed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The DNOM uses the historical process average data when the nominal is not available. Standard hypothesis test procedures are used to compare this with the process target, to check their difference.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of these will work correctly and efficiently, when the process standard deviations are different for different part numbers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standardized x bar and R charts",
            "b) Standardized attribute charts",
            "c) DNOM charts",
            "d) Both, the cusum and EWMA charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While creating the DNOM based x bar and R charts, it’s assumed that the different parts have same standard deviations. When they are not same, the standardized charts are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Standardized R chart which uses control limits D3 and D4 has the value of \\(R_i^s\\) = _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(R_i^s=\\frac{3R_i}{R_j}\\) ",
            "b) \\(R_i^s=\\frac{R_i}{2R_j}\\) ",
            "c) \\(R_i^s=\\frac{2R_i}{R_j}\\) ",
            "d) \\(R_i^s=\\frac{R_i}{R_j}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standardized R chart is used when the parts have different standard deviations. It has the quantity plotted as,\n\\(R_i^s=\\frac{R_i}{R_j}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "What is the UCL of the standardized R chart for short production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D4",
            "b) D5",
            "c) D1",
            "d) D2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standardized R chart is the best way to study the short production run data when the part standard deviations are not same. This chart has UCL value of D4."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "What is the value of LCL of the standardized R chart for short runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D4",
            "b) D2",
            "c) D1",
            "d) D3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standardized R chart is used to study the short production runs. The effectiveness of this chart depends on the control limits chosen. It has UCL and LCL of values, D4  and D3 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "What is the value of standard variable plotted in the standardized x bar chart for short run production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{x}_i^s=\\frac{\\bar{M}_i-T_j}{2\\bar{R}_j}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{x}_i^s=\\frac{\\bar{M}_i+T_j}{\\bar{R}_j}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{x}_i^s=\\frac{\\bar{M}_i-T_j}{\\bar{R}_j}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{x}_i^s=\\frac{2\\bar{M}_i-T_j}{\\bar{R}_j}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standardized charts are plotted for both R and x bar. The x bar chart has the value of the standard variable as,\n\\(\\bar{x}_i^s=\\frac{\\bar{M}_i-T_j}{\\bar{R}_j}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The standardized x bar chart has the value of LCL when used for short production runs is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) –A2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) A2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standardized x bar chart is used to find the process performance of short production runs. This chart has the LCL value equal to –A2."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Which of these has the same difference between the LCL and Center line, and the UCL and the center line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standardized R chart for short production runs",
            "b) Standardized x bar charts for short production runs",
            "c) Both, standardized x bar and R charts for short production runs",
            "d) Neither one of the standardized R chart and standardized x bar charts for short production runs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The x bar chart (standardized) for short production runs, has the LCL and UCL values equal to ∓A2respectively. So the difference from the centerline for them is equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "The term Mi, which is used in the expression of the standard variable used in standardized x bar charts for short production runs, is defined as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average of averages of standard deviations",
            "b) Average of original mean measurements",
            "c) Moving average",
            "d) Exponentially weighted moving average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term Mi is the average of original mean measurements. It is used in the expression of the standard variable used in the standardized x bar charts for short production runs."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Rj is the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Target value for range",
            "b) Target value for ratios",
            "c) Result of jth part",
            "d) Ratio of jth part"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rj is used in the expression of the standard value variable in the standardized R chart. It is defined as the target value for range for each part number.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Tj stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Target value for relative range",
            "b) Target value for relative mean",
            "c) target value for x bar for each part number",
            "d) Target value for tested value of the variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term Tj is used in the expression of the standardized x bar variable, which is used in the standardized x bar chart for the short production runs. It is the target value for the x bar for each part number."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of these is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\bar{R}_j=\\frac{Sd_2}{c_4}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\bar{R}_j=\\frac{Sd_2}{c_2}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{R}_j=\\frac{Sd_2}{2c_2}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\bar{R}_j=\\frac{d_2}{c_4}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of target for the range and the x bar, i.e. Rj  and Tj are specified using the specifications for Tj, and using the history for Rj. Here we can say that,\n\\(\\bar{R}_j=\\frac{Sd_2}{c_4}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Standardized control chart approach for short production runs was presented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rodriguez",
            "b) Roberts",
            "c) Crowder",
            "d) Farnum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Farnum (1992) has presented a generalized approach to the DNOM procedure. The standardized control chart approach is a special case of his method."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "According to Farnum, the coefficient of variation is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\frac{σ}{μ}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\frac{μ}{σ}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{2σ}{μ}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\frac{2μ}{σ}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Farnum was the first person to present the generalized approach to the DNOM procedure. He defined the coefficient of variation as σ/μ."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Which of these is true according to Farnum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The coefficient of the variation should be randomly varying",
            "b) The coefficient of the variation should be systematically varying",
            "c) The coefficient of the variation should be varying, maybe randomly or systematically",
            "d) The coefficient of the variation must be constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Farnum defined the coefficient of variation as σ/μ, which he used to give his generalized approach to DNOM procedure. According to him, the coefficient of variation should be constant, which probably occurs fairly often in practice."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Which of these is correct target value for standardized control chart for fraction nonconforming for shorter production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) p",
            "b) np",
            "c) c",
            "d) R̅"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The short production runs concept can also be used for attributes control chart. The standardized p chart for short production runs uses the target value equal to p."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "What is the statistic used to plot on control chart for a standardized p-chart for short production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(Z_i=\\frac{\\hat{p}_i+\\bar{p}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(Z_i=\\frac{\\hat{p}_i-\\bar{p}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(Z_i=\\frac{\\hat{p}_i-\\bar{p}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(Z_i=\\frac{\\hat{p}_i+\\bar{p}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}{n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The p-charts are plotted on the data of no of samples not conforming. The statistic plotted on the standardized version of it, is expressed as,\n\\(Z_i=\\frac{\\hat{p}_i-\\bar{p}}{\\frac{\\sqrt{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "What is the value of standard deviation for the standardized p-chart for short production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(\\bar{p}-1)}{n}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{2n}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standardized control charts are used to monitor processes for short production runs. The standardized p-chart which is used in short production runs is having the standard deviation value equal to,\n\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "What is the standard deviation value for the standardized c chart used for the short production runs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{c}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\bar{c}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\hat{c}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standard deviation value for the standardized c chart remains constant if it is used for the short production runs. It is expressed as,\n\\(\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "What is the value of the statistic to be plotted on the standardized c-chart which is designed to run in the short production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(Z_i=\\frac{c_i+2\\bar{c}}{\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(Z_i=\\frac{c_i-2\\bar{c}}{\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(Z_i=\\frac{c_i-\\bar{c}}{\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(Z_i=\\frac{c_i+\\bar{c}}{\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The c chart is plotted keeping the nonconformity number data as the observations. The statistic which is to be standardized version of it, when the case is of the short production runs, is\n\\(Z_i=\\frac{c_i-2\\bar{c}}{\\sqrt{\\bar{c}}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "What is the value of the target value for the number nonconforming chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) np",
            "b) 2p",
            "c) 3p",
            "d) 2np"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number nonconforming chart is called the np chart too. It plots the number of nonconforming samples in total samples. The target value for the number nonconforming chart is np."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "The attribute ui when plotted on standardized control chart for short production runs, the statistic plotted on the chart has the value equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(Z_i=\\frac{u_i-\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(Z_i=\\frac{u_i+2\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(Z_i=\\frac{u_i+\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(Z_i=\\frac{u_i-2\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attribute u is called the average number of nonconformities per unit. The standardized u-chart is plotted for statistic,\n\\(Z_i=\\frac{u_i-\\bar{u}}{\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "What is the standard deviation of the number of nonconformities per unit, when the standardized u-chart is used for monitoring the process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{2n}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(\\frac{\\sqrt{u}}{n}\\) ",
            "d) \\(\\sqrt{\\bar{u}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The deviation of the number of nonconformities per unit is plotted on Shewhart u-chart. Its standard deviation is expressed as,\nstandard deviation=\\(\\sqrt{\\frac{\\bar{u}}{n}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "What is the value of the statistic plotted on the standardized np-chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(z_i=\\frac{n\\hat{p}_i+n\\bar{p}}{\\sqrt{n\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}}\\) ",
            "b) \\(z_i=\\frac{n\\hat{p}_i-n\\bar{p}}{\\sqrt{n\\bar{p}(1+\\bar{p})}}\\) ",
            "c) \\(z_i=\\frac{n\\hat{p}_i+n\\bar{p}}{\\sqrt{n\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}\\) ",
            "d) \\(z_i=\\frac{n\\hat{p}_i-n\\bar{p}}{\\sqrt{n\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The np chart monitors the process by using the data of the nonconforming samples. The statistic plotted on the standardized version of it for short production run is,\n\\(z_i=\\frac{n\\hat{p}_i-n\\bar{p}}{\\sqrt{n\\bar{p}(1-\\bar{p})}}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "The upper limit of the standardized c-chart for short production runs is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) -3",
            "d) +3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The c chart is used to plot the number of nonconformities on the control chart. The standardized version of it has the UCL of +3 and LCL of -3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "The LCL of the standardized p-chart is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -2",
            "b) +3",
            "c) -1",
            "d) -3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LCL and UCL of the standardized p-chart are at the same units away from the center line which is at zero. The UCL and the LCL of the standardized p-chart are ±3."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "The center line of the np-chart is at _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) -2",
            "b) +2",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The control chart, which plots the number of nonconforming samples, is called np-chart. This charts when standardized, have their center line at the zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Which of these correctly shows the correct values for standardized u-chart in the order of CL, UCL and LCL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0, 3 and -3",
            "b) 3, 0 and -3",
            "c) 0, -3 and 3",
            "d) -3, 0 and 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: THE u-chart, when standardized, has the center line at zero value. The values of the UCL and LCL of the standardized version of u-chart, plotted for short production runs, are ±3."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which of these does not have the LCL and UCL at ∓3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standardized u-chart",
            "b) Standardized R-chart",
            "c) Standardized c-chart",
            "d) Standardized p-chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standardized attribute charts are the only charts which have their upper and lower control limits at ±3. Variable control charts do not have their control limits at ±3."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "EWMA and cusum charts can be used for the short production runs because ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are good in phase II",
            "b) They have shorter ARL",
            "c) They don’t detect process shift",
            "d) They detect larger process shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EWMA charts and the cusum charts both, find applications in the short production run cases. This is due to the fact that the EWMA charts and the Cusum charts both have shorter ARL than the Shewhart charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "Which of these is suitable for the short run environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) x bar chart",
            "b) R chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) Self starting cusum chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Cusum charts are effective for subgroups size of one. The self starting version of the Cusum charts is particularly suitable for the short run environment due to the same fact."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "Which of these is not one of the areas for which, the self starting cusum approach uses regular process measurements for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For establishing the cusum",
            "b) For calibrating the cusum",
            "c) For acceptance sampling",
            "d) For process monitoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The self starting approach of cusum charts uses regular process measurements for both establishing the cusum, and calibrating of cusum. These measurements are also used for process monitoring."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Which of these is eliminated by the self starting approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phase I parameter estimation phase",
            "b) Phase I parameter measurement phase",
            "c) Phase II parameter estimation phase",
            "d) Phase II parameter measurement phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The self starting approach uses regular process measurements for establishing and calibrating the cusum, and for process monitoring. Thus, this eliminates the phase I parameter estimation stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "The false alarm rate is _______ when small number of subgroups is used for the Shewhart control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreased",
            "b) Increased",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Changed randomly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of subgroups used in calculating the trial control limits for Shewhart control charts, impacts the false alarm rate of the chart. This rate is inflated when small number if subgroups is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to study the effect of the number of subgroups used for x bar and R chart control limit calculation on the false alarm rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hillier",
            "b) Robertson",
            "c) Wang",
            "d) Ricardo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The false alarm rate of the Shewhart control charts also depends over the number of subgroups used to construct the trial control limits. This was first studied by Hillier (1969)."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Which of these charts can be used instead of Shewhart control charts, in the case of small number of subgroups used to construct the charts, which were recommended by Quesenberry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R-charts",
            "b) C-charts",
            "c) P-charts",
            "d) Q-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Quesenberry recommended the Q charts to be used in the place of the Shewhart control charts, in the case of small subgroup number used to calculate the control limits. This was because small number of subgroups used with Shewhart control charts, increased their FAR."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which method was suggested by Del Castillo and Montgomery, to be used instead of the Q-chart to get better ARL performance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kalman Filter",
            "b) Acceptance Sampling",
            "c) Design of experiments",
            "d) Deleting some samples completely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Del Castillo and Montgomery found the ARL performance of the Q-charts very inadequate. So, they recommended the Kalman filter that has a better ARL performance than Q-chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a purpose for which control charts are produced for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control of the process",
            "b) Reduction of variability",
            "c) Increment of variability",
            "d) Continuous process improvement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The control charts are generally plotted for the main reasons like control of the process or statistical monitoring, reduction of variability, and continuous process improvement."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Which of these is used when the process has achieved high capability level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trial control limits",
            "b) Actual control limits",
            "c) Modified control limits",
            "d) Easy control limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At the stage, when the process has achieved a high level of capability, there is some relaxation provided to the level of the surveillance provided. This is generally done with modified control limits in the case of x charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a name of Modified control limits for x̅ charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance limits",
            "b) Reject limits",
            "c) Reserve limits",
            "d) Liquid limits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relaxation in the case of x charts in the case of high process capability is provided with the use of the modified limits. These are also called reject limits. "
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "Which of these is a method used when the process capability is quite high?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) Design of experiments",
            "c) Acceptance control charts",
            "d) Shewhart control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the process capability becomes very high, the relaxation of the level of surveillance is provided by using two methods; first is the reject limits, and the second is the acceptance control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Which of these does not say that the modified control limits must be applied?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cpk≫1",
            "b) Process spread is considerably small",
            "c) Natural variability becomes high",
            "d) Process capability becomes quite good"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modified control limits are used when the process capability is very high. The PCR Cpk≫1, very less process spread, and low natural variability indicate the high process capability. So, modified control charts are used in these conditions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "When the type I error is specified, which of these is correct expression for the UCL of the modified control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{Z_α}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "b) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z_α}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "c) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{Z_α}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "d) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z_α}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modified control charts are the alternatives of ordinary Shewhart control charts, when the process capability is high. These have UCL as,\n\\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z_α}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Which of these is a correct expression for the UCL of the modified control charts when the type I error is not specified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "b) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "c) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "d) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The UCL of the modified control charts can be done by both, specifying the type I error or by not specifying the type I error. When the type I error is not specified, the UCL is,\n\\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "When the type I error is not specified, the value of LCL of the modified control charts is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "b) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "c) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\) ",
            "d) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The LCL of the modified control chart also uses the type I error. If the type I error is not to be specified. Its value is written by the expression,\n\\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right) \\sigma \\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "____________ sigma limits are recommended for modified control charts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modified control charts are effective when the spread of process is quite less than the limits used. So 2-sigma limits are recommended for the modified control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Which of the hypothesis can be tested using the modified control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) μL ≤ μ ≤ μU",
            "b) μL ≤ μ",
            "c) μ ≤ μU",
            "d) μL = μ = μU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The modified control charts allow the mean shift between two particular mean values. This means that the hypothesis μL ≤ μ ≤ μU can be tested using the modified control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "To design a modified control chart, we must have a good estimate of _________ available.",
        "Options": [
            "a) μ",
            "b) σ",
            "c) μ2",
            "d) process variance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modified control chart limits are totally based upon the estimate of the process standard deviation. So, to design a modified control chart, we must have a good estimate of σ available."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "If process variability shifts, the modified control charts are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not appropriate",
            "b) Totally appropriate",
            "c) Good to use",
            "d) Perfect for the mapping the shifts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A modified control chart needs a good estimate of the process standard deviation. As the process standard deviation is depended upon the process variability, the modified control charts are not appropriate to use."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "If there is a chance of shifting of the process variability, which chart may be used with the modified control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) c-chart",
            "b) p-chart",
            "c) R-chart",
            "d) x̅ -chart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the process variability shifts can be monitored using a Shewhart R chart or an s-chart, if there is a chance of shifting of the process variability, they can be used in conjunction with modified control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "From which chart the initial estimate of the process variability is determined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R-chart",
            "b) c-chart",
            "c) p-chart",
            "d) Cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As R charts and s-charts are good ways to estimate the process standard deviation, hence the process variability too, they are used to determine the initial estimate of the process variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "When the type I error is specified, the LCL of the modified control chart is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "b) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{Z}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "c) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ+\\frac{Z}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "d) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the type I error is not specified, the value of the 100(1-δ) percentage point of the normal distribution Zδ is used. The LCL is,\n\\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_δ-\\frac{Z}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "The approach of using a x chart to monitor the fraction of nonconforming units or the fraction of the units exceeding the specifications, is called the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shewhart control charts",
            "b) Cusum charts",
            "c) EWMA charts",
            "d) Acceptance control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is an approach to using an x chart to monitor the fraction of nonconforming or defective units, or the fraction of the units exceeding the specifications, which is called Acceptance control chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to develop the acceptance control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Astern",
            "b) Roy",
            "c) Freund",
            "d) Crowder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first person, to develop a method to use the x chart to monitor the fraction of defective units, was Freund (1957). He first developed the technique of the acceptance control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "A modified control charts limit expression does not contain ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) δ",
            "b) σ",
            "c) μ",
            "d) α"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modified control charts was based on a specific sample size n, a process nonconforming δ, and type I error probability α. It does not depend on μ."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Which of the error probability does the acceptance control chart take into account?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I",
            "b) Type II",
            "c) Neither of the type I not the type II",
            "d) Both, type I and type II"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The acceptance control charts were first designed by Freund. These charts take both, the probability of type I error and the probability of type II error into account."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "How many approaches can be used to develop the acceptance control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The acceptance control charts can be designed by using two approaches. First uses the specified n, and a process fraction nonconforming γ that we would like to reject with probability 1-β. Another uses the values of n, δ and α."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "What is the UCL of the acceptance control chart when the sample size n, the fraction nonconforming γ are specified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "b) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_γ-\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "c) \\(UCL=USL+\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "d) \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_γ-\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Upper control limit of the acceptance control chart, when sample size n, and the fraction nonconforming for 1-β probability rejection are specified, is expressed as,\n\\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "What is the value of the LCL of the acceptance control chart when sample size n and the fraction nonconforming for 1-β probability of rejection are specified?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "b) \\(LCL=LSL-\\left(Z_γ-\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "c) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_γ-\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) ",
            "d) \\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LCL value for the acceptance control chart uses the value of lower specification limit instead of the USL. The LCL value, when n, and γ are specified to reject with 1-β probability are specified, is\n\\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "When n, γ, and β are specified, the values of control limits are between ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) μL  And μU",
            "b) LSL And μU",
            "c) μL  And USL",
            "d) μL  And LSL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that the control limits of an acceptance control chart are,\n\\(LCL=LSL+\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\); \\(UCL=USL-\\left(Z_γ+\\frac{Z_β}{\\sqrt{n}}\\right)\\) \nBy the above equations, we get the control limit values between μL  and μU."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "When the values of n, δ, and α, are specified, the LCL of the acceptance control charts, lie in between ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) μL  And USL",
            "b) μL  And LSL",
            "c) USL And μU",
            "d) LSL And μU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the values of n, β, and γ are specified, the control limits for an acceptance control chart lie between μL  and μU. But, when the values of n, δ, and α, are specified, the LCL lies in between μL  and LSL."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "When the values of δ and α are specified instead of the β and γ, what is the position of UCL of the acceptance control charts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between USL and μU",
            "b) Between LSL and μU",
            "c) Between μL and USL",
            "d) Between μL and LSL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of UCL lies between μL and μU when the sample size n, β and γ are specified, but when the values of δ and α are specified instead of β and γ, the UCL of acceptance control charts lies between the USL and μv."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "What is the expression for n which gives desired values of α, β, γ, and δ for any acceptance control chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α-Z_β}{Z_δ+Z_γ}\\right)^2\\) ",
            "b) \\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α+Z_β}{Z_δ+Z_γ}\\right)^2\\) ",
            "c) \\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α-Z_β}{Z_δ-Z_γ}\\right)^2\\) ",
            "d) \\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α+Z_β}{Z_δ-Z_γ}\\right)^2\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is possible to choose a sample size for an acceptance control chart so that the specified values of α, β, γ, and δ are obtained. The required sample size will be,\n\\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α+Z_β}{Z_δ+Z_γ}\\right)^2\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "if δ= 0.01, α=0.00135, γ=0.05, and β=0.2, what will be the sample size for the desired values of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) n=38",
            "b) n=2",
            "c) n=32",
            "d) n=45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that,\n\\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_α+Z_β}{Z_δ+Z_γ}\\right)^2\\) \nPutting the required values, we get,\n\\(n=\\left(\\frac{Z_{0.00135}+Z_{0.2}}{Z_{0.01}+Z_{0.05}}\\right)^2\\)=31.43≅32.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Modified control chart design is not based upon ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I error probability",
            "b) Sample size n",
            "c) Type II error probability",
            "d) Process fraction nonconforming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The modified control chart design includes the development of the control limits for it, which includes only the sample size n, the process fraction nonconforming δ, and the type I error probability."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "2-sigma limits are recommended for the modified control charts. Which of these is not one of the reasons for this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The spread must be low",
            "b) The limits must be greater than the spread",
            "c) Gives smaller β-risk",
            "d) Gives higher β-risk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 2-sigma limits are recommended for the modified control charts, because the spread of the process is quite low than the limits, plus it also gives smaller β-risk."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Which of these is a correct definition for an MSP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Process in which same value of data comes from several sources",
            "b) Process in which data at a point in time consisting of measurement from several sources",
            "c) Process in which many values of data come from single source",
            "d) Process in which data at a point in time consisting of measurement from single sources"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A MSP is defined as the process with data at a point in time, consisting of measurements from several different sources or streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "What does P stand for in MSP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point",
            "b) Pressurization",
            "c) Prices",
            "d) Process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The MSP is a process in which data at a particular instant of time, comes from several individual streams. It has a full form of Multiple Stream Process."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "When are the sources, or streams, in an MSP, considered to be identical?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the process is out-of-control",
            "b) When the process is in-control",
            "c) When the process is running",
            "d) The sources are never identical in any of the states of process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a Multiple Stream Process, when the process is in the state of statistical control, the sources or the streams, from which the data are obtained, are considered to be identical."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Each of the stream can _________ adjusted __________ in the case of an MSP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Never, either individually or in small groups",
            "b) Always, individually",
            "c) Always, either individually or in small groups",
            "d) Always, only in small groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In every multiple stream process, it is always a characteristic of it that, each of the stream from which the data is obtained, can be adjusted either individually, or in small groups."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "If the data of the streams of the MSP are all correlated (perfectly), what control procedure may be adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Different control chart for different stream",
            "b) One control chart for some streams and one for a group",
            "c) Different control charts for different groups of streams",
            "d) One control chart for the any stream of all streams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The above process can have different set of data from different streams at any instant of time, so it is an example of the Multiple Stream Process."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Which of these is a type of situation occurring when an assignable cause has come up in the case of MSP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The whole process is in control",
            "b) All streams are on-target",
            "c) All streams are off target",
            "d) Every stream is on-target"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the data of the MSP are all correlated perfectly, the control procedure, which may be adopted, can be to design one control chart for any one stream of all streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "When only the output of only one stream is off target we need to control _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The whole MSP",
            "b) Only that Process stream",
            "c) Every process steam",
            "d) Every process stream except the steam which has off target output"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are at least two cases of situations involving the occurrence of assignable causes in MSP: first when the output of one or a few streams is off-target, second, when the output of all streams has shifted off-target."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Which technique is used to monitor MSPs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cusum control charts",
            "b) EWMA charts",
            "c) Shewhart charts",
            "d) Group control charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the output of only one stream of the MSP is off-target, that means there is an assignable cause in it. So we need to control only that stream."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to discover the technique of GCC (Group Control Charts)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Freund",
            "b) Maxwell",
            "c) Boyd",
            "d) Montgomery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The MSP processes have different data obtained from many individual streams. The data from the group of streams are controlled using the technique of Group control charts."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Which of these is an assumed standard distribution for the quality characteristic data from different streams of MSP for construction of GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lognormal",
            "b) Normal",
            "c) Poisson",
            "d) Binomial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The MSP or the multiple stream processes are controlled using the technique of GCC. These charts were first introduced by Boyd in 1950."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an assumption made for the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same target value for all the streams",
            "b) Same inherent variability for all the streams",
            "c) All streams data are perfectly correlated",
            "d) Each stream data is based on the normal distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: While the constructing GCC for the MSPs, it is assumed that the data obtained from the streams of the MSP, is normally distributed. It is a standard assumed distribution for the data."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "If there are 6 streams of a process and sample size is 4, what is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 units individually from any 4 streams",
            "b) 4 units individually from all the 6 streams",
            "c) 10 units from any stream",
            "d) 4 units from any one stream"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the construction of GCC for the MSP, it is assumed that all the streams of the MSPs have same target value, and same inherent variability, and all the data is normally distributed."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "The upper control limits for the GCC will be ____________ for the x̅ chart.",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}+A_2 \\overline{R}\\) ",
            "b) UCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}-A_2 R\\) ",
            "c) UCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}-A_2 \\overline{R}\\) ",
            "d) UCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}+A_2 R\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The GCC are used to control the multiple stream processes. These control charts are having the upper control limits as,\nUCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}+A_2 \\overline{R}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "What is the value of the difference between the UCL and the LCL of x̅ chart of the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 3A2 R",
            "d) 2A2 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As we know that the control limits for the GCC are,\nUCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}+A_2 \\overline{R}\\); LCL=\\(\\bar{\\bar{x}}-A_2 \\overline{R}\\) \nSo the difference between the control limits of GCC will be 2A2 R\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "What is the value of the UCL of the R chart constructed for the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL = D4 R",
            "b) UCL = D3 R",
            "c) UCL = R ̅+ D3 R",
            "d) UCL = R ̅+ D4 R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The GCC is prepared with the same way as the simple x and R charts are constructed for individual process streams. The value of the UCL of the R chart of the GCC is,\nUCL=D4 R\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of the UCL to LCL of the same GCC R chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL/LCL=D2/D3",
            "b) UCL/LCL=D3/D4",
            "c) UCL/LCL=D4/D3",
            "d) UCL/LCL=D4/D2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that the values of the control limits of the R chart for the GCC are,\nUCL=D4 R ;LCL=D3 R\nSo their ratio will be,\nUCL/LCL=D4/D3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "If the sample size is 4, what will be the value of the upper control limit of the GCC R chart?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UCL=2.672R̅",
            "b) UCL=2.282R̅",
            "c) UCL=2.114R̅",
            "d) UCL=2.574R̅"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that, for sample size= 4, the value of D4=2.282. So putting it into the equation of the UCL of R chart of the GCC gives,\nUCL=2.282R\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "What will be the value of the LCL of the x chart of the GCC when the value of x =12, and the value of R̅= 0.1 and sample size = 4?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12.0729",
            "b) 12.9271",
            "c) 11.9271",
            "d) 11.0729"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that, for n=4, A2=0.0729 Putting the above data into the equation of the UCL of the x̅ chart of GCC, we get,\nUCL=12.0729."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "When the subgroup size is 4 for any process samples, what will be the value of the R chart LCL of the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that for n=4, D3 has the value of zero. Putting it into the equation of the LCL of the R chart for the GCC, gives us, LCL=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "In GCC we plot ___________ means observed at any time period.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only the maximum",
            "b) Only the minimum",
            "c) Mean of the",
            "d) Both, the maximum and the minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the GCC are used to control the process, we plot only the largest and the smallest of the s means observed at any time period on the x̅ chart. If they lie inside the control limits, so will others do."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "___________ range will be plotted on the R chart of the GCC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum",
            "b) Minimum",
            "c) Both the maximum and the minimum",
            "d) Neither the maximum nor the minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only the largest range is plotted on the range chart because if it will exceed the control limits, there is a possibility that other ranges will also do the same. The lower limit of the Range chart is mostly zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Each plotted point on the GCC is identified by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The mean value of the stream",
            "b) The stream that produced it",
            "c) The standard deviation of the stream",
            "d) The variance of the stream"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum and minimum means are plotted on the x̅ chart, and only the maximum range is plotted on the range chart while using the GCC. Each point on the GCC is identified by the stream that produced it."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "A MSP is out of control if a point on the GCC exceeds __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-sigma limit",
            "b) 2-sigma limit",
            "c) 1.5-sigma limit",
            "d) 1-sigma limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The GCC is used to control the MSP or the multiple stream processes. The data from the different streams is plotted on it, if any point on the GCC exceeds a 3-sigma limit, the process is out of control."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "What is the value of the one sided in-control ARL for the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r}{s-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^{2r}-1}{s+1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r+1}{s+1}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a process has s streams and r is the consecutive times a particular stream has given largest value, the one sided in-control ARL will be,\n\\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "If there are 6 streams of a MSP, and one of the streams has given 4 consecutive times the largest value, what will be the value of the one sided in-control ARL for this event?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200",
            "b) 400",
            "c) 259",
            "d) 421"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Given: s=6, r=4. We know that,\n\\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\) \nBy putting the values, we get, ARL(1)0=259."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Which of these is a suitable pair of s, r, while using the GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2, 6",
            "b) 3, 7",
            "c) 9, 2",
            "d) 6, 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ARL of the MSP depends on the value of the s and r of the process. So to choose r is in our hand. (3, 7) and (4, 6) are the most used pairs which give desired results. Others will give too many false alarms."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "The expected number of trials until r consecutive largest or smallest means come from the same stream, is called _________ of the MSP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARL",
            "b) ARL(1)0",
            "c) ARL(2)0",
            "d) Predicted ARL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two sided in-control ARL of any process or ARL(2)0 is defined as the expected number of trials until r consecutive largest, or r consecutive smallest means come from a particular stream of any MSP, while MSP is in control."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Who was the first person to find out the one sided in-control ARL for any event of consecutive largest values being obtained from a single process stream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bond",
            "b) Nelson",
            "c) Robertson",
            "d) Clarkes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The one sided in-control ARL for any GCC of any MSP was first explained by Nelson (1986). He expressed it as,\n\\(ARL(1)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\) \n"
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Who gave the Markov chain approach to compute the ARL(2)0?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brook and Evans",
            "b) Mortell",
            "c) Runger",
            "d) Nelson"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Markov Chain Approach was given by the pair of persons, Brook and Evans, in the year of 1972. This was used by Nelson and Stephenson (1996) to calculate the ARL(2)0."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Who was not one of the scientists who used the Markov chain approach to compute the two sided in-control ARL for any GCC of any MSP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mortell",
            "b) Robertson",
            "c) Runger",
            "d) Stephenson"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mortell and Runger (1995), and Nelson and Stephenson (1996) used the Markov chain approach of Brook and Evans (1972) to compute ARL(2)0."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Which of these is a lower bound on the ARL(2)0?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ARL(2)_0=2\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ARL(2)_0=\\frac{2(r-1)}{s^r-1}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ARL(2)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{s-1}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ARL(2)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{2(r-1)}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ARL(2)0 close form expression could not be evaluated. So Nelson and Stephenson give a lower bound on ARL(2)0 which is written as,\n\\(ARL(2)_0=\\frac{s^r-1}{2(r-1)}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which of these is one of the drawbacks of GCC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each stream does not need to be sampled at a time",
            "b) There is no information about nonextreme streams at each trial. Thus no past value related EWMA can be constructed",
            "c) It can’t be used for MSPs",
            "d) It is very easy to construct"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In GCC, there is no information about nonextreme streams at each trial. So, we can’t utilize past values to form an E.W.M.A. or a cusum statistic to improve on GCC performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "Dependent streams of an MSP are also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accuracy streams",
            "b) Cross Acceptance",
            "c) Cross-correlated",
            "d) Uncorrelated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Dependent streams of a multiple stream process are the streams that have their data related to each other. So these streams are also called cross-correlated streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "Which of these is the correct model proposed for MSP by Mortell and Runger to accommodate the practical case of the dependent streams?",
        "Options": [
            "a) xtjk = μ – At + ϵtjk",
            "b) xtjk = μ + At + ϵtjk",
            "c) xtjk = μ – At – ϵtjk",
            "d) xtjk = μ + At – ϵtjk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mortell and Runger (1995) proposed the following model for the MSP to accommodate the practical case of cross-correlated streams:\nxtjk = μ + At + ϵtjk\nHere cross-correlated streams have their data related to each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "What does the term xtjk correspond to in the model proposed by Mortell and Runger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) k Th measurement on the jTh stream at time t",
            "b) j Th measurement on the kTh stream at time t",
            "c) t Th measurement on the jTh stream at time k",
            "d) k Th measurement on the tTh stream at time j"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The model proposed by Mortell and Runger, to accommodate the case of cross-correlated stream data of MSP, is expressed as,\nxtjk = μ + At + ϵtjk\nHere the term xtjk corresponds to k Th measurement on the j Th stream at time t."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "The model given by Mortell and Runger represents two types of variability, σa2 accounting for the variance over time ___________ and σ2 accounting for the variation between the streams at specific time t.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Common to all streams",
            "b) Specific to one stream",
            "c) Specific to 2 streams",
            "d) Specific to a group of 3 streams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The MSP representation given by Mortell and Runger, has the total variation allocated into two sources, σa2 accounting for the variation over time common to all streams, and σ2 accounting for the variation between the streams at specific time t."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "What is the correct value of cross correlation given by the Mortell and Runger model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) \\(ρ=\\frac{2σ_a^2}{(σ_a^2+σ^2)}\\) ",
            "b) \\(ρ=\\frac{4σ_a^2}{(σ_a^2+σ^2)}\\) ",
            "c) \\(ρ=\\frac{σ_a^2}{(σ_a^2+σ^2)}\\) ",
            "d) \\(ρ=\\frac{2σ_a^2}{(σ_a^2-σ^2)}\\)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The MSP model was given by Mortell and Runger in the year of 1995. According to it, the value of the cross-correlation given by the model was expressed as,\n\\(ρ=\\frac{σ_a^2}{(σ_a^2+σ^2)}\\)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Mortell and Runger proposed monitoring the average at time t of the means across all the streams with _________ control chart to detect an overall assignable cause.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A cusum",
            "b) A EWMA",
            "c) A p-chart",
            "d) An individuals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mortell and Runger proposed the MSP model. They recommended using an Individuals Chart to compare the average at time t of the means across all streams, to find an assignable cause."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "A designed experiment is a test or series of tests in which ____________ changes are made to the input variables so that we may observe and identify corresponding changes in the output response.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Systematic",
            "b) Random",
            "c) Purposeful",
            "d) Non-purposeful"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A designed experiment is a series of test in which we change the input variables according to our choice to obtain a desired change in the output. These changes are perfectly purposeful."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "Which of these does not come into the general model of a process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input",
            "b) Controllable input factors",
            "c) Uncontrollable inputs factors",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The general model of process describes a process to which the input is provided in the presence of controllable factors and uncontrollable input factors, to get an output."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "The uncontrollable factors are the factor ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) That varies according to a normal distribution",
            "b) That does not vary at all",
            "c) That can be controlled by the user",
            "d) That cannot be changed according to the wish of the user"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are two types of factors present with a process input while running period of a process, the controllable, and the uncontrollable input factors. The factors, which can be changed according to user’s wish, are called the uncontrollable factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "The uncontrollable factors are also called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Designed factors",
            "b) Noise factors",
            "c) Acceptance factors",
            "d) Sound factors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The uncontrollable input factors are present when the process is running, and these factors can’t be varied according to the user’s wish. So these factors are also called the noise factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Which of these steps are not conducted when the design of experiment procedure is adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determining which variable is most influential to output",
            "b) Determining where to set the influential controllable factors so that output is near the nominal requirement",
            "c) Deleting the uncontrollable factors",
            "d) Determining where to set the influential controllable inputs so that the variability in the output is smallest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: While conducting the design of experiment procedure, we determine the influential factors which affect the output, vary the determined variables to get a required output value."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Experimental design methods are not used ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaluating the process capability",
            "b) In process development",
            "c) In process troubleshooting to improve process performance",
            "d) To obtain a process that is robust and insensitive to external sources of variability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The experimental design methods may be used either in process development or process troubleshooting to improve process performance, or to obtain a process that is robust or insensitive to external variability causes."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "The designed experiments are the part of ___________ step of DMAIC process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Define",
            "b) Measure",
            "c) Analyze",
            "d) Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major procedure parts, which are used in the designing of the experiments, are including the analysis of data and their improvement. So they are an integral part of the Analyze and Improve step of DMAIC process."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "The design of the experiment is used to determine the variables which are ___________ affecting the state of the process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The most",
            "b) The least",
            "c) Not",
            "d) Not changing or"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design of the experiment procedure is, determining the variables which most affect the process state and the output. We vary these variables to get a relationship between them and the output. "
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used to develop a new process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of experiments",
            "b) Acceptance sampling",
            "c) Control charts",
            "d) Histogram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design of the experiment procedure is an active statistical method, which can be used to control the values of the output, by obtaining the relationship between the input factors and output.  SO this can be used to design a new process with great process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "Which of these can be obtained by using the Experimental design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduced process capability",
            "b) Increased variability",
            "c) Increased cost",
            "d) Reduced distance from the nominal value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: With the use of the designed experiments, it is possible to increase the conformance of the product to the nominal value. So it can be used in designing a new product."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used in the DFSS activities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of experiments",
            "b) Histogram",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Stem and Leaf plot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The DFSS activities are said to be the Design for Six-sigma activities. The process of design of experiments is very useful in these activities."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "The DFSS stands for _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deleting for smaller standards",
            "b) Degradation for Six-sigma",
            "c) Design for six-sigma",
            "d) Development for six-sigma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DFSS stands for the Design for Six – Sigma activities. These activities are used to setup a process environment to get the six-sigma output."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used in the process of engineering design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of experiment",
            "b) Control charting",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) Cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SPC and experimental design of experiments are two very interrelated tools for process improvement and optimization. For example, if a low Cp process is in-control; Designed experiments could be used to increase process capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an application of experimental design in the field of the Engineering design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaluation and comparison of basic design configurations",
            "b) Evaluation of material alternatives",
            "c) Evaluation of key product design parameters that impact performance",
            "d) Evaluation of correct process to develop the product"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SPC is a passive statistical method as, in this procedure; we have to wait for the process information to come, to decide a step to control the process. However, if the process is in-control, we can’t do very much to reduce the variability."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "Use of designed experiments does not give _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved yield",
            "b) Reduced variability",
            "c) Closer conformance to the nominal",
            "d) Increased development time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design of experiments can also play a major role in engineering design activities, where new products are developed and existing ones are improved. So this is also used in DFSS activities."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Which of these is not a correct statement for Acceptance Sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concerned with inspection of products",
            "b) Concerned with decision making regarding products",
            "c) One of the oldest aspects of quality assurance",
            "d) One of the oldest aspects of quality control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acceptance sampling is a procedure used in quality assurance, which is concerned with inspection of manufactured products and the decision making regarding their state."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Which technique was used majorly in 1930s and 1940s for incoming or receiving inspection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SPC",
            "b) Histogram",
            "c) c-chart",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acceptance sampling was one of the major components of the field of statistical quality control, and was used primarily for incoming and receiving inspection, in the 1930s and 1940s."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Decision making regarding the lot disposition is sometimes called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lot rejection",
            "b) Lot acceptation",
            "c) Lot sentencing",
            "d) Lot wording"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Based on the acceptance sampling information, there is decision making regarding the lot information. This decision is either to accept or reject the lot. So it is called, the Lot Sentencing."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "Acceptance sampling can be used as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incoming inspection activity",
            "b) Outgoing inspection activity",
            "c) Both, incoming and outgoing inspection activity",
            "d) Neither incoming nor outgoing inspection activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Acceptance sampling is customarily thought to be the receiving or incoming inspection activity, but there are a few cases where it can be used as the outgoing inspection activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "The purpose of Acceptance sampling is to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sentence lots",
            "b) Estimate lot quality",
            "c) Estimate lot defectives",
            "d) Estimate lot conformity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Acceptance sampling procedure is necessarily a lot sentencing procedure. It cannot be used to estimate the lot quality or lot conformity to the standard specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Which of these procedures doesn’t provide a direct form of quality control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control charts",
            "b) Acceptance sampling",
            "c) Design of experiments",
            "d) Cusum charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Acceptance sampling procedure doesn’t provide a direct form of quality control. Acceptance sampling simply accepts and rejects lots; even if all lots are of same quality, some are accepted and some are not."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Which of these can be used as an audit tool to ensure the output of a process conforms to requirements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cusum charts",
            "b) EWMA charts",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) np-charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most effective use of acceptance sampling is not to “inspect quality into the product”, but rather as an audit tool to ensure that the output is similar to the required specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used in sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0% inspection",
            "b) 100% inspection",
            "c) Acceptance sampling",
            "d) 5% inspection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are generally three techniques used in the inspection of a lot; first is 0% inspection, second is 100% inspection, and third is acceptance sampling."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "The no-inspection alternative of sampling is used when ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The supplier’s process is so good that defective units are never encountered",
            "b) The supplier’s process is so bad that almost every unit is defective",
            "c) The component is extremely critical",
            "d) The component is moderately critical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the supplier’s process is so good that the defective units are never encountered. This shows that the supplier process capability is quite high."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "When is the 100% inspection done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The supplier’s process is so good that defective units are never encountered",
            "b) The supplier’s process is so bad that almost every unit is defective",
            "c) The component is extremely critical",
            "d) The component is moderately critical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The option of full inspection is chosen only when the product component is extremely critical, and can affect the whole product performance when used defective, e.g. aircraft nuts and bolts."
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "Acceptance sampling is not used when _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The test is destructive",
            "b) The cost of 100% inspection is quite high",
            "c) The supplier’s process capability is very high",
            "d) Although the supplier process is satisfactory but a program is needed for continuous monitoring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The acceptance sampling is used when the test is destructive, or the cost of 100% inspection is quite high, or when we need a continuous monitoring program."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "When the inspection error rate is sufficiently high, which of these is used as the sampling technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0% inspection",
            "b) 100% inspection",
            "c) 50% inspection",
            "d) Acceptance sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When there are many items to be inspected and the inspection error rate is sufficiently high, that 100% inspection might cause a high % of defective units to be passed, the procedure of acceptance sampling is adopted."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "Which of these is not used for a lot quality inspection purposes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EWMA Control chart",
            "b) Cusum chart",
            "c) Shewhart control charts",
            "d) Acceptance Sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Acceptance sampling procedure is used for decision making of either acceptance or rejection of a lot. It can’t be used as a lot quality estimators."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "Which of these is not an advantage of acceptance sampling over the 100% sampling plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less expensive",
            "b) Highly costly",
            "c) Applicable to destructive testing",
            "d) Lesser manpower is needed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As lesser number of units are checked while using the acceptance sampling plan instead of the 100% sampling plan, it is less expensive, applicable to destructive testing, and needs lesser manpower."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "Which of these is used when the test of the component is non-destructive, cheap and fast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0% inspection",
            "b) Acceptance sampling",
            "c) 100% sampling",
            "d) 50% sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As it will give better results in the case of 100% inspection when the test procedure of a component is non-destructive, cheap, and fast, the full lot sampling procedure is adopted."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "Which has the lowest number of manpower required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) 0% inspection",
            "c) 100% inspection",
            "d) 50% inspection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As 0% inspection does not need any equipment or personnel to check the product component supplied by the supplier, it has the lowest number of manpower required."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "Which has lesser probability of handling damage in between 100% inspection, and the acceptance sampling procedure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100% inspection",
            "b) Acceptance sampling",
            "c) Both have equal handling damage",
            "d) Can’t be predicted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As there is a lesser number of units used as samples in the acceptance sampling, there is less handling of the product, and hence reduced damage is there in the case of acceptance sampling."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "Which is the most expensive for the same testing process and product component to be tested?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) 100% sampling",
            "c) 0% sampling",
            "d) 50% sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As in the case of acceptance sampling, there are only a few units selected to be returned to the supplier, instead of returning the whole lot, it motivates the supplier for quality improvements."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "Which generates lesser information about the products and the manufacturing process, 100% sampling or Acceptance sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100% sampling",
            "b) Acceptance sampling",
            "c) Both generate equal amount of information",
            "d) Can’t be predicted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the 100% sampling procedure requires the checking of whole lot, it requires more resources to be devoted towards the sampling process. This makes it the most expensive procedure of all."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "Which has the most probability of rejecting the good lot?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) 100% sampling",
            "c) 0% sampling",
            "d) Can’t be predicted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As we there are lesser number of units as samples in the case of acceptance sampling rather than the 100% sampling procedure, it generates lesser information about the process and the product."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "Which of these requires planning and documentation of the sampling procedure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling",
            "b) 100% sampling",
            "c) 0% sampling",
            "d) 50% sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the 100% inspection accepts the lot after the inspection of whole lot, and there are rarely any defectives in the case of no-inspection, acceptance sampling is having the highest probability of rejecting the good lot."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "Which of these does not require sampling documentation at all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0% sampling",
            "b) 100% inspection",
            "c) Acceptance inspection",
            "d) 50% inspection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 100% sampling checks the whole lot, so it does not require any planning or documentation, whereas the acceptance sampling requires it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "Why are larger lots preferred over smaller lots in the case of acceptance sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because it’s economical",
            "b) Because it is costly",
            "c) Because it is time consuming",
            "d) Because it is complicated to sample larger lots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The larger lots are preferred over smaller lots as it saves time, and it is very easy to sample larger lots. The larger lots are also mostly homogeneous."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "Sequential sampling is an extension of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single sampling plan",
            "b) Double-sampling plan",
            "c) Multiple-sampling plan",
            "d) 0% sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the multiple-sampling plan is associated with the case when N numbers of samples are taken of n units, it has an intimate extension as Sequential sampling."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "Which is most economical of these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single sampling plan",
            "b) Double-sampling plan",
            "c) Multiple-sampling plan",
            "d) 100% sampling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As single sampling plan necessarily requires only one sample of n units, we may say that it is the most economical of all the acceptance sampling plans."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "How many sampling plans are there in the case of acceptance sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are only 3 sampling plans available in the case acceptance sampling, namely: single-sampling plan, double-sampling plan, and multiple-sampling plan."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "What is done in single sampling plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only one unit is checked",
            "b) Only the first lot is checked 100%",
            "c) Only n samples of 1 unit are checked",
            "d) Only one sample of n units is checked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Single-sampling plan is a lot sentencing procedure in which one sample of n units is selected and checked, at random from the lot. Lot is sentenced based upon only this sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "Double-sampling plan is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only 2 units are checked",
            "b) Only the first and last lot is checked 100%",
            "c) Only two samples of n units are checked (necessarily)",
            "d) Only two samples of n units are checked (conditionally)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the double-sampling plan, there are only two samples of n units are checked. The lot disposition is totally based upon the information from the first and second sample. There may not be two samples necessary to make decision."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "MIL STD 105E was first issued in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1949",
            "b) 1937",
            "c) 1945",
            "d) 1950"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standard sampling procedures for inspection by attributes were developed during World War II. So the MIL STD 105E was first issued in 1950."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "How many revisions have been done in the case of MIL STD 105E?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After the original version of MIL STD 105E been issued in 1950, there have been 4 revisions in it since then, and the latest version was issued in 1989."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "MIL STD 105E is a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptance sampling plan",
            "b) Acceptance sampling system",
            "c) Both Acceptance sampling plan and Acceptance sampling system",
            "d) Neither acceptance sampling plan nor system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The acceptance sampling scheme is a an overall strategy specifying the way in which the sampling plans are to be used. MIL STD 105E is a collection of acceptance sampling schemes. So it’s an acceptance sampling system."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "AQL is the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceptable Quality Level",
            "b) Acceptance Quality Level",
            "c) Associated Quality Level",
            "d) Assigned Quality level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main focal point of MIL STD 105E is AQL. The AQL stands for Acceptable Quality Level. This is the lowest quality of a product to be accepted."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "Which of these is a derivative civilian standard which is quite similar to MIL STD 105E?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ANSI/ASQC Z1.4",
            "b) ANSI/ASQC Z1.1",
            "c) ANSI/ASQC Z1.8",
            "d) ANSI/ASQC Z1.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is a derivative civilian standard originated from MIL STD 105E, ANSI/ASQC Z1.4. It is quite similar to the MIL STD 105E standard."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "Which of these ISO standards were adopted from MIL STD 105E?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISO 14000",
            "b) ISO 9000",
            "c) ISO 2859",
            "d) ISO 6000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MIL STD 105E was also adopted by the international organization for standards as ISO 2859. This is quite similar to ANSI/ASQC Z1.4. "
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "How many sample inspection levels are used in MIL STD 105E?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sample size used in MIL STD 105E is determined by lot size and by the choice of inspection levels. Three general levels are provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "Level I of inspection of MIL STD 105E requires about __________ amount inspection as Level II.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Half",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 3/4th"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are generally 3 levels of inspection in the case of MIL STD 105E. The level I requires about one-half the amount of inspection as Level II."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "Tightened inspection is instituted when at least ______ out of 5 consecutive lots have been rejected on original submission.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the normal inspection is in effect, tightened inspection is instituted when at least two of five consecutive lots have been rejected on original submission."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "When is the normal inspection to be instituted instead of tightened inspection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When 3 lots are rejected consecutively",
            "b) When 2 lots are accepted consecutively",
            "c) When 5 lots are rejected consecutively",
            "d) When 5 lots are accepted consecutively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When tightened inspection is in effect, normal inspection is instituted when five consecutive lots or batches are accepted on original inspection."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "When should the inspection with the provision of MIL STD 105E be terminated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When at least 10 consecutive lots remain on tightened inspection",
            "b) When at least 7 consecutive lots remain on normal inspection",
            "c) When at least 5 consecutive lots remain on tightened inspection",
            "d) When at least 10 consecutive lots remain on normal inspection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the event that ten consecutive lots remain on tightened inspection, inspection under the provision of MIL STD 105E should be terminated, and action should be taken at the supplier level to improve quality of submitted lots."
    }
]